So that we've gone through some one
dimensional summaries and now
I want to talk a little bit about some two
dimensional summaries.
Which include things like scatterplots,
but also you can, you can, you can kind of
group together lots of one dimensional
plots
to look at mult, two dimensional data.
And in particular Lattice and GGplot are
good at this.
so, we're going to look at scatterplots
smooth scatterplots and also,
and in, looking at two, greater than two
dimensions then
you have to get a little bit more clever
in terms of how
you present the data because one
possibility of course is actual
three-dimensional plots.
Where you might need you know, 3D gla-,
you know, a set of glasses to wear them.
These are not usually not that useful.
But I have seen them.
You can have spinning plots, which would
allow you
to kind of move the data around in three
dimensions.
These can be useful sometimes.
But often the most useful techniques are
to take a two
dimensional plots and kind of array them
or, or, or organize
them in a special way so that you can
look at a third variable or even a fourth
variable.
Uh,and so we'll talk a little bit about
these methods.
You can also use things like color and
size and
shape of, of plotting symbols to add
dimensions to your data.
So here's a way to look at two dimensional
data.
I've got in one dimension the east west
variable which is categorical.
And the other dimension I've got the pm2.5
variable.
And you can see that
I've got two box plots, one for east and
one for west.
And you can see that in the east and on
average the pm2.5
tends to be quite a bit higher than it is
in the west.
And and so that's a nice summary of, of
these two dimensions.
Now on the, in the west you see that on
average it tends to be a little bit lower,
but that, all of the extreme values of the
distribution so to speak are in the
western United States.
So the west has an average that's
lower but it has generally a larger
spread, so that's kind of interesting.
You can do a similar type of plot with,
with histograms instead, so now I've made
a histogram
on top which is the eastern counties, in
the
histogram on the bottom, which are the
western counties.
And you see the same basic features.
The western counties tend to be lower on
average,
but they have more extreme values that are
higher.
[COUGH] And the eastern counties are
generally higher on average, but they tend
to be but they don't have those kind of
very high, extreme values.
So of course one of the easier things to
do,
the most obvious things to do is a scatter
plot.
And here I'm plotting the latitude of the
monitor in the county versus
the pm2.5 just to see if there are any,
you know, north-south trends.
So as the latitude gets increases you're
going north.
And you can see that there aren't, these
are
there isn't a very strong particularly
strong north-south trend.
it does seem that the, the the pm2.5
tends to be higher in the middle
latitudes, and not
quite as high in the, in the upper and
lower latitudes.
I've added a d, a horizontal dashed line
here at 12, so
you can see roughly where the national
ambient air quality standard is.
And you can see that there are a number of
dots that
are above it, which are technically
speaking would be out of compliance.
So you can use color to add another
dimension.
So for example, if you remember there was
the latitude and the longitude and
the east-west variable in this dataset.
And so what I've got on the X-axis here is
the latitude, and the Y-axis, the pm2.5.
And then I've added the color.
So the, the, the red and black dots
indicate the east and west variable.
And so the the black dots are the east
counties and
the red, sorry the black circles are the
eastern counties and
the red circles are the western counties
so you can see,
now you can see we are looking at three
different variables here.
Another way to look at these variables is
to, just to make two plots.
So now I've got a panel of plots.
On the left hand, left hand side I've got
all the western counties and on the east,
on
the right hand side I've got all the
eastern
counties and I'm plotting them by latitude
and pm2.5.
So you can see that in the, in both cases
the
kind of higher pollution- counties tend to
be in the middle latitudes.
and,
and the north and south, northern and
southern latitudes tend to have generally
lower pollution.
This is both the case in the eastern
and western United States, so that's kind
of interesting.
So that's a quick summary of the, the,
kind
of plotting one dimensional and two
dimensional data in R.
and, and, even using color and multiple
panels for
looking at three dimensions that are
greater than two.
And in general these exploratory plots are
meant to be quick and dirty.
Notice I didn't spend any time working
with
the axes or you know, or setting the
labels.
and, and so I just kind of use the
defaults
and for the most part use the defaults in
R.
But the nice thing about exploratory plots
is they let you summarize the data and
highlight any you
know, broad features in the data which may
be of interest.
You can explore kind of basic questions
and hypotheses.
So remember, the question, the basic
question that we were looking at was,
you know, whe, are there any counties that
may be out of compliance?
And these plots may suggest useful
modeling strategies for the next step.
Which may be ana a more detailed analysis
or model fitting.
Lastly here's just a couple resources.
There's a nice website called the R Graph
Gallery which has
lots of examples of, of graphics and plots
made in R.
And of course the R Bloggers website will
often highlight lots of,
you know, plots that people have made and
have published to their blogs.
So take a look at those to get a sense of
what's possible.