This lecture's going to be about the
different counting systems in R.
And over time R has developed three core
plotting systems that vary from each other
in slightly different ways, and are useful
for achieving a few different goals.
I thought about, I thought I'd talk about
you know the three different systems.
What makes them different, and how they're
useful for various types of plots.
So the first system that I'll talk about
is, is, is usually referred to as the
base plotting system.
The base plotting system is the oldest
system in R.
It came with the original version of R.
and, the kind of conceptual model that it
uses
for building plots is a kind of artist's
palette model.
The idea is that you're kind of, you're,
you're kind of, you have a blank canvas.
And then you kind of add things to it one
by one.
So first you create the, a box with some,
maybe some points in it.
And then you add labels.
And then maybe you add a regression line
through it.
And then maybe you add titles, and, and,
axis ticks, and things like that.
And so you kind of piece together this
plot, one by one.
Every little piece of the plot takes
another
line of code, or another couple lines of
code.
And so you kind of add to it one by one.
So this is a kind of intuitive
model, because of, especially when you are
exploring
data because you may not know right away
what's the plot that you want to make.
And so maybe you'll just throw some points
on the canvas,
and then you'll add some colors, then
you'll add some labels,
and then eventually you'll piece it all
together.
And so this is all well and good as long
as you're kind
of keeping track of all the code that you
used to make the plot.
Then you can always reconstruct the plot
later.
And so the typical mode is for this type
of model is to
use the plot function so, there's always a
function that generates a plot.
And then and there are other functions
that so called, annotate the plot.
And these
are functions that add things like text,
lines, labels, things like that, to the
plot.
So the generation, and then there's the
annotation.
so, the nice thing about the system that's
very convenient, it's kind of intuitive.
I think many people think of building
plots in this manner.
But one of the, one of the drawbacks is
that you can't go back, so if
you, if you make a plot and you add
something to it, you can't take it away.
So it's kind of a it an increasing
process or a kind of cumulative process.
It's difficult to translate the a new plot
to another person.
So for example, if you develop a new kind
of plot it's, there's really no way to
translate
that, those ideas to another person,
because there's no
language, there's no kind of conceptual
language to use.
Every plot is just a, is just a bunch of R
code basically.
And so and so that's a little bit of a
drawback sometimes.
Another drawback
with the base plotting system is that
every, is because you have
so much control over the system, you
therefore have to control everything.
And therefore set everything very
carefully
if you don't like the default values.
So here's an example of a very simple base
plot.
You can see what a base plot looks like.
In this I've used a dataset called the
cars dataset which shows
the speed at which a car is moving and the
distance at
which it takes to bring, to bring the car
to a full stop.
And so you can see it's just a simple
scatter plot
with speed on the x axis and distance on
the y axis.
And so base plots look like this.
You could add a lot of other things.
You could add a title.
You could add labels in the plot.
You could make the points a different
color.
You can make them in different shapes.
There's all kinds of options that you can
choose
from and we'll talk about that in detail
later.
The second major plotting system
in R is called the Lattice System.
And this is implemented in the Lattice
package.
So this, the idea here is actually quite
different from the base plotting system.
Rather than piecing a plot together one by
one through a
series of commands, every plot is
constructed with a single function call.
And so the most commonly used function is
going to be the function xyplot.
But there are other functions like bwplot,
etc.
And so these functions basically construct
an entire plot
all at once.
And so therefore, you have to specify a
lot of information in the call to the
function, so that it has enough data to
build a plot and in an appropriate way.
The last system is most useful for
what are called, Co-plots or Conditioning
Plots.
Where you have, you want to look at the
relationship between,
let's say x and y as it changes across
levels of z.
And so, there, the, so you.
You're conditioning on different levels of
z and then you're
looking at x and y at each one of those
plots.
These are some times called panel plots.
because you're looking at the same thing
in every
panel but just for different levels of a
third variable.
And you can even combine variables so you
can look at multiple factors.
So the system is very useful, because you
can put a lot of plots on a
page very easily and very quickly as long
as you kind of follow this conditioning
model.
And then, furthermore, a lot of the
details that you would have
to specify directly in the base
plotting system are kind of calculated
automatically.
So things like the margins and a
lot of the spacings, are calculated
automatically as
long as you can accept the, those defaults
then most things will look quite nice.
So the downside of the Lattice system is
that sometimes it's, it's going to
be very awkward to specify an entire plot
using a single function call.
And sometimes you, it, it seems more
natural to kind of
piece things together one by one, like in
the Base system.
the, it's difficult to annotate a plot,
especially after the
plot's been generated, you can't add
anything to the plot.
It's done, and if you want to add
something,
you kind of have to reconstruct the
function call altogether.
There is a
way to annotate each of the individual
panels in
a Lattice plot, but it's a very tricky and
a not very intuitive use of functions like
panel
functions or things like subscripts, which
is not very intuitive.
And finally like I said you can't add to a
plot once it is done.
So here's a basic Lattice plot.
I use some data from the Lattice package.
And I basically plot life expectancy.
So the average life expectancy
in a state, versus the average per capita
income in that state.
This is data from the late 60s, early 70s
and, and then
I condition on the region of the country
that the state is in.
So the, the country is divided into four
regions.
And you can see it, look at the
relationship between income and
life expectancy by state within each, or
sorry, across states with, by region.
And so you can see that this type of panel
plot is very, is just a single function
call, in
Lattice.
I use the xy plot function and its
very simple to construct where something
like this.
And the base plotting system would involve
many different lines of code.
It would be much more involved.
So
the last system, plotting system that I
want to talk about is the ggplot2 system.
So this comes from the the grammar of
graphics which is
which lays out a set of principles for a
kind of plotting.
and, and it creates a kind of language
or grammar for describing different
aspects of a plot.
So it's based on a kind of well grounded
kind of rigorous theoretical system.
And it's implemented in R in the gg2,
ggplot2 package.
It kind of splits the difference between
the Lattice
and the base package, so it mixes ideas
from both.
So on the one hand you can kind of build
the plot incrementally
by adding things one by one, so that's
kind of like the base system.
On the other hand a lot of the kind
of aesthetic calculations are done
automatically without you having
to directly control, so things like
spacings and labels
are all kind of put in the right place.
So that's kind of like the Lattice system.
The ggplot2 system is very useful for
conditioning plots just like in Lattice.
And so you can make those kinds of panel
plots.
And the default of, the default so the
ggplot2 system has a lot of defaults.
And if you can accept them, it's quite
handy.
But you can always customize them if you
don't like what the defaults are.
And so if you know how to
use the Lattice system, you, the
transition
to ggplot2 is not too difficult, although
there
are some differences that are worth, that
I'll
talk about in in the lecture on ggplot.
So this a typical ggwhat default ggplot2
plot.
Here I, here I used the miles per gallon
data set from the ggplot2 package and I'm
plotting on
the x axis the kind of, the displacement
or
it's actually the size of the engine of a
car.
And the y axis
is the mileage on the highway for that
car.
And you can see that roughly as the size
of the engine is increasing, the mileage
is decreasing.
And so you can see that the ggplot2
package creates plots in a slightly
different aesthetic.
There's a kind of a gray background with
white grid lines.
The default is to use solid circles rather
than open circles.
And so you know, these things, you can
always customize if you want.
But the defaults are a little bit
different than the other two systems.
So, just to summarize there are three
basic plotting systems in r.
There's the base plotting system and there
is, which is kind of has this.
Artist palette model, where you kind of
add things one by one.
There's the Lattice system which you kind
of
specify an entire plot using a single
function call.
And then there's the ggplot2 system which
looks, which
kind of mixes the custom ideas from both
systems.
One of
the important things to know when you're
using
these three systems is that they can't be
interchanged.
You can't use them interchangeably.
So if you're going to use the base
plotting system, you
have to use all the functions associated
with that system.
Similarly if you're going to use the
ggplot2 system, you
have to use all the functions associated
with that system.
So you can't mix the functions between
systems.
Because otherwise you'll get, the plotting
will be confused.
And so so you typically have to choose a
system and kind of go with it
when you make your plots.
So those are the three main plotting
systems in R and then in,
in separate lectures, I'll cover in detail
how to use each one of them.