So just to illustrate how hierarchical
clustering works I'm
just going to simulate a very simple data
set here.
So I always set the seed so that the data
are reproduced here.
You can just run this code and simulate
the
data for yourself and take a look at it.
And so I plotted a total of 12 points here
and there are three clusters we can
see very clearly from the plot, and I've
labelled each of the points using the text
function.
So you can see, you know,
which point is which.
And so I'm going to run the hierarchical
clustering
algorithm to see how the points get merged
together.
So the first thing you need to do to run
an hierarchical
clustering algorithm is to calculate the
distance between all of the different
points.
So, you need to calculate all the pairwise
distances.
Between all the points so you can figure
out, you know, which two points are
closest together.
And so the easiest way to do this is with
the dist function
in R.
The dist function takes a matrix or
dataframe.
here, this dataframe has two columns, the
first column
is the x-coordinate, the second column is
the y-coordinate.
And then and so it's basically a matrix or
a data frame of points.
And what the dist function does is it
calculates the distance between all the
different rows in the data frame, and
it gives you what's called the distance
matrix.
Which gives you all the pairwise
distances.
And so if you call
dist without any other arguments it
defaults to the Euclidean distance metric
but
you can give it some other distance
metrics if you want as options.
And so here you.
Down below here you can see the most
of the distance matrix that is returned by
dist.
So you can see that it's a lower
triangular matrix.
And it gives you all the pair wise
distances.
So for example, the distances between
point one, and point two is 0.34.
Of course,
the actual distance here is meaningless, I
just.
because I just simulated the data, so the
numbers aren't particularly meaningful.
But you can see that some distances are
farther apart, some points are farther
apart than others.
So, for example, the distance between
point 3 and point 1 is
0.574 and the distance between point 3 and
point 2 is 0.24.
So, so the, so point 3 is closer to point
2 than it is to point 1.
And so you can kind of go down the line
like this and see
how far apart each of the various points
are from each other.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And so if you look, so the idea of the
hierarchical clustering algorithm here is
that we're going to take the two points
that
are closest to each other from the start.
And so that happens to be points five and
six,
and so I colored in here in the orange and
that idea is that the five points, five
ans six,
because of the closest together we're
going to group them together.
And merge them into a single cluster.
And so the idea is that here I'm going to
create a single point.
And then the little plus sign in the
middle
is kind of like the new location of this
merged set of points.
And so now instead I've kind of taken
these two points, taken these
two points, five and six, and merged them
into a single point.
So now one of that, the next two points
that are closes
together are 10 and 11 down, down the
lower right in the red.
And so I'm going to take those two points
and merge
them together and create a new kind of
super point.
That that
is kind, that will kind of filter out
through the algorithm.
And so we can keep go along like this.
And eventually we will get a little
picture here called the
Dendrogram, and it shows us how the
various points got clustered together.
So you can see on the very right side we,
there's, there's points five and six
that are grouped together, and then in the
middle there you got points ten and 11.
And so the farther down the tree.
In terms of the, the points
that are kind of further down the tree are
the ones that got clustered first.
And the points that are farther up kind of
got clustered later.
And and so you can see that there are the
the kind of points five
and six when they got merged together,
then
they got kind of clustered with point
seven.
And then when points five, six and seven,
they all merged together into a single
super point.
And they got merged with point 8 and
etcetera.
And so one of the things
about the dendrogram that's produced by
the clustering algorithm is that
it doesn't actually tell you how many
clusters there are, right?
You'll notice that there's no specific
label on the plot that
tells you there are two clusters or three
clusters or whatever.
And so, what you have to do is you have to
cut
this tree at a certain point to determine
how many clusters there are.
And so, for example, if I were to cut
it at the point that's labeled on the
y-axis, 2.0.
For example, if I were to draw a
horizontal line.
At, at the level of 2.0.
The question is, you know, how many, how
many branches would I come, would I run
into?
So if I were to draw a horizontal line at
2.0, I would run into about two branches.
And that would indicate to me that there
are roughly two clusters.
However, if I were to draw a horizontal
line at the, at
hte level of 1.0 there, I'm sorry, 1.0, at
the height of 1.0.
Then you draw a horizontal line and you'll
see you run into three branches there so
that
would tell you that there were roughly
three pluses.
So depending on where you want to draw
this, you want to draw this horizontal
line at the tree you'll get more or fewer
clusters in your clustering.
Of course, in the extreme case if you were
to top the, the, the tree all
the way at the bottom you just get
12 clusters, which equals the number of
data points.
And so you have to cut the tree at a place
that's, that's convenient for
you, convenient for you.
At this point we don't really have a rule
of where to cut it
but then once you do cut it then you can
get the cluster assignment.
From hierarchical clustering.