This lecture's going to be about some
basic principles for building analytic
graphics.
The basic goal is to provide some general
rules that one can follow when we're
building
analytic graphics from data, and we're
trying to
tell a story about what's happening in the
data.
I find these rules to be quite useful when
thinking
through building data graphics and they
apply to many different situations.
so, I've kind of cribbed these rules from,
a book by Edward Tuffey.
I'll give
the reference at the end of the lecture.
This is from his book, Beautiful Evidence,
where he,
where he kind of goes through a number of
principles,
and so, I'm going to talk through some of
these ideas
and kind, and kind of show them, in, in
context.
So, the first principle, that Tufty talks
about, is to show comparisons.
And this is a very basic idea in all of
science.
And the basic idea is that evidence for a
hyp, for a hypothesis or an idea about
the world, is always going to be relative
to another hypothesis, right?
So evidence is always relative.
And so, if you're comparing Hypothesis A,
there has to
be some alternative hypothesis that you're
going to compare it to.
And so, so whenever you hear a statement
or hear a a summary of
evidence, based on data you should always
be asking a question compared to what?
Alright, so here's a quick example.
The basic idea is that
we have a, a boxplot which looks at the
effect of an air cleaner
on the asthma symptoms of children who in
a certain, in a set of homes.
So the idea is that an air cleaner was
introduced
into a child's home, to reduce indoor air
pollution levels.
And we want to see if their asthma
symptoms are improving.
So the outcome is, it's what's called
symptom-free days.
So a higher number is better.
And here we can see that the group of
children that got the
air cleaner in their home had an increase
in their symptom-free days.
About, on the median increase was about
one symptom-free day over 2 weeks.
So that's a positive outcome, and we might
be inclined
to think that of course that the air
cleaner works.
But of course, the real question is
compared to what?
So what do we compare the air cleaner to?
And so the, the what we compare them to in
this case, is nothing.
So our, our control setting where
the air, or the control set of houses are
have
no air cleaner, and just kind of live
their daily lives.
So this was a randomized control trial
that looked
at installing an air cleaner in a child's
home.
And, and, and installing nothing in the
child's home.
And you can see now that in the control
homes,
the average change in the symptom free
case was about 0.
So there's really no change.
And then the average change in the air
cleaner
homes was about 1 symptom free day for, 2
weeks.
And so, just now you can
say okay, well relative to doing nothing,
the air cleaner is actually
a little bit better at showing an
improvement in the child's symptoms.
So it's always important to show a
comparison in a plot.
So that you can, you can have a basis to,
to compare what you're
showing and, c, so you can compare
the evidence to, between 2 different
hypothesis.
The 2nd basic principle, is to show
causality or mechanism or,
to, to make an explanation and to s, to
kind of show what's going on, show some
systematic structure.
So I mean, the, the use of the
word causality here is not supposed to be
formal.
But rather, is just to show kind of what
you believe, and how you believe the world
works, right.
So you need to be able to show what, how
you believe the system is kind of
operating, so to speak.
And so so what's the causal framework for
thinking
about the question that you're kind of
interested in?
And so if I might extend the
example from the previous slide,
previously we saw that
if you install an air cleaner in a child's
home,
that on average, they're going to
experience a one symptom-free
day increase, so a better outcome in their
asthma symptoms.
Now, we might ask, okay, well why does
that occur?
Why is it that installing an air
cleaner in a child's home, improves their
symptoms?
Well, of course, we hypothesize that the
air cleaner is cleaning the air.
It's removing particulate matter from the
air, and
so this particulate matter that's not,
that's being removed, is no longer
going in the child's lungs, and no longer
triggering their asthma symptoms.
So that's kind of how we believe things
work.
And so we can show a plot, that might
corroborate that evidence.
And so we can show another plot, which has
the symptom free days on
the left hand side, and then the
particulate matter, on the right hand
side.
So now we can see what was the effect of
the air cleaner on the, on the particulate
matter levels
inside the child's home?
And you can see that for the control
group,
there was basically no change in the
particulate matter levels.
Maybe in the slight increase, in the, in
the levels.
But there was a pretty, substantial
decrease in particulate matter levels.
For the group of homes that got the air
cleaner.
So now we can see that not only did a
child's symptom free
days increase when they got the air
cleaner, that they're that they're indoor
air particulate matter levels decreased,
also when
they got the air cleaner on average.
So, we can think about, you know, what is
the explanation for,
you know, why the the air cleaner seems to
improve symptoms in children.
And we can, and we can show, using the
data that
we observed, that it does seem to decrease
their particulate matter levels.
Now, of course, to really confirm that
this
hypothesis that the air cleaner operates
through, by reducing
PM, we'd have to do a lot, a
little bit more investigation and perhaps
more experimentation.
But this graphic kind of suggests a
possible explanation.
The third principle that that [INAUDIBLE]
talks about is to show multivariate data.
And the basic this rule can be boiled down
to
show as much data on a single plot as you
can.
And the reason is because, data are, the
world is
inherently multivariate, there's lots of
things going on all the time.
And if you just plot 2 variables, or maybe
even 3 variables.
It's not going to show the real picture of
what's happening in the world.
So if you can, you can integrate, if you
put
a lot of data on a plot, then you'll be
able to tell a much richer story.
So here is an example of a plot which is
another air pollution
example, but now we're, this a, a, if data
comes from outdoor air pollution.
So on the X axis we have, particulate
matter less than 10
microns in aerodynamic diameter, the
concentrations of those, from day to day.
So, every circle on this plot represents a
daily concentration.
And on the y axis, we have
the daily mortality in New York City.
This is for the time period 1987 to, 2000.
And you can see that overall, when, there
seems to be
a night-, a slightly negative association
between PM 10 levels and mortality.
Cause you can see that the regression line
that I put through there, is slightly
downwards sloping.
So that seems interesting, cause you
might,
one might hypothesis that higher air
pollution
levels might be associated with higher
mortality, not lower mortality.
So but you can look at other variables.
So there's not just air pollution and
mortality that
is kind of, kind of, that is of interest
here.
There are other variables that may be of
interest.
And may kind of be part of the system, and
may confound this relationship.
So, one of the things that we can look at
is see, well, how does this relationship
change across different seasons.
So if you look at, you know,
particulate matter and mor-, and mortality
in winter,
spring, summer, and fall, what does that
look like?
So, we can make a, a different plot to
show that relationship.
And this is the plot that we can make.
So this plot shows the relationship
between pm10 and mortality.
So, it's the same plot as we saw as we
showed
on the previous slide, but it's split
across the different seasons.
So we see it separately for winter,
spring, summer, and fall.
And we can see that in each plot, the
relationship is actually
now slightly positive.
So within each season, the relationship
between PM and mortality is
positive, but if you look overall, the
relationship appears to be negative.
So this is an example of Simpson's
Paradox.
If you may have heard it.
But the basic idea is that the season in
which we look
at the relationship, is confounding the
relationship between PM 10 and mortality.
And so when we look across with with the
[INAUDIBLE]
we look at the relationship within each
season it changes.
So it's important to show as many
variables as is reasonable at a given
time,
so that you can sh, get a clear picture of
the relationships in your data.
So the fourth principle is to integrate.
The evidence that you have.
And, and the basic idea here is that you
want to use as, as
many different modes of evidence, or as,
or displaying evidence as you can.
And so there's no reason to say if you're
just, if you
have a tool that makes a plot, to only
show a plot.
Or if you only have the ability to make a
table, to only show a table.
You should be able to combine different
modes
of evidence into a single presentation,
to, to make
edit, to make your graphic or whatever
display
that you're making as information rich as
possible.
And so, the idea is not, is not to let the
tools
that you use to drive the kinds of plot
that you make.
You should make a plot that you want to
make,
and not just let the tools do the
thinking.
And so what, that's one of the nice
advantages
of a system like R, because the, the tools
are
very flexible in R, and you can make all
kinds of customized plots to show the data
and to
kind of integrate different modes of
evidence.
So this is just one very quick example
from a published paper.
In the Journal of the American Medical
Association, looking at
the relationship between coarse
particulate
matter and hospitalizations in the
elderly.
And the basic idea is the details of this
plot are
not particularly important, but I just
wanted to show that they're,
there are kind of point estimates here,
which are in the
solid circles, and then there's confidence
intervals indicated by the lines
going through the confident, through the
solid circles.
But then on the right hand side here you
see this
label called posterior probability that
the relative risk is created in 0.
And so this is a measure of the strength
of the evidence
that the, the kind of the association
between coarse particulate
matter, and, and hospitalizations is, is,
in fact, different from 0.
And so, so here, we integrate, the, the,
kind
of, the point estimates as, as dots and
lines.
Then we also have texts on the right which
also, it shows another piece of
evidence, which is kind of the strength of
that evidence, as encoded by the posterior
probability.
So you can use these kinds of tools to put
lots of
information on your plots.
And now, I have to resort to putting
diff-, putting information
in different places where they may be
difficult to track down.
The fifth principle is to det-, to
describe and document the evidence
that you present, with using labels and
sources and, and whatever, and, and,
and in particular, if you're going to be
making a plot with, a system
like R, it's important to preserve the
computer code that made the plot.
So the idea is that you want to lend
some credibility to the evidence that you
present.
So, sources of where the data came from
that's very
important and how you made the plot is
also important.
So that's a very basic principle and it's
important
for your credibility.
The very last principle of course is that,
content is king, so if you don't have
an interesting story to tell, then there's
no
amount of presentation that will make it
interesting.
So when, when you're making plots, when
you're making figures, and you're making
graphs, the first thing about what's the
content that you're trying to present?
What's the story you're trying to tell?
What's the data that you have?
And then think about well what's the best
way to present that?
How am I going to present it?
And what is it
going to look like?
Because if you don't have very good
content, then there's
really not much you're going to be able to
do beyond that.
So just to quickly summarize the, the
6 basic principles are, first show
comparisons.
Always show something relative to
something else.
Show causality or mechanism, or explain at
least
try to explain how the system is working.
How the world is working, at least
according to your ideas.
The third is to show multivariate data.
So always try to show
more than 2 variables, because the world
is complex and involve many variables.
Principle number 4 is integrate multiple
modes of evidence.
So that you can use things like tables and
plots and texts all together.
You don't have to keep them separate, if
you don't want to.
Describe and document your evidence.
Always have sources and, and source code.
And, and, to lend credibility to your
plots.
And finally, always remember that the
story that you tell
and the data that you use are the most
important
elements of any graphic.
So just the, the P reference that I would
use for this presentation is, Edward
Tufte's book, Beautiful Evidence.
And you can, you can read about it at his
website which I point to here.
It's an excellent book, I highly recommend
it.
So, so that's some, these are some basic
principles about building analytic
graphics, and then we're,
and, in, and in future lectures we'll talk
about how to do that using the various
plotting systems in R.