So, I'm going to start with a little
example data set here.
This data set comes with the GGplot two
package.
You can always just load it up after you
install the packages.
After you install the packages, this is
the mpg data set.
It looks at miles per gallon for a variety
of different types of cars.
You can see in this data set from the stir
that I did that there's 234 observations.
There's 234 different types of cars and
there are 11 variables that are measured.
In particular, I'm going to be looking at
the displacement variable,
which is an an indicator of how large the
engine is.
So this is the displ variable.
We're going to be looking at the number of
cylinders
and the sorry, it's the, and the, sorry,
we're going to
look at the the highway mileage so the hwy
variable and then we're going to look at
the drv variable.
Which is the whether, what kind of drive
is it a
four wheel drive, a front wheel drive, or
a rear wheel drive.
So notice how the factors here are labeled
appropriately.
So the, for example, the manufacturer
variable is labeled
by the manufacturer of the car, Audi,
Chevrolet, etc.
And then the, the drv variable, which
indicates the type, the drive, is
indicated with a four for four-wheel
drive,
f for front-wheel, and r for rear-wheel.
So a very simple plot you can make I call
this
the hello world for GGplot is the call to
q plot function.
On the x-axis I had this displacement
variable which is a kind
of engine size variable and on the y-axis
I got the highway mileage.
You can see that I specify the data frame
with the data arguments.
So I say data equals mpg so that the data
comes from this mpg data frame.
And so that's very simple.
You can see that the plot that it makes
is, is looks very different from the
traditional base plot.
You can see that it's kind of a
gray background and there's white grid
lines behind it.
The points are closed solid circles,
rather than the kind
of more typical open circles from the base
plotting system.
And then their labels on the x and y axis.
One of the things we can do is modify some
of the, the aesthetics.
So we can highlight different subgroups of
the data so
one of the subgroups can be determined by
you know.
So there's lots of different cars here,
some of them are front wheel drive,
some of them are rear wheel drive and some
of them were four wheel drives.
So, we can separate those observations out
by
con-, by looking at the DRV, the drive
variable.
And so I've I've specified the x and y
coordinates, just like before.
I specified the data frame, just like
before.
And I, and then, another argument I have
is the color variable.
And I'm going to say that the color is
mapped to this drive variable DRV.
And the, all that says is that the
different levels of the drive variable
will be each
assigned a different color and notice I
don't
specify what those colors are they are
specified automatically.
So you can see on this new plot here that
the the
front-wheel drive cars are in green, the
rear-wheel drive cars are in blue,
and the four-wheel drive cars are in red.
And so you can see that most, the
front-wheel drives tend to have the
highest mileage, the
four-wheel drive tends to have the lowest
mileage
and the rear-wheel drive is something in
the middle.
And I noticed that the legend was placed
on the plot
automatically, and the color coding, the
different levels of the factor variable.
I didn't have to do anything special.
And so its very nicely, kind of, organized
and thought out, and you
don't have to do anything.
Everything's done automatically.
Another thing that you sometimes want to
add is a statistic,
so a statistic is just some summary of the
data.
And so the summary that we've chosen to
add here is a
kind of smoother or the more technical
name is called low S.
And and it smooths the data so you can see
the kind of overall trend in the data set.
And you can see that I do this by adding
the geom argument and and
the geom's that I want to put on this plot
are those there's two types.
One is I want to add the plot the
points themselves so I can see the data.
And then I want to add this smooth geom
and the smooth is this blue line that goes
across and the con 95% confidence
intervals for the
line are indicated by the gray kind of
zone.
A hit, you can make a histogram with
the qplot function, by only specifying the
single variables.
So here I only specify the highway
variable.
And it shows me the highway mileage for
all the cars in the data set.
But I get, again I like to kind of
speci, separate out which, which cars are
four wheels drives.
Which cars are front wheel drive,
etcetera.
So again, I specify, instead of a color
argument, I specify the fill argument.
Which says that the different hist
elements
of the histogram are going to be filled
with
different colors based on what drive they
are.
So here, you can see a similar picture
that
you saw before, which is that the four
wheel
drive vehicles tended to have the lowest
mileage, and
the front wheel drive tended to have the
highest mileage.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Another feature of GGplot are, is called
facets and facets are like panels in
lattice.
The idea is that you can, you can create
separate plots
which indicate again subsets of your data,
indicated by a factor variable.
And you can make a panel of plots to look
at separate subsets
together rather, so one option would be to
say, to color code the subsets.
According to different colors like we did
before.
But if that, if you have a lot of data
points, that can be tricky to
look at and then all the colors might
overlap.
And it may be difficult to see the
separate groups.
So, an easier way to do that is to say
split
out the three groups into separate panels
and make three separate plots.
So that's what we've done here.
On the left side here, I've got three
different
scatter plots of the displacement versus
the highway mileage.
And then I've split it up by the
different four, drives, so
four-wheel-drive from in rear.
And so you the relationship for these
three subgroups
and, it's just a different way to look at
the data rather than say, color coding the
three groups.
And I specify this with the facets
variable.
So I can and the facets variable takes
a, a format that's basically, there's a
variable on
the left hand side and a variable on the
right hand side, and they're separated by
a tilde.
And so if you, the variable on the
right hand side determines the columns of
the panels.
And the variable on the left hand side
indicates
the rows of this kind of matrix here.
Now notice that in the left plot which is
outlined by the red box, I don't have, is
only
one row and so there's no variable that
indicates
how, how many rows there should be in this
plot.
And so that's why in the facets argument I
have a dot on the left hand side.
On the right hand side I've got the DRV
variable,
which indicates that the, that should
indicate how many columns.
Now because there are three levels to this
DRV variable there are going to be three
columns.
And, and so since there is only one row,
there
is going to be three plots all in a row
like that.
On the right-hand side in this plot that's
outlined with the blue box, I've got three
histograms.
And notice that I put the DRV variable
on the left-hand side of the facets
argument now.
So that indicates that I want three
separate rows.
Because there's nothing on the right-hand
side of the tilde, I have no columns.
So I just have the one column, no extra
columns.
I just have the one column for the three
plots.
And now I've got the three histograms.
You can see, you can look at the highway
mileage.
Divided up by the three groups.
So that's a quick example using the qplot
function
using some of the data is the GGplot
package.
I wanted to go through a slightly more
involved example
using the data set that comes from here
from John Hopkins.
So this comes from the Mouse Allergen and
Asthma Cohort Study which is
a study conducted here at Johns Hopkins of
Baltimore children, aged five to 17.
These children all had persistent asthma
with an exacerbation
in the past year.
And the overall goal of the study was to
study
the indoor environment, so the home
environment of these children.
And its relationship with asthma
morbidity.
So if you're interested in kind of seeing
what a little bit of
this was about, we have a recent
publication, and I give the link here.
So here's a little bit of the MAACS data.
You can see that, there's the, there are
750 observations, and I've
just plot, I've just put five variables
here for the sake of demonstration.
One is the ID variable.
The second one is the eno, so the, so
exhaled nitric oxide is is a measurement
that we take.
Roughly corresponds to a level of
pulmonary inflammations.
So a large value of ENO indicates some
pulmonary inflammation.
The second variable that I want to
highlight is fine particulate matter so
this is
this is dust that is less that 2.5 microns
in diameter, so its very fine dust.
The last variable that I want to point out
here is these mouse positive variables.
So, this, this is a skin test that the,
that the, that the children do.
Which indicate, well, and it tells us if
they're allergic to mouse allergen or not.
So so here's the basic histogram of
exhaled nitric oxide.
So this is the log of exhaled nitric
oxide.
And you can see it has kind of an
interesting shape.
There's, there's, kind of, it looks like
there's two peaks, or maybe even
three peaks there, as you make a, as you
look across the histogram.
At the bottom of the plot here, I've got
the code
that makes this histogram, in case you're
wondering how you make it.
And so I use the qplot function to make
the histogram.
I just, so now I've made another
histogram, but I've color
coded the different groups.
And the groups are determined by this
mouse
positive variable, so I've separated out
the people
who are kind of pos, or sensitized to
mouse allergen, and the people who are not
sensitized.
So the people, you can imagine, you can
think of the, the children that are
Sensitized to mouse allergen are, are, are
more allergic and they may be more
sensitive.
They have more sensitive to a variety of
environmental triggers.
And so you can see that roughly from the
date of the blue
bars are, are slightly higher, and the red
bars tend to be slightly lower.
So, that suggests that the, the children
that are mouse
mouse positive or have slightly higher
pulmonary inflammation on average.
Another way to visualize this data is to
kind of do a density smooth.
So, you can see that on the left hand side
I
ju-, I, I, I add the geom density to this
log(eno) variable.
You can see that there are
clearly, there are at least two peaks from
the density smooth.
And if you separate those peaks out on the
right hand side.
I say, you notice I say color equals
mo-pas.
So that's the, I split out the color
by whether they're positive to mouse
allergen or not.
And you can see that the each, that the
two peaks
roughly correspond to whether they're
allergic to mouse allergen or not.
And so this is a nice way to visualize
this kind of one dimensional data.
Now if you
want to look at some scatter plots I want
to see whether exhaled
nitric oxide is related to the level of
fine particulate matter in the home.
So I'm going to look at PM2.5 and eno.
And the very left most side here.
You can see I just make a simple scatter
plot
of log eno and log pm 2.5 and it's eno
is a little difficult to see exactly what
the relationship
might be, but we'll kind of go piece by
piece here.
In the middle plot here
I've, I made the same scatter plot but
I've separated the two groups of the mouse
positive
and the mouse and the non, so the
non-allergic
and the allergic children are separated by
different shapes.
So here I specified the shape argument.
And, and I assigned the shape to be this
mouse positive variable.
And now it's not really easy to see the
two groups here.
So that there's one group that's triangles
and another group that's circles.
And because of the overlapping
of the points, it's a little hard to see.
So in the right hand side here, I, instead
of separating the two groups by shape, I
separated
them by color, and it's a little bit
easier
to see the two different groups in this
plot now.
One of the things you can do is to
smooth the relationship between log PM 2.5
and log eNO.
Now I want to look at how this
relationship is different in the, in the
two groups.
So I, I set the genome to be a point and a
smooth.
And in, and rather than use low S I'm just
going
to say, I'm just going to use a standard
linear regression model.
So I say method equals lm.
And that way I can look at the linear
relationship between pm2.5 and
eNO by whether they're allergic to mouse
or not.
And you can see that roughly speaking in
the in the
non-allergic children there were some of
these, amongst the red dots, here.
There's a little bit of a negative
relationship, but it's not
particularly strong, if you factor in,
kind of, the confidence intervals, there.
And within the allergic children, there
appears to
be an increasing relationship between PM
2.5 and eNO.
so, another
way to look at this same data is to split
it out, with a spli, with, with facets.
So rather than overlapping the two groups,
and,
and then color-coding them separately, I
can just
split them out into two a plots using
the facets variable so, I'm sorry, the
facets argument.
So here I, I specify the facets argument
and I say I want two columns designated
by the two mouse positive variables, no
and yes and so it will be two columns.
And you see, and then I smooth the
relationship within Each panel.
And you can see that again it's the same
story.
Amongst the negative, the mouse negative
children, there's a small decreasing
relationship.
And amounts, amongst the mouse positive
variable children, there's a slight
increasing relationship.
So, the qplot function is a, is a simple
function that you can use to make very
quick plots.
And it's analogous to the plot function.
So you specify x y, you specify your data,
and
then there's a variety of options that you
can choose.
And there a lot of nice built in features.
So if you want to color code subsets of
the data, that's very easy to do.
If you want to split out different panels,
that's
also very easy to do with the facets.
You can choose different plotting symbols
with the shape argument.
And so, it has it has a
lot of nice things that you can do very
quickly that are still very powerful.
The syntax of the function is somewhere in
between, kind of the base plotting and
lattice package.
I think there are the, the graphics that
are produced
very nice, if you like that the type of
design.
But if you don't, there are features that
you don't
like or you don't like the design of this
particular function.
It's a little bit tricky to kind of modify
the qplot function to suit your needs.
If you want to do kind of a lower, or a
lower level customization of different
aspects of the plot.
You really have to go into the, kind of
the guts of the
GGplot function and that's something that
I'll talk about in the next lecture.