Hi, everyone, welcome to Exploratory Data
Analysis.
This is the fourth class in the Data
Science Specialization.
So at this point you should have, you
should be familiar
with all the kind of basic tools in the
data scientist's toolbox.
You should you know, be familiar at least
with the kind of the basics of R
programming in terms of writing functions
and writing
writing kind of basic, kind of basic
operations on data.
And we should have covered the kind of the
aspects getting data
from the internet and through various APIs
and kind of processing data.
So now you've got, you can imagine, you
have got your data set.
It's been through a variety of processing
steps and it's time
to just kind of look at and see what's
going on, right?
So you want, so the purpose of this class
is to look at your data, get
a sense of what's happening and what are
the kinds of plots that you want to make.
One of the types ways that you can explore
the data without kind of having
a precise or specific model about, you
know,
what's supposed to be going on in there.
So this is before we do modelling, before
we
do prediction, before we do any sort of
inference.
And so we're going to talk about the
plotting systems in R.
We're kind, talked about kind of basic
principals about making analytic graphics
and I'll show some case studies of
exploratory data analysis just so
you can get of sense of kind of how this
type, how
this kind of thing would work in a, in the
real world.
So I hope you enjoy it.
I look forward to seeing you in the class.
And I think this will set you up really
well, for the later classes in the data
science specialization.