So here I started up Bar, and I'm just
going to do a little bit of
simple plotting just to kind show what
the,
the basics are of the the plotting
options.
So, I'm going to simulate a little, a
little bit
of data here just so I can make a plot.
A hundred normal random variables here.
And I'm going to call Hist to make a
histogram, of the plot.
So the first thing you'll notice when I
call Hist, is that a plot window opens up.
So let me just move it over here.
And the
histogram of the data is shown.
And so you can see that even though I
didn't specify any arguments in
the Hist besides the data themselves a
number of things appear on the plot.
Without my specifying them.
So for example, there's a title here.
Then there's an x label here, so here the
label is
just x because that's what the object
called when I passed hist.
The label here is frequency which is the
default for histogram so it tells you the
number of elements
within this range, so for example, between
minus one and zero.
There's going to, there's a little over
thirty elements of the vector in that
range, and you can see that the histogram
is roughly like a normal distribution.
So let me just generate some more data
here.
So we can make a little scatter plots I'm
going to generate
some more data.
And I'll plot xy here.
So now, the plotting window is already
open, so when
I call plot it's not going to launch a new
plotting window.
It's going to send the plot to the current
plotting window, which is this one here.
So, I've speci-, I've called plot and you
can see the mixed scatter plot of the
points.
The default plotting symbol here is an
open circle.
You can see.
And again
the label, I didn't specify besides x and
y but
that a number of things have occured in
the plot.
For example the label here is specified as
x on the
x-axis, and the label on the y-axis is
specified as y.
If I had changed the name of the objects,
so let's
say I say [UNKNOWN] here, and I plot x and
z.
Well the plot looks different because the
data are different but you
can see that the label here turned, turned
to Z because that's
the name of the object.
So let me just go back to x and y.
And so a number of things on the plotting
region are important for example the
margins here are.
There's four margins here, one for each
side.
This is side one.
This is side two.
This is side three, and this is side four
over here.
And you can see that the margin for the
bottom is
is, is the largest.
So there's, there's five lines of margin
text available.
On the side two, there's four lines of
margin text available.
On the top, there's also four, so, side
three.
And on the right side, side four, there's
the smallest amount of a margin text
available.
So you can adjust that using the Mar
function.
So for example, I can just say par, and
then I say Mar equals, let's say
I want two on every side.
So two, two, two, two.
Excuse me.
And then I can plot again.
And you can see that now the plot the
margins have gotten a
lot smaller and the plot kind of extends
farther out into the window.
But the problem you can see is that on the
x and the y axis, I lost my label.
And so even though I have the tick marks
there I don't have my x and y labels.
So we probably
need to make them a little bit bigger than
that.
So maybe I'll say four, four.
Like that.
So now if I plot again now you can see
there's
just enough room for the x and the y label
there.
I'm just going to demo a couple of the
other options that
may be of interest to you as you're cri,
constructing your plot.
So first is the plotting symbol I can say
plot, x,y then PCH equals, say 20.
That gives me a solid circle here.
I want a slightly solid symbol here, I
would say PCH equals 19.
Or I can, you know, specify PCH equals
two, that gives me
triangles, three gives me little plus
signs, four gives me x's, etcetera.
So you can see, so you can see that
there's many
different plotting symbols to try, you
might be wondering how I
know all the numbers for these plotting
symbols, well, it just
comes after many years of use, I've
memorize most of them all.
But, of course, if you haven't memorized
them quite yet a
handy tool is the example file for points.
So if you just say points examples are
points.
It'll go through a number of Demos so you
can see the capabilities that R can do
with plotting.
But most important is their little plot
I'm sorry little chart of the symbols
here.
And so you can see that's for example one
is
the circle, two is the triangle, three is
the plus etcetera.
Here at 20 was the solid circle small, 19
was the larger circle if you wanted the
solid square that's 15.
Solid triangle is 17 etcetera.
So you can
specify what type of symbol you what and
you just by, using the number here.
Another things, if you notice the symbols
21 through 25.
Those are actually symbols that are
similar to say.
But to ones that are, have been previously
shown, just for example, one thru six.
However the difference is in 21 through
25, those symbols have a
have have boundaries so you can see the
boundary is red and they have a fill which
to this case is yellow.
So you can specify the two different
colors, one for
the boundary of the outline and one for
the color.
And so the boundary color specified using
the col col argument.
And the, the background color, the fill
color, is specified using the bg argument.
So you can specify two different colors
like that if you
want.
Here's another chart of the plotting
symbols, and
you can continue through the demo here for
points if you want.
And I'll just finish it up here.
Just some of the special symbols that you
can plot if you want.
This is in a different font and let me
just click out of here.
So so that's one way to Change the symbol
here.
I'm going to go back to my plot here.
I'll say pch equals
let's say 20.
Excuse me.
I have to regenerate my data because it
was overwritten by the example.
[NOISE]
So here's my data again.
My little scatter plot.
Now, I can add a title to the plot by
using the title.
Now I'll just say this is my scatter plot.
And that adds a title.
I could add some text if I wanted to, so
for example,
I could use the text function to say add a
little label here.
Let's see, I'll give it the coordinates
I'll say minus 2 and then minus 2.
See that the label appears there.
I can add a legend if I wanted to.
Say the legend.
And the legend, you can give it, kind of
location specifications.
So, for example, top-left will put the
legend in the top-left.
And then I'll say
I'll just give it a stupid label, excuse
me let me
just pull plots in there so now I've got a
legend there.
So there's all kinds of annotations that
you can
add to the data as you kind of go along
so for example if I want to plot a line to
the data I could fit a linear model.
A lot that using the LN function.
Then the AD line function
will add the linear model fit on top of
the here and the data aren't related
to the other, each other so that the
linear model is the line is pretty flat.
If I wanted to adjust the thick, thickness
of that
line, I can use the AD line and specify
the LWD.
To be let's say three.
And you see that.
Now, a new line is plotted over that,
which is much thicker.
So you probably wouldn't want to do this
from the get go.
If you wanted to remake this plot, you'd
probably just
specify from the get go, LWD go up to
three.
You don't want to necessarily plot two
lines on top of each other.
But, I'm just showing this for demonstra-
Demonstration sake.
I could have also changed the color.
So make the color, say blue.
And that would make it blue.
And so there's lots of different types of
options you can specify here.
When you're, as you're making the plot
So usually, you're going to want to create
x labels and y
labels which are kind of, represent what
the data are.
So you can plot, you can put a lot of
these options in the plot function itself.
So I can say plot x,y and, and maybe x-lab
is let's say, weight.
And then y-lab, or y-lab, will be, say,
height.
The main will be scatter-plot.
PCH will be 20.
So that gets.
Now, I have actual labels on the X-axis
and Y-axis.
I can put my legend back if I want.
Maybe I'll put it in the top right this
time.
And then I can add my little line here.
So I can say, fit is,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Or maybe I'll make the line red this time.
So, that's my plot, with the labels of the
linear regression line.
And with the legend.
Now let's see what happens when we try to
put more than one plot on the page.
So for example, let's say I have another
variable, which I'll call z, and
maybe it's a, I don't know, maybe I'll
make us some Poisson data here.
Oh, excuse me.
And let's say I want to plot z versus x
and that
I also want to plot y versus x on the same
canvas here.
So the first thing I can do is let's say I
want to put,
let's say I want to put the plots right on
top of each other.
So let's say par mf row equals so that
it's going to happen, I
want to have two rows of plots and then
one column of plots, right?
So that's what we want to see.
So now I'll apply the x and y on the top,
and x and z on
the bottom.
So x and y, so PCH equals 20.
So you can see that goes on the top, and
on the bottom here,
I'll give x and z say it equals 19, and
that goes on the bottom.
So now you can see that the margins are a
little bit large here, lar, probably
larger than we would want.
and you see that the, that the margin that
I have, that's specified here.
Is
that.
And so we want to adjust the size of the
margin now
that we've kind of re- rearranged the
configuration of the plots.
So we can maybe say something like
par, let's see, par equals
Now if I plotted again,
they get a little bit bigger.
So like 20 again.
So that's how, now I put two plots on the
screen.
I could have done it the other way.
I could have said instead of them having
top
and bottom, I could have had them right
and left.
So by saying par name of row, equals a 1,
2.
Now I can plot like this
like that.
So you can see, I made the margins a
little
bit too small, because I lost my y-axis
label here.
So maybe I'll just say par.
I'll go back to four, four, two, two like
this.
And make it positive
again.
So you can see that when you've rearranged
the plotting layout, you might want
to rearrange the canvas itself to kind of
remove some of the white space.
I won't do that for the moment, just so I
can continue with the demo here.
But for example, you can put four plots on
a page.
Like say, mar equals, sorry, mf row.
Equals 2, 2.
That means two rows, two columns, so I can
say plot x and y.
That'll go in the upper left.
And you see, now, I can plot x and z.
You might wonder, well, where's the next
plot going to go?
Well, because I specified mf row, the
plots are going to go across the row.
So the next plot's going to be in the
upper right.
And then the next plot's going to be in
the lower left
so let's say I'll plot z and x instead of
x and z.
And then the last plot's going to go in
the lower right here.
So that, now I've got four plots on
a page by specifies, specifying the mf row
option.
If I'd specified mf call the same thing
would have happened but the order in which
the plots occurred Would have been
different, so now I can say plot x, y, and
that appears in the same place, but the
next
plot now is going to appear on the lower
left, and
the next plot's going to be in the upper
right,
and the last plot's going to be in the
lower right.
So that's the difference between mf row
and mf col.
The last option I'll talk about here is
the points function, just as
a demonstration to how you can annotate a
plot by adding things to it.
So, let me just reset the plot region so
that I'm only doing one plot at a time
here.
Now suppose I generate some data and, and
suppose the data consists of say, men and
women.
So there's two groups of people, here.
So I'm just going to generate some data
here.
And maybe I'll give them a little
relationship,
so it not, a little bit more interesting.
And let's say I've got another variable
here which is the group and it's going to
be half and half so the two groups in the
fifty level fifty iterations of each.
Let me just give them names.
We'll say labels.
So, I got males and females in this group
of people here.
You can see it is a factor variable of two
levels.
So, suppose I wanted to plot the data.
If I just plot the data X and Y you can't
tell who are the males and who are the
females, right?
Because they're all the same color for
example and So, suppose I want to plot the
data and plot the, make the males
one color and the females another Another
color.
So how do I do that?
So the first thing you want to do, the
basic idea is
you're going to set up the plot region,
but
you're not going to plot any of the data.
And then you're going to add the data by
gender, so you're going to
maybe add the females first, and then add
the males, and the
idea is that each time you add the data
points, they'll be
of a different color, or perhaps a
different plotting symbol, or whatever.
So first, let's set up a plotting region,
so I'm
going to say plot xy So I'm going to pass
at the data.
But I'm going to say type = N.
So this means make the plot, but don't
actually put the data in there.
So you can see that when I hit,
execute this function, everything happens
just like before.
The labels are put in.
The tick marks are put in.
The margins are specified.
Everything is there, except for the data.
So the only thing that's missing is the
data.
And so what I'm going to do is, I'm
going to add the
data, but I'm going to add them one group
at a time.
So let's say I add the males first.
So I can say points x, and then
I'm going to subset the vector so that the
g, I
only take the points where g is equal to
male.
Right, so that's a subset.
And then I'm going to say y, and then g is
equal to male.
So this is only going to plot, plot the
points, so where where the values of the
g variable are equal to male, let say I'm
going to set, make the, that color green.
Okay.
So next I see the points on the, on the
screen, are green.
Those are, those represent the male points
only.
So I can do the same thing for the female,
so
I can say points x and then g is equal to
female.
And the y g is equal to female.
And let's say I'll make these, blue.
So now you can see that there are blue
circles
for the females, and there's green circles
for the males.
And so you can see the two groups,
separately within the scatter plot.
And so, sub-setting based on a grouping
variable is very common when making plots
and the points function can be used to
kind of add points sequentially by group.
So that you can specify different types of
properties for each group.
You can also, in addition to varying the
color I could have changed the plotting
symbol.
So I could have said pch equal to let's
say 19.
So this is a kind of solid circle here.
And that would have given me a solid blue
circle
for the females and an open green circle
for the males.
So that's one way to separate out.
Groups of data points on a single scatter
plot.