In this video I want to talk about 2
things, how to set
your working directory and how to edit our
code files in Windows.
So you can see I've got R started up here,
and the first
thing you're going to want to do is figure
out what your working directory is.
Because the working directory is where R
finds all
of its files for reading and writing on
your computer.
So you can find out what yur working
directory is
currently set to be by using the Get WD
function.
And you can see it's set to be,
c:/users/rdbanks/documents.
This may differ on your computer.
Depending on what version of Windows
you're using.
and, and what hardware you're using.
But there'll be some directory.
Probably on your C drive.
Now, It, the reason why it's important to
know and to set your working directory is
because when you read data or when you
write things out using functions like read
or
write CSV, they will be read or written to
your home, your working directory.
So for example if I do something
like read.csv I want to read the say
mydata.csv.
If the file is not in my working
directory, you'll get an error.
One that looks much like this because it
can't find the file in the working
directory.
So one possibility is that you can, if you
know
where this file is, you can move it to
your
working directory.
Or, or you can change your working
directory
to be wherever this file happens to be.
So I can go the File menu here, and choose
Change deer.
And I'm going to go into my local disk
here,
users, already paying I go to my desktop
here.
So now, if I type DIR, I'll get a list of
the files that are on my desktop here.
In seeing that, lo and behold here is
mydata.csv file.
So now I can say read.csv and then
mydata.csv.
And you can see that the data will be
printed to the
console because now we can find the file
in my working directory.
So one nice thing, one thing that I
suggest that you
do for this course, is that perhaps create
a single directory or
single folder where you can put all of
your materials for the course.
And not have to worry about them being
scattered all over the place.
Any time you download something from the
website
or create a new file, it's probably best
to
store it all in one folder so that you
don't have to be searching all over for
it.
That way, you can always set your working
directory to be that,
to be that directory and not have to worry
about changing it.
So I'm going to minimize R here for a
second.
I'm going to create a folder
on the desktop.
Calls I'll just call it Coursera, and
then I'm going to use this folder for
everything that I do in this course.
So if I go back to R here, I can say
change
working directory again, changed here, and
I can go to local disc.
Users, RDping.
Now this folder is on my desktop, so
desktop
then it's Coursera here.
So now I'm going to say get WD.
Let's see the working directory has
changed to this Coursera folder.
So one of the things you're going to have
to do
a lot of in this class is to write R code.
In order to write R code, you need to be
able to use a text editor.
luckily, R comes with a rudimentary text
editor
which will be definitely sufficient for
this course.
So you can load at the text editor by
going to File,
and say New Script.
And this will give you a blank window,
that you can use to write our code.
So I'm going to write a simple function
here, it's going to
be my function [NOISE] it's not going to
take any arguments, and
all it's going to do it's going to
simulate some normal random
variables, and then it's going to take the
mean of those guys.
Alright.
So this is a simple function.
Now the question is how do I get this R
code into my R consoles that
I can actually use the function, because
you'll
notice if I go into my R console here.
I type my function.
it's, I can't find the function because I
haven't loaded into R yet.
If I type LS, you'll see that there's
nothing in my
workspace right now because I haven't
loaded any R code into there.
So how do I get the R code into the
R console?
Well there's two ways.
If you just have a little bit of code like
this function over here, I can click into
my R editor.
And if just hit hit Ctrl + A to select
all, and then Ctrl + C to copy.
Then I click back into the console, and I
can hit Ctrl + V to paste.
Now I've just pasted the code into R and
you'll see
that if I type LS, I've got my, my
function there.
I can execute it by just calling it, and
you'll see it'll give you the mean
of 100 random.
Normal random variables, if I do it again,
it will give me
a slightly different number because it
will simulate a different set of numbers.
The other thing you can do is go into my
R-editor,
and you can go to the File menu and click
Save As.
So now you can, if you save, you can hit
Save As, you can
save the file into your Coursera folder
here, which I'm going to do right now.
And you can
save it as whatever name you want.
So I'm going to call it my code .R.
.R is conventional for the extension.
So now if I type dir, excuse me.
In my console window here, you'll see that
there's a file called mycode.r.
And you can load this into R, using the
source function.
So I can say mycode .r.
And that loads the all the code that is
in this file, of course that's just the my
function.
So, I haven't done anything new here.
But let's say, I want to add another
function here.
We'll say, second for my second function,
and it will take an argument X
and it will take X, it will add a little
bit of noise to it.
So, With the R in arm function.
Okay so now I've got two functions here.
I can save my file with this little disk
icon, or I can go to file, the File menu,
hit Save.
And I'm going to source this file again.
Now, when I type LS, you'll see that I've
got this 2nd function there.
And I type 2nd, let's say 4.
I get a number that's 4, plus a little bit
of random noise.
So let me get 4 again, lastly the same
thing will happen.
I could say 4 through 10.
And it'll give me each one of those
numbers
with a little bit of random noise added
on.
So that's how I edit code, and that's how
I load the code into R.
Every time you edit your
file in the editor, you have to save it
and then if you want that code to
be available in R, you have to use the
source function to source that file back
into R.
You don't have to use a single file, you
can
add a new file, so you can say new script.
It'll open in another window, you can save
this to be a different file if you want.
So that way you can separate
code for different projects or different
assignments.
If you close the file here You can always
open it back
again by hitting, the open button and you
can see my code is right there.
And if I open it up, you'll see you'll
have all your code right back there again.
So that's how you edit code in R.
There's now there's many other text
editors that you might see on the web
that you can download, and those are fine
to use, but they're not really necessary.
The text editor that comes with R should
be sufficient for this course.