So lattice has what are called panel
functions.
So, you know, when you have a multi-panel
plot, there's a function that gets
called to, to kind of plot the data in
each one of those panels.
And that controls what happens to each one
of these panels.
Lattice package comes with a number of
default panel functions, but you
can supply your own if you want to
customize what happens in each panel.
And so basically, each panel function
receives the x
and the y coordinates of the data points
in that
particular panel.
So remember, each panel's going to
represent a subset of the data,
which is defined by the conditioning
variable that you give it.
And so you, you, each panel function will,
for each panel, the panel
function will get the x/y coordinates of
the points that are in that plot.
And so you can see here, I'm generating
some random
data that are, that are kind of, follow a
linear model.
And I create a factor variable which is
basically just separating out Group 1 and
Group 2.
And now I'm going to plot x and y by
group.
And so here I got two panels in Group 1,
it looks like
a strong linear relationship, and in Group
2, it looks like there's no relationship.
So you can, here, you can see, I'm, I'm
calling a custom panel
function, my, via the panel argument, and
I give it, I give it
a function, so the first two arguments are
x and y, and then
followed by dot, dot, dot, which means any
other arguments that may get passed.
And so, in my custom
panel function, the first thing I do is I
call
the default xyplot panel function just to
make the points appear.
And then my customization is I add a
little, a horizontal line at
each panel, which is the median of the y
values in that panel.
So now I can see there is a dash line in
each panel
right at where the median of, of the y,
the y coordinates is.
Another fancier thing I can do is rather
than
add the median, it might be useful to add
a
regression line, so you can look at the,
the linear
relationship between x and y within each
of the panels.
So here again, I, I pass a custom
function, and
I call, first thing I do is I call the
panel the xyplot function to just kind of
make the
points appear, and make all the axis
labels, and everything appear.
And then I call panel.lmline to add the
regression line to the panel.
One thing that's worth noting
is that you can't use any of the
annotation functions from the base
plotting system in the
lattice system, so any of the functions
that are
in the base plotting system can't be used
here.
As a general rule, you can't mix functions
between different plotting systems.
And so you have to use all the
functions that are relevant to the given
plotting system.
So as one quick, one more quick example of
showing on a large, larger data set.
This comes from the Mouse Allergen and
Asthma
Cohort Study which was conducted here in
Baltimore City.
To look at the indoor environment of
children with asthma living in Baltimore.
Many of these children are allergic to
mouse allergen.
So this is an observational study where,
in which there was a baseline home visit.
And then there was a visit every three
months
for a year, so for a total of five visits.
And so, one thing, one question you might
want to ask is how does the indoor
airborne mass allergen vary over time and
across subjects.
So, what I want to do is I basically
want to make a plot
of the airborne, indoor mass allergen for
every subject for every visit.
So there are 150 subjects in this data
set, and they each have five visits,
so you can, so there are going to be 750
data points here that we want to look at.
And so, what's a compact way
to do that?
Well, actually, a very easy way to do that
is
use x/y plot, and use a multi panel
lattice plot.
And so that's what we've done here, you
can take a look at
the data, one, and, and these are all the
subjects in the study.
And this is all their airborne mouse
allergen levels.
Well, it's the log of their airborne mouse
And so you can see the variation within a
person, so within each panel, you
can see that their allergen levels can go
up or down, or can vary from
visit to visit.
You can see the variation across subjects
so you can see that some
people have just very high levels, and
some people just have generally lower
levels.
So it's kind of that cross sectional
variation in addition to the within person
variation.
You can see that a number of people have
missing values, so not
everyone has five values, some people only
have two values or one value.
And so it may be useful to kind of follow
up on those subjects to see why this
subject only
have four values or three values.
You can see that some subjects, have a lot
of
variations, so they go up and down a lot
between visits.
And some have almost no variation at all,
and
every visit is the same level of mouse
allergen.
And so you may or may not want to follow
up on some of
this some of these patterns, depending on
what exactly you want, you're interested
in.
And so you can see that with essentially
one or two
function call, you can make a massive plot
like this, look at
a lot of data without having to go through
a lot of code.
And so that's what, that's a, that's part
of
the power of the lattice system, which
lets you
look at a lot of data, as long as they're
kind of kind of formatted in certain ways.
So again, this is the, the relationship
between the visit
number and the log airborne mouse allergen
levels by subject.
Right, and so this is a very quick way
to kind of summarize all the data in this
study.
So just to summarize, lattice plots are
constructed with a single
function call to one of the core lattice
functions, like xyplot.
Things like, the, one of the nice things
about lattice plots
is that things like margins and spacings
and labels are automatically handled.
And so you don't have to set them all the
time using, like you did in the base
plotting system,
where you had the margin option and the
and the
kind of spacings and the m texts and the
outer margin.
And so you don't have to worry about
that very much in lattice plots.
And the lattice system is really ideal
when you have data
sets that you can look at by conditioning
on certain variables,
so basically, you typically look, you
want to look at a relationship,
but you want to look at it within levels
of another variable.
So you want, want to look at kind of the
same kind of plot but under many different
conditions.
And you can use the customized panel
functions to modify
exactly what goes on in each of the plot
panels.
And so that gives you a lot of power
to kind of customize the look of these
panel plots.
And so I, I find the lattice system very
useful for looking
at kind of a lot of data in a very quick
way.
And so, I encourage you to try to look at
it and look at some of the
other functions, like bwplot, box plots
and scatter
plot matrices to see how they work for
you.