The lattice plotting system in R is a
plotting system that's
different from the base plotting system
and it works very differently.
And it's useful for plotting, often for
plotting kind of high
dimensional data and for making lot, many
many plots at once.
And if you recall in the base plotting
system it was possible to put multiple
plots on the same graphics device using
the mfrow or mfcall arguments.
And you can make panels and plots to
look at many different feature.
And the lattice plotting system is kind of
designed to really make, to optimize that
type of
plot and to make very high density plots
and
so it can be useful in many different
situations.
And so I'll talk about some of the, the
functions in the lattice system here.
So, the lattice plotting system is, is
implemented in the lattice package.
So you have to load the package in order
to use it.
Underlying the lattice package is what's
called the grid package which implements
a lot of the kind of low level plumbing of
the, of the lattice graphic system.
And you, you typically won't have to call
functions
from the grid package directly but it's
useful to know
that underneath there are a lot of,
there's a
lot of code that is implemented in the
grid package.
And so the lat, lattice package builds on
top of grid and
gives you a number of kind of user
functions to, to employ.
the, the one thing about the lattice
plotting system is, is that it does
not have a kind of two phase aspect like
the base plotting system did.
In where you kind of in the base plotting
system, if you recall,
you kind of create the plot and then you
annotate it with separate functions.
Here in the lattice plotting system, you
have to create
the entire plot all at once in a single
function call.
And so you have to specify all the details
within that function
call and, because you won't have a chance
really to annotate it afterwards.
So some of the main functions in lattice
are xyplot.
This is probably the most important
function.
It's basically used for making scatter
plots.
There's bwplot for bock, for boxplots,
histogram for histograms.
Stripplot is kind of like a boxplot, but
there's but it uses points.
The dotplot plots points on where, where
it will look like a violin strings.
Splom is for scatter plot matrix.
It's kind of like the pairs function in
the base plotting system.
And levelplot and contourplot are for
plotting image data.
And so, I'll just talk a little bit about
the xyplot right function right now.
Because I think it's the most important.
The basic function call for xyplot is that
you have a formula kind of notations.
So you have y ~ x.
So the y is going to be whatever's on your
y-axis and x is going to be whatever's on
your x-axis.
And then you have this vertical bar
which separates what are called,
conditioning variables.
And so f and g are going to
be categorical variables that you
condition on.
So for example, and the idea is that you
want to
you can kind of, to interpret this
function call in words, the
idea is that I want to look at the scatter
plot
of y and x for every level of f and g,
right?
So, and you don't have to use two
different categorical variables.
I just wanted to show that you could.
And so, and then the second argument is
the data argument.
And this is the data frame where the
variables x, y, f, and g can be found.
If there's no data frame there, then it
will
look in your workspace for the variables
to plot.
So here's just a very simple scatter plot.
I load the lattice package and the data
sets package, and I'm
plotting the ozone and wind variables from
the air quality data frame.
So you can see I just did ozone ~ wind, so
I got ozone on the y-axis and wind on the
x-axis, and this is your basic scatter
plot which looks
very much like a scatter plot in the base
plotting system.
Notice that the defaults are a little bit
different.
It does use open circles, but they're
colored blue by default.
Now, here's a slightly more complicated
lattice plot.
So here I've, I've gotten the same data
frame,
but I've converted the month variable into
a factor.
And now I'm plotting ozone versus wind by
month.
So you can interpret the formula as, I
want to look at the relationship between
ozone and
wind for each level of month and so
month goes from five, six, seven, eight,
and nine.
So from the month of May to the month of
September.
And you can see the relationship between
ozone and wind.
It appears to change across the month.
So there doesn't appear to be you know
much relationship in May or June.
But you can see in, in July and August,
there's a relatively strong relationship.
There is a negative one there, so more
wind means less ozone.
And you can see by September that
relationship
is starting to die down a little bit.
So I, it's very easy, so that's one of the
pow, the power
of the xyplot function in lattice is that
I can make these multidimensional
panels very simply with just a single
function call.
And you recall in the base plotting
system, I would,
there would've been many, many function
calls create this plot.
And here I just used a single line.
So now I'm, so now I'm looking at three
different variables here, the month, the
ozone, and wind.
And, and they're all kind of arranged in
one panel, which is very convenient.
So the lattice functions behave a little
bit differently, and
it's worth noting the difference between
lattice and the base graphics.
Base graphics functions plot data directly
to a graphics device.
So if you recall there's the screen
device, there's
PDF files, there are all kinds of graphics
devices.
What lattice functions do is they, they
don't actually, they don't specifically
plot anything.
Uh,hat they do is they return an object of
class trellis.
And then the object has to be printed
in order for the data in the plot to kind
of go to the graphics device.
So there is a two-stage aspect there, but
most
of the time this aspect is invisible to
the user.
Because what happens is that the u-, when
you call a function like xyplot,
it returns an object of class trellis, but
then it auto prints that object.
And so, the auto-printing feature of R
will make it
so that it automatically sends the plot to
the graphics device.
So most of the time you don't have to
worry about this two step process.
But it's worth noting that you can, in
theory, save the plot object
to an R object, and then it'll be sitting
in your work space.
Now, you can theoretically store that
object
but it's probably not wise to do this.
It's better to save the code that
generates the plot and the data.
So you can see this lattice behavior in
just in this simple bit of code here.
So here I'm calling the xyplot function.
I'm saving to an object called p, and then
I'm printing p.
And that's when the plot appears.
So when you run this code, after the first
line of code,
nothing will happen, but after the second
line, the plot will appear.
So if you just call xyplot, then it, then
we use what's called the auto-printing
feature of R.