So in R, the kmeans function is the
function that
we use to it, to implement the kmeans
algorithm, here.
And you can a, I, you can dem, I can
demonstrate it here with use, using a
simple data frame.
I got two, with just two dimensions.
And I called kmeans on the data frame and
I tell it there are three centers.
Alright, so three centroids and what
kmeans returns is
a, is a list with a number of different
elements in it.
And so, for example, the, probably the
most important element
is the cluster element and you can see
here when
I print out the cluster element, you can
see that
it's a vector of numbers from one to three
so.
And what this shows is that for each data
point in the in
the data frame that I passed it, it tells
me which cluster it's in.
So you can see that the first four points
are in cluster
three, the next four are in cluster one,
and the next four
are in cluster two.
You can see another element if you look in
the printout of the
names another element of the, of the
object returned from kmeans is called
centers.
And this tells you the location of the
centroids in the space.
So, if you want to plot the kind of, the,
the results for kmeans, the
first thing you can do is you can run the
kmeans algorithm on your data.
And here, I'm just going to plot the data.
So the first thing I do is I plot the
data, so I plot X Y
and then I color the data points according
to the cluster that they happen to be in.
So you can see I, I pass the
color argument to be equal to the cluster
number.
And then I, I use the points function to
kind of add the centers, the clusters
centroids to
the plot and I, and I plot them using the
plus symbol.
So, here I plotted the, the data and the
kmeans clustering results.
Finally, another way that you can
visualize clustering
information for an outcome in an algorithm
like
kmeans is by using the Heatmap function
or,
or use, looking at heatmaps I should say.
So here I've just, I've, I've using the
same data
I've taken out a different random sample
of the data set.
I sampled its replacement and I just run
kmeans again, again with
three centers.
And I stored it in an object called kmeans
object two.
And now I'm going to make a, an image plot
of the data, so
the first plot on the left here is just an
image of the original data.
And then on the right hand side I've
reordered
the the columns of the data, I'm sorry, I
should say the rows of the data frame so,
so that the clusters are kind of put
together.
So here, you can see that if you go up and
down the, up and down this matrix.
You'll see the cluster, the, the data
points are
clustered together so that they are next
to each other.
And so you can use this to look at high
dimensional
data, and high dimensional image type
data, or matrix type data
where you can reorganize the rows and the
columns and kind
of look at clusters that are closer
together or farther apart.
and, and, and, or, kind of, and in it, and
so
look at your kind of matrix data in an
organized way
so you can look for, so you can look for
patterns.
We'll talk a little bit about this more
when we talk about hierarchical
clustering, but again, you
can, you can use heatmap type of
visualizations
with other types of clustering algorithms
like kmeans too.
So it's, just to summarize, you know,
kmeans is a handy
algorithm for organizing and looking for
patterns that hide eventual data.
A couple of things that I for, it requires
that you know the number of clusters.
So you have to specify
at least roughly speaking, how many
clusters there are.
You can, you can kind of play with that a
little bit to determine, to figure
out kind of what, what pattern probably
looks
the best, but there's no easy rule there.
And then so you have to pick those
clusters
out by eye or sort of through some other
mechanism.
There are a few algorithms for kind of
determining the number
of clusters using, either using
cross-validation,
information theory, other types of
metrics.
And so there's,
here's a link to determining the number of
clusters.
And it's, and the kmeans algorithm is not
deterministic, so there are, depending
on how it's implemented, there can be,
sometimes those starting points are chosen
at
random, and so, so it's often useful to
run the kmeans algorithm a
couple times just to make sure you're not
getting a very unstable finishing point.
So, for example, if you run it three
different times,
and every time you get a totally different
pattern, then that
means that the, the algorithm may not be,
have
a very stable kind of view of the data.
And so, so, kmeans is, can, can be
problematic in that way for certain types
of datasets.
And here, I've got a couple links to kind
of, to videos
and, and references on, that, that provide
a lot more information about kmeans.