This lecture is going to be about K-means
clustering.
And K-means is actually a relatively old
technique that was developed
quite a while ago but it's, it remains
very useful we're
going to, were kind of summarizing high
dimensional data and we're getting
a sense of, you know, what, what patterns
your data shows.
wha, What kinds of observations are
similar to each
other, and what observations are very
different from each other.
So we're going to talk a little about
K-means
works, and show what it can do for you.
So the basic principle behind
K-means clustering is that to first define
how, what does it mean for things to be
similar to each other and what does it
mean for things to be different from each
other.
So in some sense you want to define you
know?
What does it mean to be close?
How do we group things together, and how
do we visualize this grouping?
And then once we visualize the grouping
how do we interpret what we see?
So I think The basic.
The most important thing is defining: what
do we mean by close?
And we need a distance metric
to define you know, what it means for two
things to be close together.
Because depending on the context, two
things could
seem close, but not, but not be very
close.
And then in a different context, you have,
you
could have a totally different meaning of,
of distance.
And so this is a very important step.
And if you don't do it well.
You end up with nonsense at the end.
So, get kind of the classic garbage in,
garbage out.
So the couple of t, traditional distance
metrics and
this in, statistics are, you having a
notion of continuous distance.
Which is like euclidean distance, so this
is like the straight line between two
points.
Another continuous measure is basically
like a correlation similarity between.
Let's say two variables and so you can see
how correlated they are, or how similar
they are.
So highly correlated points would be
similar.
And then another distance is called the
Manhattan distance.
And this is kind of, we'll, we'll talk a
little bit more about this a little bit
later on.
So, you need to pick a distance or
a similarity metric that makes sense for
your problem.
So k-means clustering is a way of
partitioning a
group of observations into a fixed number
of clusters.
And so the idea is that you have, you have
to
set, say beforehand how many clusters of
data, of points are there.
So for example, if you have 100
observations in your data set you
might think that they could be neatly
divided into say four different groups.
Okay?
So you have to have a sense of how many
clusters there are first.
And then each of these groups
is going to have a centroid.
Right?
So it's going to be like a center of
gravity around which each group kind of
gathers.
And then once you have these centroids, we
kind of defined we
kind of assign each of the observations to
each of these centroids.
And that's how we do the group kind of
assignment.
And so the basic approach is to kind of
pick some, or the
algorithm for writing K-means is to
kind of pick some, pick a centroid.
You know, assign all the points to the
centroids.
Then maybe recalculate the centroids and
reassign all the points.
So you kind of iterate back and forth
until you reach a solution.
And so the things that you need, you need
a distance metric.
You need a number of clusters, so a
fixed number of clusters that hit the
specify beforehand.
And you need an initial guess as to where
the centroids are.
And often you might just pick some random
points, just
to start the algorithm in terms of where
the centroids are.
But K-means clustering algorithm will
produce
a, a final kind of estimate of.
Where the cluster centroids are.
And it will tell you which centroid each
observation is assigned to.
Here's a quick example of how you might
use the K-means clustering algorithm.
I've generated just some random data here
that
are in two dimensions so it's easy to
visualize.
And so the x coordinates and the y
coordinates
all come from a normal distribution with
different means.
So I specifically
created three different kind of clusters
for these twelve observations.
So each cluster has four observations in
it.
So when I plot the data, it's very obvious
that there are three clusters.
And I put labels on each of the points.
So here we see that the algorithm started.
And I've just chosen some three random
points.
To be the centroid.
So you can see there's kind of red plus,
and a purple plus,
and an orange plus down at the bottom.
So those are the random starting points
for the centroids.
You're going to see the first thing we're
going to do.
Is we're going to take each of our data
points and assign to it the closes
centroid, right?
So you can see for example point number
eight at the very top.
The closest centroid is the red plus over
in the upper left.
So that gets assigned to that cluster.
And then point number four down in the
lower
left here, that gets assigned to the red
cluster also.
And then the three points one, two, and
three they
get assigned to the orange plus in the
orange cluster.
And then, the rest of the points are
closest to the purple little plus there.
So, they get assigned to the purple
cluster.
And so, that's the first kind of initial
grouping
of the of the points to the three
different clusters.
And then the next thing we're going to
do is we're going to recalculate the
centroid.
So now we have the cluster definition.
Every point is assigned to a cluster.
We can recalculate
the centroids, so for example, by taking
the mean of that cluster.
So now you can see that the purple pluses
has
moved slightly to be in the middle of that
cluster.
The red plus has moved a little bit to be
in the middle of that cluster.
And the orange one is now in the middle of
the three orange dots.
And so the, the the cluster centroids
gets, get recalculated.
And then you kind of repeat the process
again.
So you take each data point and you say
well what cluster centroid
is it closest to now?
And I can see that point number four for
example used to be in the
red cluster but now it's closer to the
orange cluster so now it gets reassigned.
And then you see for example point number
seven is now
closer to the red plus so its in the red
cluster.
and, and then we recalculate the centroid
from this, you see,
now the centroids are kind of moving
toward you to the point.
So, you can see how the clusters are kind
of forming as you go step by step but
the two processes are to assign the points
to each
cluster, and then to update the cluster of
the centroid locations.