Now, another layer that you can add to
your plot is a smoother,
and many times you want to do this just so
you can get a sense
of the overall trend in the data, so I
want to, you might want to get
a general sense of, as PM 2.5 increases do
we get more nocturnal symptoms?
So on the left hand side here, these, this
is this is the code down here.
The bottom that I use, I have my original
GG plot
object, G which just had the X and Y kind
of Aesthetics.
I added my points to make the scatter plot
and I added a smooth a geom underscore
smooth function.
It adds a little smoother which is the
blue line and the grey confidence bands
and so I used the default for the geom
smooth which is a low s smoother.
And which is generally fine.
But you can see there's a lot of noise on
the boundaries, so on
the left and right side of the smoother
the confidence intervals get very wide
because it's flexible smoother, and the
noise, there's a lot
of noise on the boundaries because there's
not much data there.
And so I'd rather something a little bit
simpler
than [INAUDIBLE] I just want a linear
regression line.
And, and so, that's less flexible, but it
still gives me a sense of the trend.
So, here on the, on the right hand side,
you see
I've re-, I've re-made the plot, and I've
added the geome smooth,
but I give it, in option, I said method
equals LM, and
this will do a linear model instead of a
low S smoother.
And you can
see that on the edges of the linear model,
the, the uncertainty
in the compass band's a lot smaller than
it is for low S.
And you see that generally speaking there
seems to
be an increasing trend with pm 2.5 and
nocturnal symptoms.
So, another layer we want to add is the
facet.
So, this is the final layer to kind of
reproduce that original simple plot.
That I made with Q Plot.
So here the facets are going to be,
are going to be determined by the BMI
category.
So I want to compare children who are
normal weight and children who are
overweight.
And so that's going to be two separate
plots, but then I
want to plot the same relationship in each
one of those windows.
So that's what creates the facet.
And so, I can add my facet
with the the facet underscore grid
variable.
And this variable uses special notation
which is separate.
Which has kind of a variable on the
left-hand side and a variable on the
right-hand side.
And, and they're separated by this tilde.
And so, the variables that you specified
in the
facet function determine how the grid, how
the separate plots.
Are laid out on the screen.
And so, the number of plots will be,
will be equal to the number of levels of
your factor.
And so, I have two levels in my factor.
I've got normal weight and overweight.
Then that will create two plots for me.
If I, notice I only have a single Set
a factor variable that I want to separate
on.
So, I don't want, I'm not going to have a
matrix of plots.
I'm just going to have a single row of
plots.
And so, I'll, if I, so I'm only going to
have two plots because there's two
categories in this BMI variable.
If
I had two variables, which I, and I'll
give you an example of that later.
So a variable on the left-hand side and
the
variable on the right-hand side, the in
the product
of the number of factor levels is going to
be
the number of plots that you generate with
the facets.
So here I've added the facet grid function
and I also added the smoother with my lm.
Notice that it doesn't, it doesn't really
matter
what kind of order you put these things
in.
You can add them in Any order
you want.
And notice I stuck the facet grid function
in between the smooth
and the point and that was fine it still
generated the plot.
So facets are useful for, for kind of
conditioning on a categorical variable.
And you can see it here that the normal
weight children have
don't seem to have any relationship in pm
2.5 and nocturnal symptoms.
Whereas the overweight children might
appear
to have a stringer more positive
relationship.
The last thing that I'll mention is you
notice
the labels in each of the panels I didn't,
I didn't actually label them by hand, the
labels
come from the levels the factor variable
that you condition
So it's important that you use the factor
variables
in an intelligent way and have intelligent
labels on
them because the GEGE plot will take that
information
and automatically apply it to the labeling
of your plots.
And so in GEGE plot the substance is
easier to
modify your data and make sure
the metadata is then specified
appropriately rather
than to kind of Plot things and then kind
of modify the plot later.
It's better to make sure all your data is
kind of organized and labeled
appropriately before you make the plot,
because
then that makes the plotting code much
simpler.
Okay, so once you've kind of made your
plot often you want to modify things
like the axis labels and the titles and,
and other kinds of kind of plot metadata.
And so there are a number of, of functions
for doing that.
For, for the labels there's the xlab
function, the ylab function and the
ggtitle function.
Those are all st-, I use to specify the x
label, the y label and the title.
You could also use the labs function,
which is a
more general function that can be used to
specify x,
y labels or titles.
It doesn't really matter what you use.
Each of the geom functions, like the geom
points and the geom,
smooth function have options that you can
use to change things, so you
can explore some of those options too if
you don't like the default.
There are some things that only make
sense kind of at a global thing, globally
meaning
for the whole plot, and so that the theme
function is vail, is available for that.
So this might specify kind of the big
basic colors, the background
colors are here for example the le, the
position of the legend.
And you can use the theme
function to specify these options.
Then finally there are, there are some
general themes that are built
in that kind of control a lot of different
elements of the plot.
So you can specify to kind of set many
options at
once and, and basically The theme_gray is
kind of the default theme.
It gives you the gray background with the
white line, the white grid lines.
The theme_bw for black and white is a kind
of more stark, a plainer theme if you
don't
like the gray background.
So, I'll talk a little bit about kind
of modifying some of the features of the
aesthetics.
So for example, sometimes there, you might
want to change the colors of the points
if you don't like black points or if you
don't like them to be solid.
You like them to be transparent.
You can, on the left-hand side, I've
modified, modified my, my
basic scatter plot of pm2.5 and nocturnal
symptoms by doing two things.
One is I've made the color steel blue.
I've increased the size of the points to
be 4 the default is 1.
And I've, and I've changed the alpha
transparency to be a half rather than
solid.
So now you can see that the blue, there's
blue points that are a
steel blue, they're somewhat transparent
and they're
a lot bigger than they were before.
The important thing to realize that I,
I've placed these options in the geo-point
function
and each one of these options the color,
the size, the alpha, have all been
set to be a constant.
And so the constants Basically are, are
for the are not actually
aesthetics they're just options for the,
for putting the points on the page.
On the right hand side here you can see
that the plot looks similar but I I've,
I've got,
there's two colors now and each of the
colors corresponds
to if the child is over weight or normal
weight.
And so now you can see what I call, what
is called geom_point.
Rather than say just color equals bmicat,
which would assign
the, the category of bmi to be a different
color.
I had to wrap it in this aes function
which stands for aesthetics.
So now, rather than specify color as a
constant like
steel blue The color has been assigned to
a data variable.
And so, it's very important that you know
the distinction between, giving
a, assigning a color to be a constant,
like black or white or
blue, and assigning color to be the value
of a variable.
So, when you assign color to be the value
of a variable - What happens
is that all the points and each set of
points is assigned a different color.
Then they are put back on the page along
with this legend on the right hand side.
Then outside of the A.E.S. function I
still have
my size equals 4 and my alpha equals 1/2.
So those are unchanged from the left hand
plot.
So that the points are still bigger, and
the transparency is still half.
And so, so the import-, so, so the key to
remember here is that there's a difference
between assigning a
aesthetic value to be a constant, and
assigning aesthetic to
be, to be the, the correspondent, or
variable, data variable.
If you want it to be a constant, you
can just specify in the geom point
function directly.
If you want it to be assigned to a data
variable, then you have to wrap it in this
aes function.
You can modify the labels with the labs
function.
So the labs function here I've called a
few different times.
I've added on to my basic plot.
So the g object, remember, it's just the
data frame plus the x and y coordinates.
Here I've added geome point function, and
I've, I've signed the color variable, the
BMI
category, so now the different, the two
different BMI categories in, in two
different colors.
The labels I set the title to be
max cohort, because that's where the data
come from.
This is a max study.
I've set the x label to be this
expression,
which is log of pm 2.5, and I used the
mathematical annotation that I talked,
that we talked about previously
to get that pm 2.5 that 2.5 subscript on
there.
And then I took the y label to just be
nocturnal signal.
So now it's a little bit cleaner.
The plot has kind of more appropriate
labels on it.
I can also customize the smoother if I
want to.
So now, I'm going to modify the options to
the geom's smooth function.
So here all I've done to, is I add an
option to say it's size equals four.
So I made this line a little bit thicker.
And I mad the, the line type to be equal
three.
So the three that, that just means a
dotted line instead of a solid line.
I still use method equals LM, so I want to
regression line.
And I turned off the confidence intervals,
so I, so that it's a little bit more clear
to see.
So I see SC equals false.
So these are all functions that you can
add to
the GM Smooth function if you don't like
the defaults.
So another thing you can do is just change
the overall theme.
So the default theme, you look in the
previous slide here.
You can see that there's a gray
background, with those kind of white grid
lines.
There's this solid kind of thicker white
lines for kind of larger kind of
intervals.
And then there's kind of thinner white
lines for smaller intervals.
If you don't like that background, you can
change it
to the kind of a more basic black and
white background.
So this is the theme_bw theme.
And another thing, as you can see, I've
changed here is, I've changed
the font.
So the default font is going to be
something like
Helvetica, but I've changed it to be a
Times font.
So now you can see that it's a serif font
as opposed to sans serif.
And it looks like, and it uses the Times
font to
do the labels, to do the legend, and also
the axis ticks.
So you can see, the numbers on the axis
are all in the Times font.
So the theme function, the various theme
functions can
be used to modify these elements of the
plot.