Alright so in this lecture I'm going to
talk about ggplot, but I'm
going to talk about some of the
more kind of, underlying fundamental
aspects of ggplot.
In the last lecture I talked mostly about
the qplot function and how you could use
the, the qplot function to kind of make
your basic plots scatterplots, bar charts,
things like that.
This is in some sense a replacement for
the base, for the plot function in R,
which
is, which we use the base plots to create
the same kinds of things, scatter plots
and histograms.
So the qplot function's very handy, but it
doesn't reveal a lot of the underlying
infrastructure
that kind of, is built into ggplot that
allows you to make all kinds of custom
plots.
So I just wanted to highlight a couple of
the basic ideas in this lecture.
I don't really have time to go over every
single
little detail of the ggplot package,
because it's so big.
So I thought I would try to get you
started on a couple of basic fundamentals.
If you have a lot more interest in
developing
plots using the ggplot framework you can
you
can, there are a lot of references that
I mentioned in the previous lecture in
terms
of the ggplot2 book and other types of
books.
So I encourage you to look at those
resources if you want to explore
this type of plotting framework further
than what we discuss here in the course.
So, let's get started.
Just to review a little bit in terms of
what is ggplot2.
Remember it's an implementation of the
grammar of graphics.
Which was developed by Leland Wilkinson.
And the grammar of graphics basically
describes
a re, an abstract representation for
graphics.
And so that the idea is that it's kind of
the verb, noun, adjective for plots.
So what are the basic elements that can be
modified, and cannot be modified, and
things like that?
So that's a theory of graphics that you
can kind of
build on to develop new graphics using
this kind of abstract language.
So some of the basic components of a
ggplot kind of graphic, are, you need
data.
Of course, the data is the most important
thing,
that's what you're going to put on to the
page, and
so you need to have a data frame that
has all the data that you're going to plot
in it.
You need something that's called an
aesthetic mapping, these are, these
describe
how the data are mapped to things like
colors and sizes and points.
Geoms are specific
objects that you're going to put onto the
page, like things like
points or lines or tiles or shapes or
whatever, you have it.
Facets are, are used for conditional
plots, so if you're
going to have multi, typically you want to
have multiple panels of
plots, where it might show the
relationship of something as
something as a third variable changes
that, that's a facet.
And then stats are statistical
transformations like smoothing,
binning, quantiles, regression, things
like that.
Scales are to find how the different
variables are coded, in terms of the plot.
So, for example, you might have a binary
variable that represents sex.
So you let the males will be red, and the
females blue, or something like that.
And so that is a scaling for a particular
type of dichotomous variable.
And lastly, you need a coordinate system
which we
won't focu, focus on too much on this
lecture.
But you need a coordinate system that
tells you
how certain numerical representations get
translated onto a plot.
So when you build a plot with ggplot2, the
basic idea if you're not
going to be using the qplot function,
you'll
want to kind of build it piece by piece.
You can kind of think of it as the
artist's palette model.
So this is the, similar to the model in
the base plotting system but where
you kind of start with something, and you
kind of add things piece by piece.
So unlike the lattice system, where you
had to have the whole plot is encoded in a
single function call, you can start with a
single
call to, you can start with a ggplot
function.
And then you kind of add things on piece
by piece, maybe, as you
think of them, or as you see things in the
plot, you make little changes.
You can kind of add things here as you go.
So the idea is that plots are built up in
layers.
Okay.
And so, the most fundamental layer of
course is the data.
So the first thing you usually start with,
is you kind of tell
ggplot about the data that you're working
with, and some basic aesthetics.
Like, if you're making a scatter plot,
here are the x and y variables.
Then you might overlay a summary.
For example, you might overlay a
statistical
summary like a smoother or progression
line.
Something like that.
And on top of that you might have some
metadata or extra annotation for the plot.
So the running example that I am going to
use for this lecture I spoke about
previously has come from the mouse
allergen and
asthma cohort study which was conducted
here in Baltimore.
Just very briefly, this is a study that
included Baltimore children, age 5 to 17.
They all had persistent athsma, with an
exacerbation in the past year.
And we're interested in a lot of the
environmental triggers for asthma
morbidity in this study.
So some of those, so one of those triggers
we're going to look at is indoor
air pollution, as as specified by
particulate matters,
so fine particulate matters which is PM
2.5.
And we'll also look at nitrogen dioxide,
NO2.
And I want to know whether BMI or body
mass index modifies the relationship
between PM 2.5 and asthma.
So do children with different BMIs have a,
respond differently in terms
of their asthma symptoms to exposure to PM
2.5.
So that's the kind of basic question that
we want to answer here.
So here's a, a basic plot.
I made this using the qplot function.
You can see the code down there at the
bottom.
And and the basic idea is I plotted the
relationship between, I've taken the
kind of scientific question in the
previous
slide, and translated that into a plot.
So I plotted the relationship between
nocturnal symptoms here.
So these are the
number of days in the past two weeks where
there were symptoms at night.
So, symptoms while sleeping for example.
And so, so the, I plotted the relationship
between nocturnal
symptoms and the in the log of the PM2.5
indoor value.
And you can see that, you know, roughly
speaking,
on the left side we have all the normal
weight children and there doesn't seem to
be a
very strong relationship between log PM2.5
and nocturnal symptoms.
Now the right side we have the overweight
or obese children and
there seems to be an increasing
relationship between PM 2.5 and symptoms.
And so you can see that there's perhaps
some evidence of an interaction between
the BMI
and PM 2.5, because the relationship
between PM
2.5 and symptoms appears to differ by BMI
status.
So, of course, in order to formalize this,
you'd probably want to fit some
sort of model, do a little bit more
thorough analysis, of course, and adjust
for various things.
But we're going to stick, stick here with
this plot for the moment.
So you can make this plot very easily with
the qplot
function and by adding things like facets
and geoms, to the plot.
But I'm going to recreate this plot using
the
kind of more, the, the lower level ggplot
framework.
And so how do we build this up layer by
layer?
First, so first we start with
the data, right?
So here I've got a little excerpt of the
data frame.
And you can see that there are three
variables here.
There's logpm2.5, there's BMI category,
and that's
two levels, there's normal weight and
overweight.
And then I have the number of days with
nocturnal symptoms.
So that's going to be a number between 0
and 14, because it's over the last two
weeks.
And so you can see, so the data are very
important in
any ggplot graphic, because almost
everything that you put on the plot
is a, can be thought of as some sort of
data.
And then in the first, in the next line
here I've got my initial call to ggplot.
You can see I just call ggplot and I give
it the data frame.
I give it a pair of aesthetics.
I give it the x and the y variables, which
are logpm2.5 and NocturnalSympt.
And then, and then I save this to a plot,
to an object that I call g.
And if I call summary on this object, you
can see, I get, it shows you what the
data are, shows you what the the mapping,
the aesthetic mapping is and
it shows you some, something about
faceting,
which, in which case there's no faceting.
So, the, that's null.
So, you can always call summary on a
ggplot object and it'll give you
a quick kind of list of what's in this
plot and what are the data.
Now, the important thing to realize is
that I, I haven't made a plot yet.
There's no pic, if you run this code,
there will be no picture on your screen
yet.
So, for example, if here I, I called
ggplot, and if I, if I say
print g, I immediately get an error,
because
it says there's no layers on this plot.
And so, what does that mean?
It basically just says it doesn't know how
to, how to draw the data yet.
In the sense that it doesn't know if you
want points, it doesn't know if you want
lines or tiles or other kinds of polygons
or
shapes, and so it doesn't have enough
information yet
to draw the plot on the screen.
So the next line here, I add, so notice I
use the plus operator
here, so you can literally add things to
your plot by using the plus operator.
And so when I add the geom_point function,
this
and I save it to a new object called p.
So my new, this p object is also a ggplot
graphic, but it's got this geom_point
thing added to it.
Now when I print that out and print that
out,
I get a plot, I get a picture on the
screen.
So notice that the geom_point function was
called with no arguments.
I didn't have to tell it about the data, I
didn't have to
tell it where the points were, I didn't
have to tell it anything.
So, there are a bunch of defaults that it
will,
that will get used, but the point is that
the original
ggplot object, which is encoded in this g
object, has all
the information that, that, that, that the
geom_point function will need.
And so I don't have to separately
specify it again.
So, I don't, in this first example here I
saved the modified
object to something called p, but you,
you, don't have to do that.
I, I, could have just said g plus geom
point
and then the plot will have auto printed
to the screen.
So you can use auto printing, or if you
want to save the object, you can.
So here's the plot, and I, and with the
point layer added on to it.
So I reproduced the code down here at the
bottom, just for your reference, and
you can see that the default for the
points, are a solid circle, filled circle.
And and so I used the default because I
didn't specify anything different.
So here, here are the data.