Hi, everyone, this lesson is going to be
about ggplot2 or the ggplot2 package.
And we're going to, I'm going to talk
about how to
do some basic plots using the ggplot2
package and what it's about.
And in this, in the next lecture I'll talk
a little bit in more detail
about how it's designed and how you
can make extensions to various ggplot2
plotting functions.
So the first question very basic.
You know, what is ggplot2?
Basically it's a package
in R that you can download from CRAN.
And and it implements what's called the
grammar of graphics, which is originally
written by
Leland Wilkinson and it is described in a,
in a book called the Grammar of Graphics.
Now the Grammar of Graphics is a
description of how
kind of graphics can be broken down into
abstract concepts.
You can, so think of the grammar of a
language like English.
You have things like verbs and nouns and
adjectives.
And so
the question is, you know, what are the
verbs, nouns, and adjectives of a data
graphic?
And the Grammar of Graphics kind of
describes kind of those basic elements
so that you can put them together to make
new types of graphics.
Just like you could take a verb and a noun
and an
adjective and make a new sentence that
maybe no one's ever heard before.
You could take the grammar of graphics and
put together various aspects
of plots and make a graphic that no one's
ever seen before and
so that's the basic idea.
It's a very powerful concept to kind of
organize all kinds of data graphics.
And until recently there was no specific
implementation for it
in R, but Hadley Wickham who when he was a
graduate
student at Iowa State implement the
Grammar of Graphics as an
R package called ggplot and its current
implementation is called ggplot2.
So one could think of this as almost
a third graphic system in R.
Even though it's based, is built upon the
grid graphic system which is, which comes
with R.
It's kind of a third mode of, of plotting
that has become very popular.
So if you think of the first mode as like
the base plots using functions like plot,
and hist, and
boxplot, and then the second mode as the
lattice plots
so using XY plot and these kinds of
trellis type functions.
And then the third mode is ggplot.
So you get the package from CRAN.
You can, you can use install.packages.
It installs on all almost all sys...I
imagine on all systems.
You can go to the ggplot website which is
ggplot2.org.
And so the nice thing about ggplot is
that, is that, is that it is based
on this grammar of graphics, and so, it,
in a sense, there's a theory of the
graphics.
So you can take this theory and kind of
reassemble the different pieces to make
new types of plots.
And as Hadley Whitcomb says in his book,
you know, the basic idea
is that you want to shorten the distance
from the mind to the page.
So if you have some data that you're
looking at, And you want,
and you thin of a way that you want to
visualize that data.
You want to be able to rapidly take those
ideas and turn them into a picture on your
screen.
So, from the GG plot two book,
this sentence kind of summarizes the basic
idea.
But the idea is that, the grammar tells us
the statistical graphic is mapping from
data to aesthetic attributes.
So color, shape and size.
- of geometric objects, so, points, lines,
and bars, and the plot may also
contain statistical transformations of the
data and
is drawn on a specific coordinate system.
So, we have things are that, we have a
mapping from data to aesthetics, geometric
objects, we have statistics.
Now we have a coordinate system.
So in this lecture I just want to talk
about
the qplot function which is kind of the
most basic
function and it's probably the best place
to start for
someone who is transitioning from say the
base plotting system.
So in the base plotting system you know
the work horse function
is the plot function and so qplot which
you can think of as
standing for quick plot Is kind the work
horse function for for
GD plot and its analogous to the plot
function and the base system.
So one
key difference that you have to get used
to when you're using
GD plot is that typically when you make a
plot and you pass
data to the q plot function you want to
tell it where the
data comes from and the data will always
come from a data frame.
So a data frame is going to be.
So, your data have to be organized in a
data frame.
And then when you plot variables those
variables are going to come from the data
frame.
Now, you don't have to specify a data
You can
if you don't specify a data frame the the
cue plot function or
all the plotting functions will, will look
for the data in your workspace.
But it's generally a good idea to specify
the data frame.
That way when you read the code that
generated
the plot You know exactly where the data
came from.
So then so the data frame is
very important to organize before you
start plotting.
Once you start plotting the plots are made
up of aesthetics
and geoms and so aesthetics are things
like the size, shape,
and color of things.
Points and the geoms are sort of
the objects that you're pointing, plotting
I'm sorry.
So are you plotting points Are you
plotting
lines, are you plotting bars, you know,
whatnot.
One aspect that's important for the qplot
function, and also is similarly
important when you're using lattice
functions,
is the idea of using factor variables.
So factors are very important because they
indicate subsets of your data.
So if you imagine you have a data frame or
you have a y variable and a x
variable and then a factor variable the
factor will
indicate subsets of your data in the data
frame.
So for example you might have factor that
indicates the gender.
So you have a bunch of
males and a bunch of females.
So those are subsets of your data and you
might want to plot a certain relationship
divided by
the various subsets or you might want to
color
certain points, depending on whether
they're male of female.
And so the categories that are indicated
by various
factor variables can be useful for
annotating a plot.
And so, one aspect, so one thing that's
important about this feature is that, is
that when
you have factor variables in a data set,
you want to make sure that they're
properly labeled.
So it's usually not useful to label a
factor variable
as one, two, and three, even if you have
three categories.
One, two, and three is not particularly
informative.
Usually you want to label them with the
more informative labels
so that you know what those factor
variables are trying to encode.
Now the qplot function is a fairly
straight forward function
to use.
I think it's very easy to pick up.
It hides a lot of the details of, of what
ggplot is doing underneath which is fine
for many cases.
But the ggplot function is really kind of
the core function of the system.
It's very flexible and you can use it in
combination
with a lot of things that g, that qplot
can't do.