In this video I just want to talk
about an example of exploratory analysis,
just to show
kind of the tools that you might want to
use when you're just starting out looking
at data.
So a lot of these things are basic things
that we've
covered you know like one dimensional
plots, two dimensional plots, basic
summaries.
Exploratory plots just to get a sense of
what the data will
look like, and what you might be able to
do with it.
Now the first thing of course, any time
you look start to look at data is
you have to have a kind of a basic idea in
mind of what you're looking for.
This could come in the form of a
hypothesis or even more generally just in
the basic question, you know what are you
trying to answer with this data set?
So the data set I'm going to use right now
for this example,
comes from the U.S. Environmental
Protection
Agency and it involves air pollution
monitoring
data from the United States.
In particular we're looking at fine
particulate
matter air pollution that's in the air.
So particulate matter is, is just a fancy
word for dust.
So this is just dust that's in the air and
it's
it's a, it's of concern because we inhale
air all the time.
And along with the air we inhale the dust
and it may have certain health effects on
populations.
So one of the important pie,
pieces of legislation in the last four
decades in
the United States has been the Clean Air
Act.
And the Clean Air Act has been designed to
reduce, the levels of air pollution in the
United States.
And so one of the questions that you might
want to ask uh,when it comes
to these kinds of data is, are air
pollution levels lower now than they were
before?
Right, so it's a very basic question.
It's fairly general.
We can, we can look at it in a variety
of different ways, and so we're going to
look at it in a very specific way.
We're going to look at a fine particle air
pollution.
And so this, fine particle air pollution
was, started being measured in 1999.
And it's currently being measured today.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to look at data from 1999.
And, and look at the fairly recent data
from 2012.
And I want to answer the very basic
question.
Are the
levels on average lower in 2012 than they
were in 1999?
And so.
The nice thing about air pollution data in
the United States is that the EPA collects
all this data and makes it essentially all
available on their website so it's freely
available.
I'll put the URL up on the website and you
can download as much or
as little as you want, so what I've done
is I got the EPA website and
I've just literally downloaded the zip
files.
For 1999 and 2012 for fine
particulate matter is, sometimes called
PM2.5, alright?
So let's take a look at the, just the, the
basic data files that you get.
So in this directory here, I've got.
The the, the two files for 1999 and 2012.
Now, I should say that the, the original
files are zip files.
And each of the zip files come with two
things.
One is a text file, which is .txt
extension
and another is a PDF file which contains
some documentation.
So this is just the raw file that I
downloaded from the EPA website.
I haven't done anything to it.
So we're, let's just take a look at a
couple lines of let's say the 1999 file.
Right, so I'm going to take a look at
this.
And so one thing you can see is that
there's,
it's a little bit messy here, but one
thing that's you
can see if I just pull this out a little
bit,
is that there's basically one record per
line in this file.
The first record here is kind of the
header.
And it tells you the names.
Basically gives you the names of the
different columns.
You can see each column
is separated by a kind of vertical line
here.
So that's nice to see.
You see that every record here begins with
RD.
All right, so these are called RDs.
That indicates kind of the type of record.
And that corresponds to the heading in the
RD here, a heading over here.
There's another type of heading here that
corresponds to
RC records, which are, which are these
guys over here.
And if there were any RC records in
this file, then they would have those
type, that
heading.
I don't believe that there are any RC file
records in this
file, but we can just double check that by
using a quick grep.
So let's take a look at if any records
start with RC.
And nope, not for that one.
Let's take a look at 2012.
And
none for that.
So these are all RD records and so we can
take, we
can use the RD headers to indicate one of
the various columns okay.
And so some of these columns are not
going to be particularly important to us,
but some
of the things we're going to want to know
are
for example, what state, the, the record
comes from.
The county.
The site ID indicates the kind of monitor
within
that county, and then most importantly is
the sample value.
So that tells us what, that's the actual
kind of mass
of PM2.5 being micrograms per meter cubed,
so that is going
to be very important and because we want
to see the
le, if those levels have gone down between
199 and 2012.
And the date of collection might also be
important too Now there are a number of
other
things that are indicate you of certain
records may
have problems but we're not going to worry
about
those at the moment.
Those kinds of things may come in, and
maybe
important later on in a, in a more
in-depth analysis.
So let's start at R here, so okay.
And the first thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to read in
the data for 1999 and so we're just
going to call it pm0.
Zero meaning kind of like the first one
and then, I'll name the second
one pm1 or something.
So I'm just used a straight read table
here.
I'm going to give it the 1999 file.
And what, first thing I'm going to, do is
I'm going to ignore the lines
that start with the hash symbol and I'll
figure, I'll pick those up later.
I'll say header equals false and then sep
equals remember it's solid line here and
then the missing values are indicated in
this
file which is the blank string all right.
Now read those in you can see That happens
relatively quickly.
Let's take a look.
It's always good to, you know, to check
to see, you know, how many dimensions you
got.
It's got about 117,000 rows 28 columns.
Let's take a look at the first few rows
here.
And you can see that I don't have the
headers for the columns.
So, I'll get those in a second.
But you can see that they're all using
different columns.
And remember the first column was this RD
record indicator.
And there are a lot of missing values here
which
are not that important right now.
So one thing of what I want to do is kind
of get the column names, for each
of these columns so that we don't have to
refer to them by, you know, V1 V2.
So if you recall the column names come
from the very first line in the file.
So I'm just going to read one line.
The first line, so, you can use read lines
for that.
And I'm going to give it the file name and
it's going to tell us to read one line.
Okay, so I've print out c
names here, you can see first of all, its
just a string and it hasn't been split,
you know, using the separator cause I
didn't use
read dot table I just read the line
directly.
So the first thing I'm going to have to do
is split all the, all the names out.
So I can use strsplit for that.
I
split on the cell line, and it's a fixed
pattern, not a regular expression.
So now if I print out cnames, you can see,
I get
a character vector containing, for each
element, it has the column name.
Now, strsplit actually returns a list
back, and so
you're just going to want the first
element of this list.
So now I'm going to assign the column
names to this
table to be the first value of this list
here.
So now if I take a look at this data frame
you can see that
that all the column names are basically
there.
Now, one of the things that you'll notice
is that these company
column names are not valid because they
have spaces in them for example.
And so one thing you can do to fix that is
to use the make dot names function.
And the make dot names basically takes an
arbitrary string and makes,
turn it into a valid name, column name for
a data frame.
So now if I take
a look at the first few lines here.
You can see that it's replaced the spaces
with dots.
So now all of these are kind of valid
column names for a data frame.
So they'll be easier to reference in
future kind of modeling or analysis
functions.
So the first thing I'm going to want to do
is take out
the PM2.5 variables that's, remember
that's the sample value column right here.
And you'll see the first, the first three
values here are missing, but then we've
got 8.841.
14.9,
etcetera.
And those are in units of micrograms per
meter, cubed.
So let's take a look at that columns, pull
it out, we'll
call it X zero here and I'll just plot the
sample value column.
Let's see what it is first.
It's a numeric column, that's good, it
should be numeric.
Let's run a str on it.
okay, so we got 117,421 values in the
numeric vector.
Still a little summary.
So you get a five number summary of this
data.
So you can see the median is 11.5
micrograms per meter cubed.
The maximum goes up to 157, which is quite
a high level for a daily value.
And there also some missing values here.
So let's see, and so 13,000 missing
values.
Let's see, kind of roughly what that means
in terms of the proportion, so we see
is.na on this and you can see that about
11% are missing.
So we come across and one interesting
feature about this data
set which is that there are a number of
missing values.
And so, one thing you have to ask yourself
is, okay, are missing values something
that, that I need
to worry about, for the question that I'm
interested in answering.
Remember, we want to, we want to get a
sense of,
you know, is, are, in general, is the
whole
country, does the whole country have lower
air pollution
levels in, in 2012 than it did in 1999?
See, so the question is, you know, does an
occasional missing value on a
given day in a given county or monitor, is
that going to make a big difference?
In particular, is having 11%
of your values missing going to make a big
difference in your analysis?
So, that's something to think about.
Missing values can play a very different
role, depending
on what kind of question you're trying to
answer.
And so you have to, you don't always,
although missing values
can be very inconvenient, a lot of the
times, they don't
always cause a problem in the, what kind
of question you're
trying to, depending on what type of
question you're trying to answer.
All right.
So now we've got the 1999 data.
Let's read in the 2012 data here.
So I'll take, I'll call it pm1, I'll
read.table it.
And
And we'll do the same kind of [UNKNOWN]
approach.
I'll comment out [UNKNOWN] these rows.
Header equals false.
Sep equals the [UNKNOWN].
And then any strings like that, okay.
So,
one thing you'll notice is that this is
taking
quite a bit longer than reading in the
1999 file.
One of the one of the issues is that PM
2.5 monitoring only just began in 1999.
So there were very few monitors at that
time.
Of course, over the years The monitoring
has increased, and so now in 2012 there's
a much bigger monitoring network available
and
so there are more, going to be more
observations.
So let's take a look at how many
observations
exactly we have here.
You can see, it's quite a bit more,
there's, there's one, about 1.3 million
records here as opposed to the, you know,
the 117,000 records that we had before.
So that may be a bit of a problem in and
of
itself, but we, I'll kind of put that to
the side for now.
So one thing I know is that the two files
have the same column name, so you can
see they both have 28 columns and I know
that the, the column names are going to be
the same.
They're both Rd records.
So I can just give the names for this data
frame to be the same as the other one.
So we make that names here
again.
And you can see if I take a look at the
first few rows.
Oops all the columns here.
So you can see the there, the data are now
2012, and the sample values here are the
pm 2.5 values.
So I'm going to grab the pm 2.5 values
from here.
And let's take a quick check on what we
have here.
That's a numer vector, a numeric vector,
4.3 million elements.
So that looks good.
So now let's do a quick comparison of the
2012 and the 1999 data.
So I'll do a summary on x1.
I'll do a summary on x0.
So that's interesting.
So you can see that in the 2012 data, the
median is about 7.3.
In the 1999 data, the median's about 11.5.
So there does appear on average to be a
decrease
in the levels for the whole country in, in
pm 2.5.
And notice that there are quite a few
missing values in the 2, 2012 data set.
We can take a look at what proportion that
is.
and.
Oh.
It's only.
See.
It's only about 5%.
So that actually, as a percentage of the
total, there's
actually fewer missing values in 2012 than
there were in 1999.
So that's interesting to know.
5% missing is probably not that big of a
deal.
And so, let's take a look at.
So it's.
So on first glance, it appears that, The
the, the [UNKNOWN] five levels have gone
down over the years.
And so, that's good, that's good news for
public health.
Let's take a look, let's see if we can
take
a look at a plot, a visual representation
of this data.
So, let's take a look at a box plot.
Let's see, boxplot(x0,x1).
And let me bring this up.
So it's a little hard to look at.
There's a lot of skew in the pm2.5_ data
and
so there, these are data are both, they're
right skewed
and so you can see that it's kind of all
smooshed down near zero but then there's
some very large values.
One thing you'll notice is that the
maximum value
here is 909 which is an extremely high
level.
In fact it's so high.
For the United States we might think that
it's perhaps an error, or something wrong
with it.
909 micrograms for me queued, although not
impossible,
we observe it in other parts of the world.
We generally don't observe it in the
United States, unless, for
example, in some special or strange
occurrence So maybe we'll think, we'll
think about that value a little bit later
eh since we're
not really focused on extremes right now,
we're looking at the medians.
So one way to kind of fix this box plot is
to take a log of these guys
so let's take the log of X,0 base ten log
[NOISE] and
that will hopefully kind of even out the
box plot a little bit.
So here you can see the the 1999 data is
right here.
S you can see the mean is about a log
equal to 1 which is roughly 10.
Micrograms per meter cubed.
And then, you can see that the black line,
which was
the median of this box, that does go down
quite a bit.
Remember, this is on a log scale, so even
a
small change can be a big change in the
absolute scale.
But one
thing that you'll notice is that the
spread of the data has also increased too.
So even though the average levels have
gone down, there
are more kind of extreme values in the
later data.
And so that's interesting not exactly sure
what to make of it.
So the next thing you'll want to take a
look at we noticed in
the summary of 2012 data there's negative
values here, so that's a little bit
strange.
So,
one of the things about measuring TMP.5,
is that we measure the mass of it.
Kind of per unit of airflow.
So basically the idea is that there's a
filter and
there's air being sucked through the
filter, and then the particles
collect on the filter and we weigh those
filters to
see how much, how many particles have
landed on the filter.
And so because of the way that it's
measured, you really can't have a negative
measurement.
You can't have negative mass.
And so if there's a negative value for.
The PM 2.5 variable.
That's a little strange, that's a little
unusual.
So let's take a look, we can take a look
at that.
And see kind of, maybe get a sense of
what's going on.
So, let's, let's pluck out the values.
So, let's take a look one more time at the
summary.
Let's take, let's pluck out the values
that happen to be negative.
So, I'll, I'll create a logical vector.
That is true or false depending on, you
know,
whether the, the 2012 PM 2.5 value is
below 0.
So, you take the stir on this.
You'll see that this is true false vector.
So if I take the sum of this.
NA RM equals true.
You'll see that there are about 26,000
values.
That are below zero or negatives, so
that's a
little bit strange, we see what's the
proportion this is.
So about 2% of the values, this is not
really large number of values.
So maybe something that we don't even care
about but but maybe worth taking a look
at.
So, in particular maybe interesting to see
whether there
are negative values at certain times of
the year.
Or maybe the only negative values occur at
certain
locations or times.
So let's take a look at the dates of the
measurements.
So we'll pull up the dates column.
And you can take a look at this.
First of all you'll notice that it is an
integer vector.
Right?
So they're, these are coded as integers by
default.
Which is not going to be as useful for us,
so we want to be able to convert them into
dates.
And so one thing you'll notice is that
they're in
the year, so the first four digits of the
year,
second is the month and the second is the
day, right?
So here we've got 2012 and then January
and then 28th, right.
And so let's take a look, let's convert
those guys to date Variable as
a date and it's going to be in the year,
month, day format.
Okay.
Now's it's a reasonably long vector so
it's probably
going to take a few seconds on a
reasonable computer
Now, take a look at the dates vector.
So you can see now it's in the date
format.
So let's take a look at just the histogram
of
the dates to see kind of where the
collection occurs.
And we can do it by month.
And you can see that
The most of the, most of the, the hi, the
measurements are occurring in kind of the
in the winter months here.
So winter and spring months here.
So let's see where the negative values
tend to be.
So we'll do hist on dates and negative.
So this only makes a histogram of the
dates where the negative values occur.
Oops.
And I say month.
And you could see that the the negative
values tend to occur, seem to occur more
often in the in the
late, in the in the December, January,
February types of months.
There's a little bit of a spike here, in
April, May, June type period.
So, it's interesting to see that there
aren't many
negative values here in the summer months
here, and
so it's not entirely clear why, you know,
what
this tells us but it may be worth
investigating.
One issue with PM2.5 is that many areas of
the country.
It tends
to be very low in the winter.
And high in the summer.
And so typically when, when when pollution
values are high, they're easier to
measure.
And when they're low, they're harder to
So maybe some of the negative values are
just kind of
a measurement error when the values tend
to be very low.
So but given that it's only 2% of the
data, I'm
not going to spend too much time worrying
about it at the moment.
It may be something that we worry about
later.
So one of the things that I think would be
interesting to do is, you
know, rather than look at the, the air
pollution levels for the entire country
and say.
Okay, well the median for the entire
country has gone down
between 1999 and 2012, why don't we pick
out one monitor.
See whether or not we can see a change or
a decrease in the level just at that one
location, and
so and that way we can kind of control for
the fact that you know there's different
monitors at different times.
Now one thing that we have to do, is we
have to find the monitor that was kind of
out there
in 1999, and was also out there in 2012
it's
because then you have the Net, which
changed quite a bit.
And so, we're going to pick a state and
then
try to find a monitor in that state to
see whether or not, you know, to see
whether
or not, you know, the pollution levels
have gone down.
So I'm just going to pick New York state
because that's where I'm from.
And let't try to take a little, let's try
to find a monitor
there that we can, where we can look at
the change in the levels.
So, the first thing I'm going to
do, is I'm going to subset the PM data to
look at the
all of the kind of monitors in, in, in New
York state.
So I'm going to take So I'm
going to take the pm0,
data frame, and I'm going to subset on
state code equals 36, which I
just happen to know is New York state,
because I do this a lot.
And I'm going to pluck out the county
code.
And the site ID columns.
And then, I'm going to do the same thing
for the 2012 data set here.
Okay, so
and then, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to.
So, if you take a look at site zero, you
can see it's a two column data frame.
And it just had the, the county code and
the site ID.
What I'm going to do is create a special,
kind of variable that's
base, that's just the county code and the
site id pasted together, right?
And so we can literally use the paste
function to do that.
So I'm going to kind of replace this guy
with paste, and I'll take the first column
and
the second column And separate it with a
period.
And then I'm going to do the same thing
for the 2012 data, alright?
So now if you take a look at site zero its
character vector, you can see that the,
it's the kind of county.
and the site ID.
If you look at this it's kind of the same
thing, right.
So one thing that you'll notice is that
the
2012 vector, it only has 18 elements and
so
there are only 18 counties and site id
combinations
whereas the 1999 data had 33 of those
combinations.
So the only thing, so basically what we
want to do
is we want to see is well where.
What is the intersection between these two
guys?
So where you know which which county slash
monitor ID numbers exist in both sets?
So we could just use the intersect
functions for that,
and I'll assign it to an object called
both.
So these are the monitors that are in both
the 1999 and 2012 data sets.
So we can print this out.
You can see that there are There are ten
monitors, ten county/monitors that are in
both data sets.
So, that's good at least that there are a
few that we can look at across the time
period.
now, one of the, one of the things that
would
be useful, is if we chose the monitor that
is
that first of all, in both time periods,
but also
had a lot of observation that we could
look at.
So lets take a look at how many
observations are
in each of these monitors, at each of
these time periods.
Okay.
So so the first thing you want to do is
you want to count,
you want to figure out how
many observations are available at each
monitor.
So I am going to create a new variable
called county.site.
Which is just the,
what we just created so its, its the
county code.
Pasted with the site ID.
I'm putting this in the original data
frame here.
I'm going to do it for the 2012 also.
And
what I want to do is I want to subset this
data frame to be just New York state.
So I'm going to subset pm0 to be state
code 36.
And county site is also, is one of these
special monitors which is in both in both
data sets.
Alright, do that for this guy here.
And now what I'm going to, so if you take
a look at this, it's
the same data frame, but it's only the
rows that are in New York City.
So, you can see that the state code here
now is 36.
Right?
So, So what I want to do is I want to
split this data frame by the kind of
monitor.
So, I want to split it into separate data
frames by each monitor
and then count how many observations there
are in each of them.
So I'm just going to do a split this
data frame by the, this county site
variable.
[SOUND]
Right?
And now actually that was not particularly
useful because it just spit out
a whole list of data frames, and I don't
really know what happened there.
So what I want to do is I want a S supply
over
all these data frames and count the number
of rows that there are.
Okay, so that gives me the number of
observations.
That are in each of these data frames.
So you can see that, for example, county
one,
site 12, had 61 observations, and county
one, site five had 122.
So then I'm going to want to do the same
thing for the later period.
Excuse me.
Had to change this, too.
And you could see now for there are for
there county one websites hub only had 31
observations.
In 2012 rather than 61 in the 1991 data
site
so I think that the county that I'm going
to.
The county slash monitor that I'm going to
pick here is going to be county 63.
And the monitor 2008.
So let's take a look at those guys and see
what we can look at in terms of pm trends.
So I'm going to call a new data-frame
called pm1sub, so I'll subset it, pm1.
[SOUND]
County code is 63.
And the site ID is 2008.
Alright.
And then I'm going to do
the same thing for the 1999 data.
I know that they're both there.
And I look at pm 1.
I know there's 30 observations, and for pm
0, so there should be 122.
So there you go.
So, so the thing we're going to do now is
we're going to take each of these data
frames, and we're just going to plot the
data,
the pm 2.5 data, as a function of time.
So it's going to be like a little time
series here.
And on
the x axis is going to be the date and on
the y axis is, is going to be the level PM
2.5.
And we just want to get a, to visualize
whether or not we can see if the levels of
PM 2.5 have gone down over this kind of 13
year period at this particular modern.
Okay so we're going to make some plots to
do that.
So, the first thing we need to do is to
get the dates out so we can plot
the data as a function of date.
So dates, I'll create a dates
vector here from this pmsub data frame,
and get the pm2.5
data out.
[SOUND]
And so I make a plot of the dates.
You can see
well first thing you'll notice, is that
the
dates are not coded properly, they're
integers here.
And so we need to convert them into dates.
So I'm going to do that right now.
[SOUND]
And they're in year, month, day format.
So now if I make this plot again well
first
of all you can take a look at the new
variable.
And if I make this plot, so it's in date
format now.
And you can see now the plot makes more
sense,
the X axis is coded appropriately, and you
can see
that the data are kind of bouncing around
all over
the place, somewhere between four and 14
micrograms per meter, cubed.
So this is the 2012 data.
So let's do the same thing for 2000, for
1999.
We'll convert these guys to date format,
since we know we have to do that.
And let's make a little plot here.
Oops I didn't get
the PM2.5 data.
[NOISE]
Alright so let's make a plot of the 1999
data so you can see that again.
First of all you'll notice that, the
data are only actually recorded starting
in July,
through the end of the year.
So only about a half of the year of data
is collected there, and so, and
you can see that they range from roughly,
say, five micrograms per meter cubed, to
about 40.
Of course its a little hard to look at
the plots separately, so why don't we make
a plot.
That kind of puts both, both 1999 and 2012
on the same panel.
So so we need to use par for that, and
we'll say mfrow is, is 1, 2.
So this says 1 row, 2 columns.
And I'm going to adjust the margins a
little bit to create more space.
So I'll first of all plot the 1999 data on
the right, on the left hand side here.
I'll change the plotting character for
fun.
Alright.
And then I'll plot the I'm going to put a
little line here at the median, for that
year.
Okay.
So that gives me the median.
About maybe 10 points or so micrograms per
meter cubed.
So now lets plot the 2012 data.
And we'll plot the median.
Alright, so that's well that's a little
bit
unusual, it looks like the values are
going up.
Between the two years.
So actually, it's a little bit, because
you'll notice that the y-axis for
the 2012 data, is totally different from
the y-axis for the 1999 data.
And so even though it looks like it's
going up between
the two, periods, it probably actually is
going down, if you look
at the median here it's a little over ten
And the median
here is a little bit, is quite a bit under
ten actually.
And so
this picture is by itself is a little bit
misleading so what we need
to do is we need to put the two plots on
the same range.
So let's do that by calcul, calculating
the range
of the dataset with the with the range
function, alright?
So let's take a look at.
The range of x0sub and x1sub together.
And we'll remove the missing values.
You can see that it's between
three and 40 micrograms per meter cubed.
So let's assign that to this, to a
variable called rng.
And now we need to remake the plots to be
To, to kind of fix the range here.
So, I'll set par
just in case I, I don't need to do this
actually.
I'm supposed to plot the dates.
And pch equals 20.
But now I'm going to set y lim to be equal
to this range.
Okay?
And I'll set the ab line, h equals median.
All right, and then I'm going to do the
same thing but for the 2012 data.
And
remember, I'm going to, I'm going to keep
the range here to be the same.
And and I'll set the the horizontal line
here.
And now you can see it makes more sense,
right?
So, you can see that the horizontal line,
the median
is going down between the two years at
this monitor
and more interestingly actually for me is
the fact that
you can see there's a huge spread of
points here in
the 1999 data and there's a relatively
modest spread Of points for the 2012 data.
So what this, so what this means actually
is quite interesting.
Is that not only are the average levels
going down but
these extreme values are also coming down
across the years, too.
So now, so we, so on average we're kind of
breathing in lower levels of pollution.
But we don't get these huge spikes on a
daily basis, like we used to get in 1999.
So that,
those two kind of facts are quite
interesting, because
they, they kind of address two different
types of problems.
One is more of a chronic problem of
having,
I don't know, just on average very high
pollution levels.
And one is more of an acute problem where
you get
these really big spikes that can cause
different types of health problems.
And so we've reduced the average levels
and
the spikes at this monitor so that's quite
interesting.
So one thing I think so the last thing I
think I want to look at is to say well
lets not look at the whole country but its
also
not that useful to perhaps just look at
one monitor and.
So why don't we look at the individual
states in the country?
So we'll look at the individual states to
see how the individual states have
improved or not.
Across the years.
And one of the reasons why this is
important is because
the states are actually where a lot of the
implementation of the
regulations occur.
So, when the EPA sets the national
guidelines
for air pollution levels, it's up to the
state to figure out how it's going to
kind of come into compliance with those
guidelines.
And so, be useful to kind of develop a
summary at the state level.
To kind of see what's going on at this
kind of very important level.
Furthermore the State is some, somewhere
in
between the whole country and individual
monitor.
So what I want to do, is create
a plot that has kind of the value of state
averages
for 1999 and the state averages for 2012
and I just want
to connect the dots to connect each state
to see whether
it's going up or it's going down or maybe
staying the same.
So that's the kind of plot I want to make.
So let's let's figure this out,
so change my plot window here.
Back.
So [UNKNOWN] let's take a look remember
the the the data has a.
Has a column here which is the State Code
and
so, there, every, every state will have a
code there.
And so what I want to do is I want to take
the sample value here.
So, this is the PM 2.5 value.
And I want basically, I just want to take
the average value.
By state, right?
So, this is the kind of thing that's
going to require the T apply function.
Wh-, the T apply, remember, takes the mean
of a,
of a vector within subgroups determined by
another vector, right?
And so this is the perfect job for T
apply.
So, what I'm going to do, is I'm going to
take and
I'm going to create a vector that I'll
call Mean Zero.
So this is the mean of the 1999 data.
And I'm going to base it on the pm0
dataframe.
And I'm going to tapply
the sample value based on the state,
within subsets of the state code.
And I want to use the mean function.
And I'm going to get rid of missing values
here.
Okay.
So if I take a look at this guy now you
see that there are
there are 53 elements here and these are
the means of the individual states, okay?
If I take a summary you can see that
they range from 4.8 micrograms meter cubed
to 19.96.
OK.
So now we need to do the same thing for
the 2012 data.
So I'll just go up here.
Just change this to a one.
Same operation.
I take a summary of this data and I can
see that it ranges from about 4 to 11.
So and the
median is definitely lower.
The median in 1999 was 12 And the, this is
the state average.
This is kind of the median of all the
states.
And the median of all the states in 2012
is 8.7.
So now I want to create a data frame for
each of these guys that has kind of the
name of the state and the or the ID of the
state and their average pm2.5.
So I'm going to create a data frame called
D0.
A variable called state it's going to be
with the names of this guy and
then mean which is the value and do the
same thing for the later data.
So if you look at D zero you can see
that there's the state and then the mean,
d one.
It's also the state and the mean now I
just want to merge these guys together so
I can
use the merge function on d zero d one,
and I'm going to to merge it on the state
name,
typo there.
So if you look at the merged values there
are you can
see there are 52 rows and if you look at
the merge
you now you can see that the mean mean x
so this
corresponds to the 1999 value And this
corresponds to the 2012 value.
So, now I've got a data frame which is,
which has the state code.
It has one row for state.
And then each row,
there's the kind of state average for 1999
and the state average for 2012.
So, just basically what I want to do is
create a plot that
plots those state averages and then
connects, connects them with the line.
So, that's the last thing I'm going to do
here.
So I'm going to reset my par to be to just
one plot here.
Instead of a panel plot.
And then with this merge data frame, I'm
going to plot I know that there are 52
values.
So
I'm just going to plot the 1999 values.
On, in 1 column,
that's the, I, I'm in the
alright.
And I want to set the X [UNKNOWN] here, so
I want to make room, because I know I'm
going to plot the
2012 values later So I want to set the
xlim to
say, let's be and then like that.
Oops.
And alright, so you can see I've got my
1999 values right here.
And then I'm going to do the same thing
but instead of
plotting, I'm going to use points to add
the points for 2012.
And this
is the third column of the data frame.
And I don't need this xlim in here because
I'm using points.
And if I bring the plot over here, you can
see that I've got my
plot so [UNKNOWN] so you can see that the
data's kind of gone down quite a bit.
We saw this already in the, in the
individual monitor data.
So all we need to do now is kind of
connect the
dots here, and so we can use the Segments
function for that.
So we give the x coordinates the y
coordinates.
And then the, the second set of x
coordinates which will be 2012.
And there, now we can see.
Okay so
this is quite interesting, Now, we can see
that most of the states have gone down.
You can see this line here has gone down.
These lines here.
Some, some states have gone up.
And a, but the vast majority of these
states appear to be going down.
One thing you'll notice is that there
appear
to be some lines going off the chart here.
That's because I didn't set the y lim to
be equal to the full range of the data
set.
So we could have fixed that but I won't
bother with it right now, we can fix it
later.
But now we can see that each of the
states,
have, how, how, how they progressed over
the many years here.
So some states kind of have barely, really
moved at all, so this state right here.
Has barely really moved at all.
And the lines kind of connecting the dots
help us
see what the trends are at the individual
state level.
Alright so that's basically, that's kind
of a first exploratory
analysis of some air pollution data in the
United States.
As you were just to summarize the, the
basic question we were trying
to answer was, you know, have particular
matter levels decreased between 1999 and
2012.
And we looked at it for the whole country
between
1999 and 2012.
We looked at it for an individual monitor
between those
two time periods, and we looked at it for
individual states.
And so through a combination of, kind of,
summaries, five number
summaries, box plots, scatter plots,
things like that we can get
a very nice look at the data, right, and
get a
since of what kinds of questions we can,
can continue to ask.
And what kinds of things we should, we
should follow up on.
So that's just a, that's a base kind of a
simple case study
of how, of how to do exploratory analysis
and I hope you find it helpful.