This lecture's going to be about
constructing exploratory graphs which are
graphs that you make more or less for
yourself, so that
you can look at the data and explore kind
of what's
going on in, in the data sets that you're
looking at.
And so, I mean, the basic question that
we're trying to ask
here is, you know, why do we use graphs in
data analysis?
And there are a couple of different goals
that we want to achieve
here, you know, understanding the data
properties,
finding patterns in the data basic
patterns.
Maybe just suggest some modeling
strategies, you know?
Do we want to use a linear model or a
nonlinear model to debug an analysis?
So maybe you started doing an analysis,
and you
want to figure out, you know, what's going
wrong.
And then we want to communicate results,
too.
So we want to present things to people in
a graphical form.
And exploratory graphs are really about
the first four things on this list here.
So we want to basically understand
properties about our data,
we want to look at some basic patterns
suggest some
modeling strategies and and to debug an
analysis.
But in this particular lecture, we're not
going to
be talking much about how to build graphs
for communicating results, and we'll talk
about that
in a little bit later in other lectures.
So some of the characteristics of
exploratory graphs
are that they, they tend to be made very
quickly, so they are kind of made on the
fly as you are looking through the data.
You tend to a large number of them because
you want to look a
very different aspects of the data, you
know, look at lots of variables and
you have to go through them kind of one at
a time often.
And the goal is for you to develop a, as
the analyst, to develop a personal
understanding of the dataset.
And to get a sense of, you know, how how
it looks.
What are the properties, what are the
problems?
and, and what are the things that need to
be followed up?
It's just, just so you can get a sense of,
kind of what the data's looking like.
So you if you can think of an,
an, an underlying question essentially of
all exploratory
data analysis, it might be you know, what
do my data look like?
And so and so this is the goal for making
exploratory graphs and a lot of the things
that you typically
worry about, you know, later on in terms
of appearances of
a graph or how it's presented you don't
worry about now.
So things like the axes and the
legends are typically going to be cleaned
up later.
Things like and color and sizes are
primarily
used for, for you to kind of separate
information.
But you might,
if you were going to present this in a, in
a different setting for example in a
presentation or a talk you might think a
little bit more carefully about color and,
and size.
So, I, I just want to go through a
specific example in this lecture just so
we can talk about the various types
exploratory
graphs that you might make using a real
dataset.
So here this dataset is, it involves air
pollution ambient air pollution in the
United States.
And it comes from the US Environmental
Protection Agency,
which sets national ambient air quality
standards for outdoor air pollution.
And the particular type of air pollutant
we're going
to look at is called fine particle
pollution of pm2.5.
And the standard in the United States is
that the annual mean averaged
over three years at a given location
cannot exceed 12 micrograms per meter
cubed.
And so any state that exceeds this level
of 12 micrograms per meter
cubed when you take the annual mean and
average it over three years
is considered to be out of compliance with
the national standards.
And so there's data available for on pm2.5
from the US EPA's air quality system.
And so I've downloaded that data and
summarized
it here just for the purposes of this
presentation.
And the basic underlying question in this
exploratory analysis is just going to be
are
there any counties in the United States
that
exceed the national standard for fine
particle pollution?
And so
we have, we have monitoring data from many
counties
in the United States where air pollution
is a problem.
And we want to see whether or not they
exceed the
12 microgram per meter cubed standard,
that's, that's recently been set.
So the data here are available.
You can read the menus in the read.csv
function.
And I've put the code here so you can take
a look.
And here are the first couple lines of
this data frame.
And so there is the first column is the
level of pm2.5.
It's the, it's the annual average [COUGH],
sorry it's the,
it's the annual mean averaged over the
past three years.
So, a, actually it's the years 2008
through 2010 and
then the fips column that's the, it's an
identifier column that's
for the county.
And then the region is just whether,
whether
this county is in the east or the west.
The longitude and latitude, basically, is
a is,
is the locations of the monitor in that
county.
The longitude and latitude coordinates for
the monitor in that county.
So we basically remember this is the
underlying question is we
want to see do any of the counties exceed
the standard of,
of 12 micrograms per meter cubed?
Even in an exploratory analysis where
you're just kind of, you
know, looking through the data and seeing
if there are any problems.
You, you, you still want to have kind
of an underlying question that you're
thinking about in
the back of your mind, even if it's a
little bit of a vague question at this
moment.
Because the question that you ask will
drive your thinking about what the data
look like, and so something that may be a
problem for one type of question,
may be not a problem for a different type
of question.
So when you look through the data you
have to have a background question kind in
mind.
So, we want to see if counties exceed this
national ambient air quality standard.
So a couple of, so we can look at one
dimensional summaries
of the data, and here are a couple that I
list out.
One is a five number summary.
There's boxplots, histograms, density
plots and bar plots.
And I'll illustrate a few here.
So, I mean, the first
one is the five number summary which is
really not a plot at all, obviously.
But it's a, it's a summary of just some
particular aspects of a, of a, of a given
variable.
And so, the summary function in R can
produce the summary,
and actually it's the six number summary
because it includes the mean.
The traditional five number summary is the
minimum, the first quartile, the median,
the third
quartile, and the maximum, and the summary
function just puts the mean in there, too.
So here you see the median
is ten micrograms per meter cubed which is
under the standard.
The maximum is 18.4 which is over.
So, there must be some counties that
violate
the standard at least during this time
period.
And so and the things, you can see the
third quartile is
11, and the first quartile is 8.5, and the
minimum is 3.38 here.
So, here's a boxplot of the pm2.5
variable,
and I just I decided to color it blue.
And you can see that the median is about
ten, just as we saw in the five number
summary.
And you can see that there are a number of
counties
that appear to be over the 12 microgram
per meter cubed limit.
And then there are some, there are many
that are that are under it.
That are, so that are in compliance.
Here's a histogram of the same data.
And so the nice thing about the histogram
is that you get a little
bit more detail about you know, the shape
of the distribution of this variable.
And one
nice thing that I like to do is to put a
rug underneath the histogram.
So the rug basically plots all of the
points in your dataset that, along
underneath the histogram.
So you can see exactly where the points
are that make up the histogram.
And so you get, on the, on the one hand
you get the histogram
which is a summary, but you also get some
fine detail with the rug underneath.
So you can see, you know, where the
outliers
are, and where the bulk of the data are.
So you can see that the, the bulk of the
data seem
to be centered around ten or so.
But there are couple of outliers kind of
above beyond 15.
One thing you can do with a histogram is
change the breaks, the
number of essentially the number of bars
that are going into the histogram.
And so you can see in the previous slide
the bars are
kind of wider so the, the histogram is a
little bit smoother.
But in this slide I made the, the
bars smaller by setting the breaks equal
to 100.
And you can see
that you get a little bit more of a
rougher histogram.
And so one of the things that you have to
worry
about when, when you set the breaks
argument is that you
don't want the number to be to big so that
you
get lots of little bars and then the
histogram becomes very noisy.
Of course, you don't want the number to be
too small, because then you just
might get a few bars and you can't really
see the shape of the distribution.
So, it's, it's usually useful to play
around
with the breaks argument, just to adjust
the
number of histogram bars there are, so as
to get the histogram that you like the
best.
Here's the box plot that I showed you
before, but now I've overlaid some a
feature onto the plot, which is just a
horizontal line at the level of 12.
So number 12 is the national ambient air
quality
standard, and so I've overlaid the line
right at, right
at 12 just to get a sense of, you know,
how many what counties are above and below
the line.
So you can see the bulk of them, over 75
%,
are below the line because in the entire
blue box is below
that line.
And the upper end of the blue box is the
75th percentile or the third quartile.
So, that's useful for sumari-, for kind of
pointing out specific features.
You can do this on a histogram, too.
So here I've put a vertical line at, at
12, so that's the black line.
And I put a, another vertical line, which
is
in magenta, at the median just so you can
summarize.
You can see exactly where the median of
the distribution is.
That was easy to see in the box plot
because the box plot contains
the median as a feature.
But the histogram does not and so it's
sometimes nice
to put a vertical line in there to
highlight the median.
So you can see that again that the median
is below the
standard, but there are a number of
counties that are above it.
A barplot is another graphical summary for
categorical data.
And here I'm plotting the, the region
variable so that you can see how
many counties there are in the east and
how many there are in the west.
So you see that the, the majority of the
counties are in the eastern part of the
United States.
And the there are a little over a hundred
counties in the western part of the United
States.
And so that just summarizes this
particular variable which is a categorical
variable.