So the qu-, you might be wondering, well
where
do I come up with interesting palettes of
colors?
Well, you can always create your own
palette
of col-, colors, just that I did in
the previous slides, by say, by indicating
colors
like red, yellow, or anything in the
colors vector.
That you get when you've, when you call
the colors function.
But you might want to come up with some
more interesting colors, color palettes,
and that can be done using the color brew,
the RColorBrewer package in R.
So the RColorBewer package
is available on CRAN and all it does is it
provides a
set of interesting palettes that you can
use for different types of data.
And these are this, this package was
created from
work that was done by Cynthia Brewer,
who's at Penn
State and she's done a lot of work
researching
appropriate colors for, for creating maps
and for mapping data.
So, but these palettes can be quite useful
for
other types of data that don't really
occur on maps.
So the three types of palettes that you
can cre-, that you can get from
the color, RColorBrewer package are the
sequential
palettes, the diverging palettes and the
qualitative palettes.
So the sequential palettes are used for
data that are ordered.
You can think of this as being used for
numerical data or continuous data.
It doesn't have to be continuous but the
dat-, the
idea is that the data are ordered from low
to high.
But diverging palettes can be used
for data that kind of diverge, or they
deviate from something.
For example, if you have a bunch of data
and
you want to show the deviations from their
mean then you
might, so this way, in this sense that
there's data
that can be positive and there's data that
can be negative.
And they can, as they go away from
whatever that center point is, maybe that
center
point is zero, they can get bigger in
two different directions, maybe going
negative and going positive.
So that's a diverging
set of data, if you want to use a
diverging color palette to represent that.
The last color palette is the qualitative
palette which is
just used to, to represent data that are
not ordered.
So these can be factors or categorical
data that
don't have any specific ordering, they
just have different values.
So so the palette information that you get
from the, RColorBrewer package
can be passed to functions like colorRamp
and colorRampPalette to be used
in the plotting functions in R.
So these are the various palettes that are
found in the RColorBrewer package.
The top set here these are the sequential
palettes and you can see that
they basically go from light to dark for
as you go from left to right.
But they go, they travel through a
different set of colors on each
palette so the top one here kind of goes
from yellow, orange to red.
And then the bottom one here is called the
Blues palette.
It just goes, goes by light blue to a dark
blue.
So these are used for ordered data,
for numerical data that have a low and a
high.
The second set of palettes here, is the,
is the
qualitative palettes and these are used to
represent categorical datas.
And you can use, see that the colors
in the palettes don't really have any
specific ordering.
They don't go from light to dark.
They don't go, they don't go from any
specific order.
But they do, so they just have a certain
set of colors
associated with them, and they, and each
palette has basically a theme.
some,
some palettes are kind of bolder than
others,
and some are more on the pastel side.
The last set of colors, you can see, are
the diverging palettes.
And the colors in this palette, you can
see
that they are kind of light in the middle.
And as you go from left to right they get
darker in different color ranges.
And so, you can think of that, the
left being negative and the right being
positive.
And so these are the, and that's how they
diverge.
And they try, and
they, again they travel through different
sets of
colors here, so the top one here goes from
a red as you, from the left all the way to
a kind of purple-blue on the right.
And then the bottom one here goes from
brown on
the left to kind of blue or green on the
right.
So you can choose your palette here,
depending
on what kind of color scheme you prefer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So the ColorBrewer package can be loaded
into lib-, after you
install it using the install.packages
function, you can view library
RColorBrewer.
And then the brewer.pal function is really
the only
useful function in the package and it
takes two arguments.
The first argument is the number of colors
that you want for your palette.
And this is usually small, it'll be, you
know, two, three or four.
You don't need that many blotches on your
palette for the primary colors.
And then the second
argument is the name of the palette.
And the name of the palette really is not
easy to remember, you just have to look in
the help page for brewer.pal and it will
list
all of the names of the palettes that are
available.
So, here I'm using a blue-green type of
palette
and I want three different colors from
that palette.
So now, you can see that the character
vector that it returns has three colors
and
they each have a mix of red, green, and
blue, and if you're fluent in hexidecimal,
you'll know what these values are.
But it's not really important to know
exactly what the, the
colors are, you'll be able to see them on
the screen.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm going to
pass this palette of colors into the
colorRampPalette function.
and, and it's going to return a function
that I'm going to call pal.
So now, I'm going to create the image of
this volcano using the image function.
But I'm going to, instead of using the
heat colors or the topo colors palette,
I'm going to use this palette that I got,
from the Brewer, ColorBrewer package.
And so, I'm going to specify that I want
20 different
colors to be in, to be represented in this
image.
So that the 20 colors are going to come,
they're going to be interpolated from this
blue-green palette.
So the resulting image looks something
like this.
And you can see that as it gets, as it
gets higher, the
ima-, the colors get darker and more green
and at the lower elevations,
the colors are lighter and more blue.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Another function that uses the ColorBrewer
palettes
is the smoothScatter function which comes
with R.
And, this function is particularly useful
if you have to
plot a lot of, make a scatter plot of a
lot
of different points and you don't want to
just have a
bunch of dots on the screen that are
overlapping each other.
So here, I'm plotting 10,000 points.
And if I were to just plot this on the
screen using the
plot function I would get a mess of points
that are kind of overlapping
each other, it's kind of hard to see the
details.
So the smoothScatter function, what it
does is
it creates a histogram, a 2D histogram, of
the points in your plot, and it just
plots the histogram using a certain set of
colors.
The default set of colors that it uses is
the blues colors.
Oh sorry, the blues palette in the
RColorBrewer
package which is a sequential palette and
it
gets kind of darker blue as you get higher
and lighter blue as you get lower.
So, the darker
blue areas of this plot are the high
density.
So that's where all, most the points are
in the high density region and
the lighter blue parts of the plot are the
lower density regions of the plot.