I just want to make one quick note about
the
version of R that you'll be using in this
class.
You might notice from some of the videos
that the videos are made using R
version 3.0.3, which was the most current
version at the time the video was made.
However as of now, the most current
version of R is 3.1.1.
And so I encourage you to install that
version of R.
Which should be the default version that
you find when you go to the R website.
So don't try digging around for older
versions of R.
You won't need them.
So I, in general, I always encourage
people to use the
latest version of software, because those
will have the latest features.
And they will have hopefully fixed a bug
that may have been present in earlier
versions.
So, for this version of the course use R
version 3.1.1.
Thanks a lot.