In this case study, I'm going to talk more
about exploratory data analysis
techniques, and how to
use them, on a data set that involves
using smart phones, to, kind of, predict
human activities.
So remember, just any exploratory data
analysis, you have to
have a sense of kind of like, what you're
looking for,
what might, and what might be the kind of
the
key priorities that you want to get outta
your data set.
And so that will help you guide kind of
what you looking at and how you
approach it um,remember that,the basic
idea
of exploratory data analysis is you want
to kind of produce a rough cut of the kind
of analysis that you
ultimately maybe want to do so maybe this
isn't going to be perfect
its not going to have all the right bells
and whistles to it.
But it's going to give you a rough idea of
kind of what
in, kind of information you're going to be
able to extract out of
your data set and what kinds of questions
you're going to be
able to feasibly answer and, and what
questions might not really be possible
to answer with the given data set.
So, so exploratory data analysis is really
important because it rules
out certain questions, and it kind of
pushes you along other directions.
It really allows you to give you that
rough
cut analysis that can,can take you to the
next step.
So let's take a look at the Samsung data
set in this example and see what we can
find.
So um,the data set here comes from the
University of California Irvine or U.C.I.
machine learning archive.
And it's based on predicting people's
movements.
be, from the Gal, from the Galaxy pho,
Samsung Galaxy phones.
So, here's a picture of the Samsung Galaxy
S3.
The actual data set was was produced using
the Galaxy
S2, and but the,the idea is kind of
basically the same.
So, in each of these's, phones.
There's an accelerometer and a gyroscope.
And so it helps you kind of, to understand
the
kind of three dimensional position and
acceleration of a person.
Assuming that they are holding their
phone.
So this is where the data set comes from.
This is the UCI machine learning
repository.
you can go to the link to learn a little
bit more about the data set.
How it was collected, and kind of what is
available on the website.
And so, we, I've downloaded
a subset of the data, which is just the
training data set for the purposes of this
lecture.
So the data been processed a little bit to
make it a little bit easier to use.
Basically you get a matrix, The, that has
kind of, has
the observations on the rows and the
various features on columns.
And you see that at the bottom here, I've
got the activity label which is the kind
of the,
for each row that tells you what the
person was doing at that time.
And so for example there is six possible
activities
that you can be doing; there's laying,
sitting, standing.
Walking, walking down and walking up.
And, the ideas that you, you want to
be able to kind of deter,separate out
these six
activities based on the many features that
are collected by the accelerometer and the
gyroscope.
And so
the, the I listed the first 12 features
here.
I can see that that they have body
acceleration as the mean
standard deviation, the mean absolute
deviation,
the maximum of each of these features.
So one thing we can do really quickly is
just
to look at the average acceleration for
the first subject.
So the first thing I'm going to do is
just, convert the activity variable into a
factor variable.
And then using the transform function.
And them I'm going to just subset out the
the first subject.
So subject equals one and I'm, for the
rest of this presentation
I'm just going to ignore the rest of the
subjects for a moment.
Um,and so.
If I plot the first
subject, I can look at the first column,
and that's
the, first column is the body, the kind of
the body
excel over the mean body acceleration in
the x direction,
so acceleration's going to divide into
three dimensions, x, y, and z.
And then the second plot here is going to
be the, body excel, the mean body
acceleration
in the y direction and, and I've color
coded each of the, activities, by I'm
sorry.
I've color coded each of the activities.
So you can see for example, on the left
hand plot, that there's
green, there's red, black, blue and some
alternate activities so part of the
problem
with the left hand plot is that you can't
tell which activity is which,
so on the right hand plot, I added a
legend, using the legend function.
Just so you can figure out kind of which
Activities correspond to which color.
And so you can see that the green is
standing, the red is sitting, the black is
laying, etc.
And so you can see that, for example, the
mean body acceleration is ah,relatively
kind of uninteresting for things like
sit,standing and sitting and laying.
But for things like walking and working
down and walking up, there's much more
variability.
In the, in the mean body acceleration for
the x direction.
We can try to cluster the data, just on
the average acceleration.
So, I've taken just the first three
columns of this matrix,
and I calculated a distance matrix using
the DIST function.
And I'm using a Euclidean distance just as
the default.
And I can call the hclust function to
do, to do a hierarchical clustering of
these data.
And I've called this my plclust function
just to visualize it.
And you can see that the clustering is a
little bit messy.
And there isn't any kind of clear pattern
going on.
All the colors are kind of jumbled
together at the bottom.
And so we might need
to look a little bit further to try
and kind of extract more information out
of here.
Another thing we can look at is the
maximum acceleration for this, for the
first subject here.
And so I look at, I'm plotting here
columns ten and 11.
And and so you see that column ten is the
body, the maximum body acceleration in
the x direction, and, and column 11 is
the maximum body acceleration in the y
direction.
And so you can
see that again for things like laying and
standing
and sitting, there's not a lot of
interesting things going
on, but for walking in, and walking up,
and
walking down, the maximum acceleration
shows a lot of variability.
So that may,may be a predictor of those
kinds of activities.
But maybe early separating, kind of not
moving from
moving, which might be kind of obvious in
retrospect.
Um,so if you cluster
the data based on maximum acceleration,
you can see that there's two very clear
clusters on the left hand side, you've
got the, kind of the various walking
activities.
And on the right hand side you've got the
various, you know, non moving activities,
laying, standing, and sitting.
And so, beyond that, things are a little
bit jumbled together, you
can there's a lot of turquoise on the left
and so that's.
That's clearly one activity, but in the
blue and the kind of magenta kind of mixed
together.
And so,
a cluster based on maximum acceleration
seems to separate out moving
from non moving, but then once you get
within those clusters.
For example, within the moving cluster or
within the non moving cluster, um,then
it's
a little bit hard to tell what is what,
based just on maximum acceleration.
Um,we can try a little singular,singular
value decomposition
on this data, just to explore what's going
on.
Now before I do the SVD, I'm going to do
it on the entire matrix, which is 560
something um,columns.
I'm going to remove the last two, the last
two columns are just
the activity identifier and the subject
identifier which are not real interesting
data.
So I, I get rid of the five, the columns
and 63 and then I run the SVD on the data.
And you can see,
I'll take a look at the first and the
second left singular vectors and color
code them by activity.
And again, you can kind of see there's a
similar type of pattern.
The first singular vector really seems to
separate out the moving from the non
moving.
So you can see that there's a, a kind of a
green, red, black on the bottom.
And the blue, turquoise, magenta on the
top.
And then the sec, the second singular
vector's a little bit somewhat a
little bit more vague, what it's looking
at.
It seems to be separating out The magenta
color from all the other clusters
and so I think this is the walking down,
or walking up one of those two.
And so it's not clear what is different
about that, that it
kind of highlights, that gets highlighted
on the second singular vector here.
So one of the things we can try to do
is try to find the maximum contribuators,
the, the contributor.
So in the second singular vector we, I'm
sorry, in the second right
singular vector, we can try to figure out
well which of these features
is kind of, is, is kind of producing the
most variation, or is
contributing to the most So the
variation between the various, the
different observations.
And so we
can, we can, we can use the which.max
function to figure
out okay, which of the 500 or so features
corresponds to
the, the, the kind of largest, or
contributes most of the
variations across observations, and I say
that to an object called maxContrib.
And then I'll cluster based on the maximum
acceleration plus this extra feature and
I'll, and I'll
calculate the distance matrix to run the h
plus function and you can see now the kind
of various activities seem to be
separating out a little bit
more, at least the three movement
activities have clearly been separated.
We've got the magenta, the dark blue and
the turquoise all
separated out the various non moving
activities seem to be all kind
of mixed together too so the, whatever
this maximum contributor happened to
be it didn't really help to separate out
the non moving activities.
But it seemed to help a lot in terms of
separating out the movement activities.
So, this max contributor was the body
acceleration, the mean
body acceleration in the frequency domain
for the z direction.
And so this was a, kind of the, the body
acceleration.
For the z direction where they applied and
you transform
and they give you the kind of frequency
components from that.
So that's kind of interesting.
We can try another clustering technique
here which is K-means clustering.
Ah,and one
of the things about k-means clustering
that you have
to be a little bit careful about is that
you
can get kind of different answers
depending on, you
know how many times,starting values you've
tried and how and
how often you run it so whenever you, when
you start k-means it has to chose a
starting point
for where the cluster centers are often it
will
just chose, most algorithms will chose a
random starting point.
So if you chose a random starting point
you may get to a solution that is
suboptimal.
So if you chose a different starting point
you may get
to an even better solution.
And so it's usually good to set the nstart
argument to be more than one so you can
start at many different starting points,
just so you
can get the optimal, or, a more optimal
solution.
So here is one clustering that we've done
with k-means.
And you can see that the, I've specified
six
centers, so I know that there are six
clusters.
So I'll just specify them right away.
And you can see that the,
some of the clusters kind of jumble
together.
So you can see cluster three is
a combination of laying, sitting, and
standing.
Whereas cluster one is walking, cluster,
clearly walking.
Cluster two is walking down.
Cluster four is walking up.
Cluster five is just walking.
And again, and cluster six is a mixture of
laying, sitting and standing.
And so you can see there, k-means here had
a little bit, had trouble separating
out also the laying, sitting and standing
from
the, the three, the in, in, in the
clusters.
If you try it again, you can see the
arrangement's a little bit different.
But again, cluster two for example It's a
mixture of
laying, sitting and standing, cluster five
similarly a mixture of sitting
and standing, but some of the, but the
other clusters
seem to, the other activities seem to
cluster out very, easily.
So now if
we try 100 different starting values, and
take you know,
take the, the most, the optimal solution
from this 100.
You see that things seem to separate out a
little bit better, not much better than
last time.
You can see cluster one is a mixture again
of laying, sitting, and standing.
Cluster two is clearly laying.
Cluster three is clearly walking and
cluster four is walking down and
so you can see how these things kind of
cluster together and
I'll do a second try with 100 starting
values.
And you see, this is going to, probably
going to be our best effort.
And cluster six still is a mixture of
three
activities, and cluster five is a mixture
of two.
So you can see kind of, can see where the
kind of cluster centers are.
And the idea is that each of the clusters
Has a
mean value or a center in a, in this 500
dimensional space.
And so we can see kind of which features
of these 500
features seem to drive the location of the
center for that given cluster.
And then, that will help us, help give us
some idea of you know what features.
Seem to be important for classifying
people in
that cluster, or classifying observations
in that cluster.
So for in the first cluster here, which
seems to correspond to laying, you can see
that the center has a, a relatively high
value for a high, or positive values for
the first three features, which is kind of
the mean body acceleration.
And low values for some of the other
features.
I, It features,features four through ten.
I'm only plotting the first ten here of
the 500 or so.
And then you see the second cluster here.
is, corresponds a little bit more, has,
has some more interesting values for
other Features so there's mean by
this mean acceleration there's also max
acceleration
that seems to have a kind of
subinteresting values.
So one of the things that you can do by
looking at the
cluster centers is to see well what
features seem to have interesting values
that
kind of drive the location to that center
And, which could give you a
hint, in terms of what features will be
most useful for predicting that activity.
So this is a just a short demonstration to
show how you can
take a large data set with lots of
features and lots of observations.
And start to explore it a little bit with
various clustering techniques.
We use Hierarchical clustering, use
k-means
clustering, and we use the singular
value composition to look at various
features of, of this data set.
So given what we've learned here, we may
want to be interested in
following up on kind of what's separates
out the various non movement activity.
So in terms of laying, sitting, and
standing, you know, we seem to
have some difficulty At least on the
first glance, separating those three
activities out.
The movement activities in terms of
walking.
Walking up and walking down.
We seem to be able to kind of separate
those out into separate clusters.
Usually just a few variables most of them
max accelerations variables.
But the non movement kind of activities
seem to harder to separate out.
So, the nice thing about the exploratory
data analysis is that it gives
you this rough cut, that tells you kind of
where to spend your energy.
So, you probably don't, may not have to
spend too much
energy on the movement activities, but
maybe you need to spend, look,
dig a little bit deeper looking at the
kind of non movement activities.
So I hope you find this useful in terms of
how to get started using clustering
techniques and how to get a look at the
data and and,and kind of further your
analysis and,and to kind of get you going
for ah,more formal analysis.