So the grDevices package has a few
different
functions to help, you deal with colors
and the
ones that I'm going to talk about in this
lecture are the colorRamp function and the
colorRampPalette function.
basically, these two functions do take
palettes of colors and interpolate between
them.
So the, the, the model that you could
think of is basically, you know,
if a painter has, his palette, and there
are of four, two or three
blotches of specific colors on that
palette.
And then what you might do is take your
brush,
and kind of mix between the various colors
of the various
per, blotches on that palette, to create
new colors that are
blends of the original colors that you had
on the palette.
So I've never done any actually painting,
so
I just the only thing I know about
painting
is you know from TV and movies but, that's
kind of what I imagine a painter would do
is take these primary colors and then
blend them together with the brush.
And so, that's what the colorRamp and the
colorRampPalette functions
do, they take a set of colors that make up
a palette and they interpolate between
them numerically of course
to make new colors that are blends of the
original colors.
Another function that may be of interest
to you is the
colors function which just, you just
executed with no arguments and it
gives you a character vector of all the
names of
the colors that you can use in a plotting
function.
So these are colors that you can reference
by name rather than having to
reference their kind of red, green, and
blue values that we'll talk about later.
So the colorRamp function specifically
takes a
palette of colors and it returns another
function.
And this, this function that's returned by
colorRamp will take values
between 1 and 1 indicating the extremes of
the color palette.
And so, a similar function that already
exists in R is the gray function.
And the gray function interpolates between
black and white.
And so it gives you kind of all
the shades of gray there between black and
white.
The colorRamp function is a generalization
because it will take any
set of colors in your palette and it will
give you
a function back that takes numbers between
0 and 1 and
it kind of interpolate between the
extremes of the color palette.
The colorRampPalette is a very similar
type of function it takes a palette
of colors and what it does it returns
another function that rather than taking
a value between 0 and 1.
It would takes an integer argument and it
will return a vector of colors
interpolating that palette.
So, this is similar to the heat.colors
function or the topo.colors function.
So, So let's just.
A very quick example here.
In the top here, I've created I'm going to
use
a palette that consists of two colors, red
and blue.
So you can imagine that on your
little painter's palette here, you've got
a blotch
of red and a blotch of blue, and you're
going to
mix them together in varying degrees to
create new colors.
So I, when I pass this through colorRamp
it returns function back and
that function I've called pal, and, and
now pal can take numbers between 0 and 1.
So when I say pal (0).
What do I get back?
I get a little matrix here with one row
and three columns.
And the three columns
indicate, are, are, represent the colors
red, blue and green.
And so in the first column, I've got 255
which is the
maximum value that I can have in this, for
the, for these colors.
The numbers that you specify go between 0
and 255, so
there's 256 total numbers that you can
specify for each color.
And so when pal is when I, when pal
(0), it gives the argument 0, basically
what it gives
me back is red, because that's kind of one
end
of the color spectrum that I've specified
in my palette.
The other end being blue, of course.
And so I've got the maximum value for red,
I've
got 0 for green, and I've got 0 for blue.
So that color is red.
When I say pal (0) down here you see, I've
got 0 for
red, 0 for green, and then I've got the
maximum 255 for blue.
So this just gives me the color blue.
So that's the other end of my color
palette.
So what if I do something in between, like
pal (0.5)?
So this gives me something that, this
should give me a
color that's kind of in the middle of red
and blue.
So it's going to give me 127.5 for red,
and then 0 for green, then 127.5 for blue.
So it's kind of half red, half blue,
whatever that color is happens to be.
Notice that there's no green in any of
these
calls because when in interpolate between
red and blue,
you don't encounter green along the way.
So if I were to give a sequence of numbers
between 0 and
1s pal would give me a sequence of colors
between red and blue.
So here I'm giving a sequence between 0
and 1 that's that's, that's a length 10.
So it starts at 0 and it ends at 1 and and
there's a eight numbers in between.
And so when I pass the sequence to pal,
you'll see at the very top here, I've
got, I start with red, so it's maximum
red, and then, 0 for green, 0 for blue.
And
I slowly reduce the red amount and
increase the blue amount, till I get
to the bottom here, where I've got all
blue and no green and no red.
So those are the various colors that you
get
in between red and blue as you interpolate
the palette.
So, that's the colorRamp function.
The colorRamp palette function is very
similar but it just
it, the type of function that it returns
is slightly different.
So here I'm passing it a different
palette.
So this palette has two blotches, it has a
red and a yellow
blotch on it and we're going to try and
interpolate between those two colors.
And so I've got a function here that's
returned by colorRampPalette
called pal and now pal is going to take
integer arguments not
numbers between 0 and 1.
So, suppose I give it 2, so pal
(2) will return two colors that
interpolate the palette.
Now, because the palette itself only has
two colors
they will, when I just give a 2 it'll
just give me the two colors on the palette
so the first being red and the second
being yellow.
And so, that the way that the format here
is slightly
different instead of giving a matrix with
red, green, and blue values.
It gives me a character vector
which has numbers for, or, or values for
red, green, and blue that are represented
in hexadecimal.
And so if you ignore the pound symbol
there, you'll see there are two digits.
There are six digits in, in each character
string.
The first two represent red, the second
two
represent green, and the third two
represent blue.
So you can see for the first number here
I've got FF0000.
So in hexadecimal
F is the largest number you can have.
So FF on the red, the red pair means a
maximum for red is 00 for green 00 for
blue.
So that's red.
In the second string here, I've got FF for
red, FF for green and then 00 for blue.
So I've got the maximum on red and maximum
on green and I got nothing for blue.
So what does that gives me?
Well, that gives me yellow and by
combining red and green I get yellow.
So that's the other end of the spectrum on
the palette.
So, when now, if I say pal (10), you'll
see the first element here
is going to be red, because it's FF on red
and 0 on everything else.
The last element here is going to be
yellow, because it's
FF on red, FF on green, 0 on the blue.
But then in between, I've got my
interpolation of colors, so you'll see
that there's, there'll be there'll be,
there'll be some red, and then there'll
be some mix ins, a little bit of green as
you go along here.
For more, for all the colors there's no
blue, because there's,
you don't encounter blue when you
interpolate between red and yellow.
So you can see now the representations of
the colors
in hexadecimal here changing as you go
from red to yellow.
[BLANK_AUDIO]