So when it comes to graphics file devices
there are basically two broad categories
of devices.
One is called vector devices or vector
formats and the other format is called
bitmap.
So vector formats are used, are most
useful for things like line graphics.
So, if you have a scatter plot and maybe
you
draw a regression line through it these
are line graphics.
They don't have, they're not like natural
scenes
or images of photographs or things like
that.
And so, these types of graphics are
useful, are, are
usefully kind of generated using vector
formats because they resize well.
So if you have to take the image and kind
of make it bigger or smaller,
that it won't get distorted and the, and
the quality of the graphic won't be, won't
suffer.
For example the PDF format is very
portable, you can
use it on almost any platform that's out
there right now.
And so it is a good format, a general
purpose vector format.
Vector formats are typically not very good
if you have a
plot that has like, that has a lot, a
large number
of points because every single point has
to be represented by
a piece of information in the, in the, in
the file format.
And so, these files tend to be extremely
large if you
plot a lot of different points to a vector
format file type.
[INAUDIBLE] scalable vector graphics or
SVGs, is
a popular format for web based plots.
It's useful because it supports things
like animation and interactivity.
In the plot and, and almost all web
browsers recognize the SVG format now.
Windows metafile is the, is, is the vector
format that's available only on Windows.
And you may see older files lying around
that are in the post script format.
This is kind of a predecessor to the PDF
format,
it's not used very often, but you may see
it around.
In the bitmap format file file formats
there are few commonal ones.
Probably the most common is PNG which
stands for portable network graphics.
The night, and so basically, bitmap
formats are represent
plots or images as a series of pixels,
essentially.
And so They are, they are very good for
for [UNKNOWN] that
had a lot of different points were,
because they will be very
efficiently represented in a bitmap
format.
the, a PNG is particularly good for things
like line drawings
or images with solid colors it uses a
lossless compression algorithm.
So that the file sizes tend to be small
and,
and pretty much every web browser can read
PNGs now.
So if you, so they're good for web, web
based plots.
JPEG you might be familiar with.
If you have a digital camera or something
like that.
They're very good for things like natural
scenes.
Which don't, which don't
have solid colors but have lot's of
gradients of colors.
It uses a lossy compression algorithm.
So the file sizes are very efficient, very
small and they're also good for just
because it's a bitmap format, it's good
for plotting, making plots with lots of
points.
Bitmap formats in general do not resize
well, so when you create a plot and
you try to make it bigger or smaller they
can distort the quality of the image.
And so generally speaking, you should not
resize bitmap
plots after they've been generated.
JPEGs of course, can be read by any
computer or in any web
browser so they're very useful for that
kind of, for web based plots.
they, they're not very good for line
drawings because if you create a
line drawing in PD, in JPEG otherwise
you'll see some aliasing in the lines.
TIFF is another older format for for
bitmap files.
It supports lossless compression and
it's and it's a very commonly used still.
Bmp is a negative, a bitmap format for
Windows.
And is commonly used for things like
icons.
So it's possible to open multiple graphics
devices.
And so for example, for example, you might
want to
create three or four different plots to
look at, at
the same time, and the way to do that is
to have say three or four different screen
devices open.
And so the way you can do this is, is to,
is you can launch graphic
devices explicitly you launch the screen
device for
example on Mac by calling the quarts
function multiple
times and then you'll open multiple
graphic devices screen devices.
And so but you can only plot to one device
at a time.
And so, the graphics device that you plot
to
is the active graphics device and you can
figure out
which graphics device is the cur, is the
active one
by calling the dev.cur() function or
dev.cur stands for current.
And that function will return an integer
that will tells you which
graphics device is currently active.
So, every graphics device is as, is
assigned an
integer that's between two and and two and
up basically.
So there's no graphics device that has the
number one.
So, every graphics device gets an integer
and you can change which
graphics device is the active graphics
device by calling the dev.set function.
And dev.set takes an integer value which
will switch
you to the graphics device that is, that
corresponds
with the integer that you're given.
So you can switch back and forth between
the
graphics devices using the dev.set
function if you need to.
Finally it's possible to copy plots from
one device to another.
And this is probably most commonly used
when
you've created a plot on the screen and
you've
decided that you really like it and then
you
want to, then you want to put it into a
file.
And so there's two ways that you can do
this.
One is that you can, after you, if you've
saved the code.
That can make the plot on the screen.
You can just open up a file device and
then cut and paste the code into R and
then close the file device and then you
got your plot in a file.
But, a faster way and sometimes more
convenient is to
copy the plot from the screen device to
the file device.
And you can use this with the dev.copy
function which
just copies plots from one device from any
device to any
other device And then, if you specifically
want a PDF
file there is a function called
dev.copy2pdf which will take the
screen device and copy it directly to a
PDF file.
And it's important to note that copying
the plot is
not an exact operation so, the, the, the
plot you
end up with in the file, may not look
exactly
like the copy, the plot you saw on the
screen.
So it's a, there may be some adjustment
you have to do.
So here is some code that just creates a
plot on the screen.
This is the Old Faithful Geyser data that
comes with R
and then I want to copy it to a PNG file,
so I want to create a PNG file on my
computer
that contains the plot that I'm looking at
on my screen.
So, I can call dev.copy, the first
argument to dev.copy is the, is the
function that opens the file device in
this case, this is the PNG function.
And then, I just give it a file name,
which is needed to create the file.
So, I just call it geiserplot.png.
And then, once I've copied the plot, I
still need to close the PNG device with
dev.off.
So, once I've call dev.off, there'll,
there should be a file
on my computer that, that's going to be in
a PNG format.
And I can send it to someone or include it
in a presentation.
So, that's a quick summary of the the
graphics devices in R.
The basic bottom lines are that every plot
must be created on a graphics device.
And usually this is the screen device, but
and it's useful for exploratory analysis.
But if you want to preserve a plot or send
it to
someone, you have to create a plot in a
file device.
And there a variety of different file
formats that you can use.
There are vector formats like PDF and SVG,
and
therebBitmap formats like PNG and JPEG.
That you can chose from.