So there's one thing that is worth
pointing out which, maybe which differs
in ggplot than it does from say the base
plots Is that if you
have a plot where, where the the data kind
of exceed the limits of
the plot the behavior between base plot
and ggplot can change a little bit.
So here on the left hand side I've just
simulates some data.
So just, so, so this is not max data.
And I just, I, and I, I intentionally
introduced a little outlier here.
So in the 50th data point, I just changed
that value to be 100.
So now as the, just kind of this random
series of, of noisy data.
And then right in the middle, there's a
point that's 100.
And so if I call plot, so I'm going to
make a standard base plot here.
I call plot on x and y, and I, and I
say type equals l, because I want to make
a line plot.
But then typically if you have some out
lier like this you don't want to
look at the outlier you just want to look
at the core of the data.
So it's
typical to kind of set the the y axis
limits to be, to
be roughly kind of where the data are and
just ignore the outlier.
So you can see that the time series that
gets
drawn has all the data connected and that
you can see
roughly where it's going to shoot off to a
hundred and
comes back down to be roughly where it's
suppose to be.
So you know that outlier is out there
somewhere, but you don't see it in the
plot.
Now, if I do the equivalent plot in
ggplot, I can create my ggplot with with
the test data, and the aesthetics to the x
and y.
And then I add the geom_line function to
make
a line plot as opposed to a scatter plot.
You can see that just plots the whole, all
the data including the outliers.
And it's maybe not exactly the kind of
plot
you want to make because the outliers
maybe not that interesting.
So if you want to do this, it's you have
to be careful about how you do it.
And so the first is that on the left-hand
side, you
might think, well, I'll just change the y
limits to be within,
kind, in the range of most of the data
between minus 3 and 3.
The issue here is that what ggplot will do
is that it will subset the data.
To include the values that are between
minus 3 and 3.
And so, of course, the outlier is not
included in this data
set and so you won't see that data point
in this plot.
So you can see this clearly where the
outlier's missing the
two lines are not connected, but then
everything else is connected afterwards.
So if you want to recreate the kind of
phenomenon
that you saw with baseplot You have to
add, this special
function called coord_cartesian, which
that sets the limits to be minus 3.
The one, the y axis limits to be minus 3
and 3.
Now you can see in the plot here that
the outlier is in fact included, in the
dataset.
It's the dataset hasn't been subsetted to
only include
the ones that are in the y axis range.
Um,so, I just want to go over a slightly
more complex example of kind of adding
pieces to a plot, just so you can get
a sense of how the different layers are
added on.
And then hopefully get you going from
there.
So, so here I've just, I've made the
scientific question just a little bit more
complex.
I want to know how is the relationship
between PM 2.5 and
nocturnal symptoms vary by both BMI and
nitrogen dioxide or NO2.
And so as NO2 or BMI values change how
what does the relationship between
PM PM 2.5 and nocturnal symptoms look
like?
So one tricky thing about this is unlike
our previous BMI
variable which is kind of categorized into
normal and over weight.
Now, NO2 variable is continuous, or it's
really the
log of the NO2, and it's really a
continuous variable.
So we need to, so we can't really
condition on a continuous variable
when we're making plots because then there
would be an infinite number of plots.
And so we need to categorize this variable
into a reasonable series of ranges.
And so what we're going to do is we can
use the cut function
for this purpose, to cut literally cut the
data into a series of ranges.
So here is some code to make NO2, split
NO2 into tertiles, so this is going to be
three separate categories you know, kind
of between
zero, the minimum, and the 33rd
percentile, the 33rd.
In the 66 and the 66 to the maximum.
And so the first thing I need to do is use
the quantile function
to figure out where in the data ranges are
the 33'rd and 66th percentiles.
And once I've use the quantile function to
find these cut points I pass that to
cut function and I use the cut function
to actually NO2 into these three different
ranges.
And so what the cut function does is it
just
returns a factor variable where each of
the original data
points is replaced to buy its category in
terms of
the, which tertile it's in, so in terms of
the low,
the middle, or the high tertile.
it's, it's a very handy function for when
you're using things
like lattice or ggplot and you have to
categorize continuous variables.
So now you can see the levels of this
variable, the cut variable are, there's
three different levels.
There's kind of 0.378 to 1.2, and 1.2 to
1.42 and then 1.42 to 2.55.
So those are the three categories that
I've split the NO2 variable into.
So here's the final plot, just to show you
what I'm going
for, and then we'll work backwards, figure
out exactly how to do it.
So you can see that there's eight
different plots here.
On the top you see all the normal weight
children.
And on the bottom you see all the
overweight children.
So those are the two categories of BMI.
And then there's there's four, there's
actually four categories of.
NO2 is the, the first tertile on the left
side, the second tertile on the second
column, the third
tertile on third column, and then there's
actually some data that are missing.
And so these are the data that are missing
NO2 values, but they're
not missing all other values, so you can
still in some sense plot them.
And so it's, it's sometimes, it's often
important to look at the missing data
just.
Just to see if there's anything special
about those missing.
You don't always want to exclude them
right off the bat
because there might be something special
about them you've missed.
So, what does this plot have?
Well first of all I've, I've modified
the transparency on the points.
So I've made them a little bit transparent
so
you can see a little bit of the density
there.
I've added a smoother to each panel, so
this is a linear regression smoother.
So, it's not the default.
And I've turned off the Confidence bands.
There are multiple panels so I've used
faceting to create this plot.
I've changed the kind of default labels
and the titles, so
I've added to, to reflect and be a little
bit more descriptive.
And then finally I used a
non-default font, so the default font is
Is Helvetica,
and I've changed the font here to be
Avenir.
And so, there are a number of options that
I've modified here.
And so, here's the code for doing it.
So, the first, in the first set of code,
I, I just call ggplot.
I give it the data and I give it some
basic aesthetics in terms of the x and y
variables.
And then, to this G object, I add a bunch
of things.
I add points using geom_point.
I add a, I make the panel
using the facet_wrap function and I add a
smoother using the geom smooth
where I specify the LM method and I turn
off the standard error bars.
I, I changed the theme to be this black
and white theme where I,
and then I modified the font to be Avenir
instead, instead of the default.
And I've also made the font a little bit
smaller, to be ten points instead of the
default 12.
And then finally, I've called the labs
function three different times
to change the labels, the x label, the y
label, and the title of the plot.
So you can see that I've added all these
different things piece by
piece to make this plot a little bit more
interesting every single time.
And it's easy to do this with ggplot, and
I, and
then, and the nice thing about ggplot
which I didn't do here
is that you could in fact save this to a
new object
and then you would have everything stored
in a single R object.
And then if you wanted to add on more
layers, you could add to that, that new
object,
you could continue to add different things
if you wanted to.
So it's a very modular, very kind of a, a
useful framework.
For constructing plots that are new just
for your data.
So, just to summarize very quickly, I know
this has been a very
brief introduction in ggplot, and there's
a lot things that you could talk about.
But given that this is not a course
specifically on ggplot, my hope was
to kind of get you started, to get you
typing in some basic code,
making some basic plots.
I hope, and then if you want to know more,
you can kind
of look at some of the references that I
mentioned in, previously.
So, I think in summary, ggplot is a very
powerful, it's very flexible if you
can learn the grammar and learn the
different
pieces that you can add to a plot.
And that can be tuned and modified.
There are lots of different types of plots
you can make.
I left out a lot, but you can explore and
mess around.
I think that's how, that's kind of the
best way to learn about these things.
And to, and to take a look at some of the
references that I mentioned in part one.