Graphics devices in R are very important
because we need them to make plots.
There are many different types of graphics
devices that
we can on which we can make plots, and so
this lecture's going to cover, just
briefly the various different
graphics devices that are available to
most users of R.
So, first of all, what is a graphics
device?
So very simply, a graphics device is, is
something
or some place where you can make a plot
appear.
So the most obvious
place for, for a plot to appear is on your
screen, or, or a window on your screen.
And so when you open up R, and you call
the plot
function, a window, a graphics window
launches and your plot appears there.
So that's called the screen device.
Other places where you might want to send
the plot include things like files.
And so files come in a variety of formats.
You can have a PDF file, a PNG file, or
a JPEG file, or, or a scalable vector
graphics SVG file.
And so
there are a lot of different file devices
that you can
choose from, and you can send a plot to
those files.
So any time you make a plot in R, it has
to be sent to a specific graphics device.
otherwise, it, that, it, it's, there's no
way for it to be generated.
The most, and the most common place for a
plot
to be sent is this, this, is this screen
device.
So, the screen device on the Mac, is
called
a quartz, on Windows, it's called windows
and on the,
on Unix/Linux systems it's called x11.
So when you make a plot, you, the, you
first
have to think about where's this plot
going to show up.
And there's a full list of the devices
that are available to you under
the devices help page here, which you can
call up with the question mark devices.
There are also graphics devices that have
been created by users on
CRAN, that you can make available to R, by
installing those packages.
We won't talk about those here.
I'm going to focus mostly on the devices
that come with R.
so, when you're
plotting data and you're doing some
visualizations
and exploratory analysis and kind of
looking through
some data, usually the most obvious place
to send a plot is the screen device.
So you call a plot function like plot, or
xyplot, or maybe you're
using qplot and ggplot2 and the plot will
go to the screen device.
And then you can look at your data, very
quickly, and see if you
want to make a, see what you're going to
do for the next plot.
on, on any given platform, whether you're
using a Mac or
Windows or Unix, there's only one screen
device.
So, you don't have to make any choice
about, you
know, what screen device you're going to
send it to.
There's only, there's only one place to
go,
and so, you don't have to worry about it.
Now, however, usually after you've done
some
exploratory analysis and you've kind of
figured out,
well, what plots are things that you want
to keep or you want to include.
Or maybe you want to send a plot to
someone then you have to,
you have to make the plot on another type
of device, you for example,
a file device.
So when you make a plot in a file then you
can take that file.
You can include it in a report.
You can include in a, in a presentation
that you're making.
Or maybe you can email it someone.
And so files are more, much more useful
for that type of purpose.
So there are many different files devices
to choose from unlike with the
screen device and so we'll talk about some
of those file devices here.
It's important to realize that not every
graphics device that I talk about in
this lecture, will be available on all
platforms.
And so, for, for example, there's no
Windows device on a Mac or
on a UNIX system and similarly there's no
quartz device on a Windows system.
So, you won't be able to open every single
graphics device on every platform.
so, how does a plot get created?
And this might seem a little obvious, but
there's
actually more than one way to, to create a
plot.
So the first one is which is the, kind of
the simplest approach
and probably the one that you're most,
you're already familiar with is that
you call a plotting function like plot, or
xyplot, or qplot, and the
plot just appears on the screen or the
screen device I should say.
And then you can annotate the plot with
functions like text or title or
ac, or or things like that.
And then once you finish annotating your
plot and
it looks the way you like it, then that's
it.
You're finished.
The plot is on the screen and you can look
at it.
You can show it to someone else on the
screen.
So here's some code that just loads the
dataset and creates a plot using the plot
function and then it adds a title to the
top of the plot and then that's it.
So, it's, that's a very simple way to
create a plot on the screen.
Another way
for creating a plot is most commonly used
for file
devices and it's, and it involves
explicitly launching a graphics device.
So you might open a file device, and
then you create the plot using plotting
functions.
You can in the case of, if your using
a file device it's a little bit tricky
because
the plot will not actually appear on the
screen,
because all the plotting information is
going into a file.
And so you have to know exactly what
you're doing when you create a, a plot
to a file because you won't be able to see
it on the screen.
So typically, the best way to do this is
to save your code, your
plotting code, in a separate file and that
way you can just kind of
cut and paste the code into R, and you,
and you don't have to
worry about, you know, making a, making a
mistake while you're typing the code in.
So after you create the plot, you annotate
it if you need to.
Then you have to close the graphics device
with the function dev.off.
Once you've closed the graphics device
then the,
the plot is complete and if you send it to
a file, you
can open the file in your computer or you
can look at it.
You can include it in some, in a re,
in a presentation or you can email it to
someone.
So here's some code that just opens the
PDF device here, with the PDF function.
You have to give it a file name so I just
call, called it myplot.pdf.
And then you have to make the plot, do
some annotation
and then you have to close the plot with
the dev.off function.
So, once I've called dev.off there should
be a file in my
working directory called myplot.pdf and
you can open that with any PDF viewer.