So there are a couple of other functions
that may be of use to you.
One is the rgb function and the rgb
function takes
arguments for red, green and blue, and
what it returns.
So these are numbers between zero and one
for red, green and blue and it will
return, hexadecimal string that can be
passed to functions like image or plot.
And so that, so if you want to convert
between red, gr, red, kind of ,um,
decimal red green blue representation to
this hexadecimal
string you can use the rgb, function for
that.
Another thing you can use rgb for is to
add transparency to your colors.
And so, there is a fourth argument to rgb
view which is a number between
zero and one, the alpha parameter, which
have
been used, to specify transparency in your
colors.
Zero being the most transparent, or
basically
completely transparent, and one being not
transparent
at all.
And lastly I'll just mention the color
space package which can be used
to, to have a different, to exert a
different type of control over colors.
You may want to explore it, but I won't
talk about it here.
So just a quick example of the
transparency in r,
so here's a plot of a, a, of a thousand
points.
And you could see that in the high density
region
here, I'm using the pch 19 which is a
solid circle.
In the
high density region, all the plot, all the
points just kind of overlap each
other, so you just see a black,uh,blob
there in the middle and it's,
card, kind of hard to see what the
resolution for the different points
because there is no definition of points
there because they are all overlapping.
So if I add a little transparency to the
plot you'll see that the circles
become transparent so when they overlap
each other
they, you can kind of see through them.
And so that the areas where
there are lots of points overlapping they,
they get darker and when there are
areas where there are no points
overlapping
you just see kind of a transparent circle.
So here I've got below, I've got the code
that I've used to create this plot.
And you can see that I've specified an
alpha parameter of 0.2.
And, and the r, the red, green and blue
are all zeros so I can get black.
Uh,and so point two is pretty close to
zero, so there's a lot of transparency.
Um,but you can see that when I use the
transparency like thisiIt's
kind of a cheap and easy way to get
essentially a histogram estimator
because, you know, the, the darker areas
will represent higher density areas of
the plot and the lighter areas will
represent kind of lower density areas.
So you can see a little bit more
information when you have a plot with
a lot of different points in it when you
use a little bit of transparency.
So that's just, that's the basic intro
into
the use of colors and transparency into r.
I think that the careful use of colors and
plots
and maps and whatever just, can make it
easier for
the reader to get the point that you're
trying to
make, or to see the comparisons that
you're trying to make.
And and I think it's it's useful to have a
good set of colors, especially
to match kind of sequential colors and
sequential data and diverging colors with
diverging data.
The color brewer, the RColorBrewer package
is a
very useful package that's available on
CRAN, and
it provides these uh,color palettes for
the different
types of data that you might be plotting.
The color ramp and color palette functions
are
essential when you're trying to
interpolate between colors, especially
if you're using the RColor per package and
you
want interpolate between the colors on a
given palette.
And then finally, transparency is very
useful because it can be used to clarify
plots which have many many points on them
by cre, by allowing the colors to be
transparent and to kind of overlap each
other.