So some of the key base plotting functions
that you'll use a lot of
course is the, one, the first is the plot
function which makes a scatterplot.
And it can make other types of
plots depending on whether you're, you're
plotting a
special type of object, but for the
most part you usually want to make
scatterplots.
Uh,lines is a, is a function that doesn't
create a plot but it adds to a plot
and so sometimes you want to connect a lot
of dots together so you want to make like
uh,a time series type of font.
You want to make, you want to draw
lines instead of scatterplot lines is
useful for that.
points, adds points to a plot, so
sometimes
you want to create a plot, and then you
want to
add some other points that might represent
a
different group or a different subset of
the population.
Text as labels, so you want to annotate
the plot with text labels.
Title adds so text can be used, I should
say, to add labels within the plot.
And the title function is typically used
to add annotations outside the
plot, like x and y axis labels, titles,
subtitles, and things like that.
Mtext is, the m stands for margins, so
it's
used to place text in the margins of the
plot,
both the inner and the outer margin, and
the
axis function is for use for specifying
the axis ticks.
So here is a couple, a couple examples of
how to
make plots, and then adding, annotating
them, here I am plotting
the wind and ozone that I had before.
Or scatterplot, but now I'm adding a title
to the top of the plot.
So here is the ozone and wind from, in New
York City.
In this plot, I'm again doing a
scatterplot, but I, instead of using the
title
function to add the title, I just, I put
the title directly into the call
to plot, but then, what I want to do is, I
want to sub-set, I want to kind of
plot all of the data points that are in
the month of May a different color.
And so what I do is I subset
the data frame just to include the
observations from
month equals 5, and then I use the points
function to add, to kind of re add points,
but this time color them blue.
So you can see in the plot below that the
the, they're a subset of
blue points, and those correspond to the,
to the data points in the month of May.
Now I could do um,um, more subsets so I
can plot them different colors.
Cause here I'm, I'm plotting but the
um,the initializing a plot but
then one thing you can see is I added the
argument type equals
n and so what type equals n means it
basically sets up
the plot and initializes the graphics
device but it doesn't actually plot
anything.
So it doesn't put anything into the
plotting region.
It just
makes a, it sets up all the other stuff in
the plot without the actual data.
And then as I, in order to put the data
into
the plot, I kind of go through subsets of
the data frame.
To add the data from the month of May, and
add data for the month of not May.
So, for the month of May, I make that
color blue, and then, for
the other months that are not equal to
May, I just make that color red.
So, you can see all of the other points
are red.
So now, I can kind of accurately see which
ones are blue, which ones are
May, without kind of ov, over plotting
existing points.
And then as a last touch, I add a legend
to the top right part of the plot, so I
can distinguish, which ones are May, which
ones are not May.
Finally, one common thing you will
typically want
to do is add a regression line or
a smoother to a plot, so here I've
just added a regression line to this same
scatterplot.
So I first make
the scatterplot and you notice, I changed
the default.
Plotting character pch to be 20.
So, 20 is a kind of small filled in
circle.
And then I fit a linear model to the data,
which is using the LM function.
And then I just call the abline function,
which
is another annotation function, ah,and I
just pass it,
the linear model object and I specify lwd
equals
to 2, which is a thicker line than the
typical default line.
So abline can interpret the regression
model output and
plot a line, plot with a given intercept
and slope.
And so here you can see, I've added the
regression line to the plot.
Um,and so you can see,and you can see the
downward trend.
So, all the previous plots into the single
plot
that you might, that would appear on the
graphics device.
But sometimes you want to have multiple
plots on a single device.
So here I made two plots.
One plot is ozone versus wind.
And the other one plot is ozone versus
solar radiation using the same data set.
And so in order to do that I can just
set the par mfrow equals to one row and
two columns.
So I They, I can make the two plots side
by side.
And then I just call plot twice.
So every time I call plot, it creates a
new plot.
And so the first one will be, the in the
kind of left hand side and
the second column plot will be in the
right hand side and that's how I use
mfrow.
Now, you can see that, when I use multiple
plots, some I have a title
on each plot so that it tells me kind of
what the two variables are.
And the first one's ozone and wind, second
one's ozone and solar
radiation, and the third one here is ozone
and temperature.
But sometimes you want to have a label
that's.
Kind of covering the entire panel of
plots.
So that's what the outer margin is for.
So here in this call of the par I set
mfrow equal to one row, three columns.
I set the margins to be a little bit
smaller than defaults and then I set the
outer
margin to be actually bigger than default,
the b,
the default for the outer margin is zero
all around.
So on the top I want a little extra space
so I can add the title.
Ozone and weather in New York City, which
is
kind of a title for the entire panel of
plots.
And then I call plot three times to make
the three plots and then
I use mtext to add the kind of outer title
to this panel of plots.
So that was a quick, kind of introduction
to the base
plotting system, covers some of the basic
functions that you would use,
that you would use including plot and
a couple of annotation functions like, A
line.
And points and things like that.
So, it's, you can see that by creating.
And when you create base plots, you are
kind
of building up a plot by function by
function.
And you kind of end up with a, with many
live code to create one plot.
And that's kind of that's how, that's
typical of lots of base plots.
Every plots starts with a function that
initiates
the plot, so like, plot or hist or box
plot, and then a series
of functions which will typically annotate
the
plot by adding points, lines, text and
legends.
So the, the base plotting system is very
flexible.
It, it gives you a lot of control over all
of the various details of the plot.
Of course this can be a little bit tedious
if you need
to control everything all the time but
often the defaults are okay.
And but, the flexibility is quite useful
if
you want to make, kind of, publication
quality plots.
and, and, and so, it's nice to have that
de-, that degree
of control, with all, for things like
legends, spacing's and all that.
And so, so that's the, kind of the base
plotting system.
We'll talk more about the other plotting
systems in other lectures.