This video is going to show how to install
R for Windows.
If you go to cran here, click on download
R for Windows, you want to
hit the base sub directory, and then click
on the link download R 2.15.1 for windows.
So this is going to download and you want
to save it to somewhere on you hard drive.
Okay, once that's done downloading you
want to find
it on your computer and then open up the
setup package, which is an executable that
you
can double click and it'll start the setup
program.
So you want to choose English for now and
we're going to start running through the
setup wizard.
This'll be pretty straightforward.
You have to accept the license.
Choose the default install directory and
choose the default e
32 bit user installation which should be
fine for most people.
You don't need eh, to modify the start up
options if you don't want to.
and, creating a start up menu item is
usually a good idea.
So, the, you hear the defaults are all
okay, once you
click through that you'll see the program
file start to install.
Okay, so now it's done installing, you hit
finish, and you'll notice that there is a
R icon on your desktop now, so you can
double-click on that icon to launch R,
and here we are, so that's installing R on
Windows.