This lecture is going to be about plotting
and color in R.
It's kind of an adjunct lecture to the
lectures that we've already
had in plotting in both base graphics and
the lattice graphics system.
I just want to talk a little bit about how
you specify different types of colors
using different palates in R.
You might think that the specification of
color in a plot is maybe kind of a
secondary decision and in some sense it is
it's definitely secondary to something
like the data,
but of course, but the judicious and
appropriate use of colors, I
think in plots can help to describe the
relationships that you're trying
to demonstrate and can help various
dimensions of the data come out
more effectively than if you just choose
an arbitrary set of colors.
So, there are a couple of things,
functions, and things
that I want to cover in this lu, lecture,
but the
basic point that I'm, is that the default
color schemes
for most of the plots in R, are pretty
bad.
And you don't have to be an expert in
design or anything to really kind of see
this.
But the kind, the natural color schemes
that you kind of gravitate towards when
you use the plotting functions are not
particularly well suited for different
kinds of data.
But there have been a number of
developments
in R, via packages and also in the core
R system that can help with the handling
of
specification of colors and, and various
types of plots.
And so we're going to, I'm going to talk
about one
of these packages and some of the
functions in this lecture.
So, the basic problem that typically comes
out in most plots.
This is a pretty standard plot in R that
you might see in a presentation
or a paper there's some points on the plot
and I'm just plotting random points here.
And you see that
there are, the points are in three
different colors.
The first is black.
The open circles are in black.
Then there's a couple of points that are
in
red and a couple of points that are in
green.
So why does this happen?
Because in most plotting functions there
will be a col argument, col.
When you say col equals one, you get
black.
When you say col equals two, you get red
and when you say col equals three, you get
green.
And so, if you have a plot and you want
three different
colors in it.
It's very easy to say, okay, well, just
give me col equals one, two, three.
and, and so, you get black, red, and
green.
Col equals four, would have been something
like
cyan, and then, col equals five is
magenta.
So, those are the kind of standard colors
that you just get stuck with,
when you, when you set col equal to be
one, two, three, four or five.
And so if you go this route the red and
the green don't,
are not particularly meaningful in this,
in this case.
Of course, you don't know what the data
are about.
So it's it's possible that they are, but
in most cases, they're not the,
the most suitable colors for the type of
data that you're going to show.
And, and also, just from a design point if
you use this color scheme all the time,
then all of your plots will look like
they belong in some Christmas show or
Christmas presentation.
So, if the question
is whether or not we can choose a better
set of
colors that better communicates the idea
that we're trying to get across.
Another standard set of colors is shown
here.
This is the volcano data set that comes
with R.
And it's basically a data set that shows
different elevations of a volcano.
And, there two, the color, set of colors
on the
left is called, is comes from the heat
colors palette.
And so, this is a palette of colors that,
goes from kind
of a reddish to, to indicate low, to a
yellow or white, to indicate high.
And then, on the right side here, we've
got a
palette of colors called the topo colors
or topographical colors
and this goes from a kind of blue, which
indicates
low to a a brown or a white which
indicates high.
So for the heat colors it, if you know
what fire is,
it may be reasonable to, to kind of see
that picture
and know that kind of what is low and what
is high.
For the topographical colors, it's not,
maybe not immediately clear
to some people wha, what is low and what
is high,
it's not so the fact that blue is low and
green is higher than blue it may not be
particularly obvious.
It's not particularly obvious to me.