This lecture is about the base plotting
system in R.
Now previously we talked about the three
different plotting systems that R has.
The base plotting system, the lattice
system, and the G G plots, the two system.
So here I'm going to talk about the base
plotting functions and the,
which is the kind of most commonly used
system in, for plotting in R.
All of the core plotting and graphics
engine in R is
encapsulated in the graphics package and
the G R devices Package.
The GR devices package contains all the
code for the graphics devices, including
the screen
devices, like X11 and Windows ports, as
well
as file devices like PDF and Post Script.
The graphics package contains the plotting
functions, so, so very
basic functions like plot, hist, boxplot
and, and many others.
And so this will be core plotting system,
what we call the base graphic system.
The lattice system is, is encapsulated in
the lattice package.
And that uses another package called grid,
which is a kind of a low-level,
graphics system that's kind of an
alternative
to the, to the base graphing system.
We usually, we don't ever, we usually
don't call the grid
package directly, only indirectly through
packages like lattice or GE plot.
And the last package we'll talk about in a
separate lecture.
So in the process of making a plot there
are a lot
of considerations that you have to make.
In terms of where will the plot be made?
Will it be made on the screen?
Will it be sent to a file?
How will the plot be used?
Is it for viewing on the screen
temporarily?
Is it going to be in a web browser?
Are you going to be printing it in a
paper?
Is it going to be publication quality, or
you're
going to use it in a slideshow or
presentation?
So, these are kind of questions that you
need to think about when you're making a
plot.
Another thing, another question that you
might
want to think about is there, is there
a large amount of data that's going to go
into this plot?
Or maybe just a few points?
Or is it an image?
Or is it a line drawing?
Or is it something like that.
Un, and then lastly one question that's
worth ask, what, asking is
whether you need to be able to dynamically
resize the graphic, because
you may want to use something like a
vector format if you
are sending it to a file rather than a bit
map format.
So those are a couple of questions that
you
want to make as you start making a plot.
The other question of
course is what graphic system you want to
use?
There's Base, lattice, and ggplot2.
And the reason why you have to ask
yourself this
question is because you can't really mix
the three different systems.
And so the three systems, roughly
speaking, are,
you know, base graphics has this kind of
piecemeal construction where you put
things together one
by one, through a series of function
calls.
Now, the lattice system creates entire
plots out of a single function call,
so everything kind of has to be
conceptualized from the get go.
And the ggplot2 system kind of combines
concepts from both lattice and base.
So in this lecture we'll be focusing only
on the base plotting system,
and, and we'll be talking about creating
graphics on the screen device only.
So in base graphics, you,
you're essentially creating two
dimensional graphics.
and, and you have to do it in a two phase
process.
The first process
initializes the new plot and the second
par, phase
I should say, annotates or adds to an
existing plot.
And so there are a number of functions
that are useful for initializing a plot.
And then there are ano-, separate set of
functions that are useful for annotating a
plot.
So the plot function or the hist function
are two
examples of functions that are init-, used
for initializing a plot.
And what they do is that if they, if
there's no graphics device open already,
it will launch
a graphics device.
And typically, this will be, come in the
form as
a, of a window that pops up on your
screen.
And then it will draw the plot on that new
device.
The plot function is a generic function in
R, and so, it has, it,
it can behave differently, depending on
what kinds of data you pass to it.
If you don't pass it a special type, piece
of data, so, if you
just pass it, if X and Y are, for example,
vectors, then, you use
what's called the default method for plot.
This default method has a lot of
arguments.
And you can look at the help page for plot
and see what those arguments are.
For example, you can set things like the
title, the x-axis
label and the y-axis label and many other
types of details.
In general, the Base graphics system has
many
parameters that you, can use to set that
can set, and tweak to make your graphics
look exactly the way you want them to.
This is kind of a, it's a, it's a
double-edged sword,
because there are a lot of things that you
can customize.
But of course, then, there are a lot of
things that you have to set that are not
automatic.
And so, most of these parameters are
documented in the help page for par,
so you just look at that help page, you'll
see a lot of parameters there.
It wouldn't help, hurt to try to memorize
this help page,
of course, but it's always there for you
if you don't.
So, here's a, the, a basic graph that,
that is made using the base graphic system
here.
I'm using the hist function which creates
a histogram.
Which is a kind of a one-dimensional plot.
And so here I'm loading the air quality
data set
from the data set's package and I'm making
histogram of ozone.
And so you can see that I'm not setting,
I'm not using,
there are other arguments to hist but I'm
not setting all of them.
And so I'm just using the defaults for,
for whatever
there is there for hist, and it makes a
simple histogram.
And so, this if my graphics device had not
been open in R,
it would have opened the graphics device
and then put the histogram in there.
Another fundamental type of plot is the
scatter plot, of course.
And this can be created using the plot
function here.
I'm using the same data set, but I'm
making a scatter plot of ozone versus
wind.
And so you can see the default plotting is
if
I don't specify any other arguments to the
plot function it's,
I'm using all the defaults here.
And the default plotting symbol is a, is
an open circle with kind of a white
background.
And then finally, this is another function
that initializes the plot.
It's the box plot function.
here, and you can see I'm making a
box plot of the distribution of ozone by
month.
So you see the box, the box plot function
uses a kind of formula notation, where I'm
saying on the Y axis I want ozone, which
is the left hand side of the tilde.
And on the right hand side I specify what
I want
on the X axis, which in this case is the
month.
And so like, the, the month is to kind of
divide it into a categorical vector.
cat, sorry, car, categorical variable so
if for
the months of May, June, July, August and
September.
And here you see, I specified what I want
the x lab, the x label to,
x axis label to be through x lab and the y
axis label through y lab.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So there are a couple of key base graphic
parameters that are
useful to kind of keep in the, and, at the
front of your
brain, or at the top of your head,
whatever you want to call
it because they are, you know, you tend to
use them quite often.
The first one is the pch or the plotting
character or plotting symbol.
And you notice that the default in the, in
the previous plots tends to be, is the
open circle.
But you can change this to be something
else,
and, and so the pch can be, take two types
of arguments.
It can take a number which refers to a
table of kind of built-in symbols.
Or, it can take a character.
So we can take character element which
would be plot that character on the
screen.
So if you give the letter A for example,
then it will
use as, the letter A the plotting symbol
for all your data points.
So sometimes this is useful for kind of
self-labeling a plot, so you
can see that all the As represent one
group, and all the Bs represent
another group.
The lty is the line type, and so if you're
plotting things that have, plotting data
that are lines this
will specify whether it's a solid line, a
dashed line
or a dotted line or a dot-dash line, or
etc.
The lwd is the line width.
So some, a lot of times you want to
control the line
width depending on how, you know, how the
plot's going to be used.
For example, if the plot's going to be in
a presentation where lots of people are
going
to be sitting in the back row, then you
want to, usually you
want to have very thick line width so they
can see the lines.
But if it's going to be in a publication
where
it's going to be in a mag, in a journal or
printed and people are going to be looking
at
it much closer, then you don't need such
thick lines.
The col is the col-, the plotting colors.
This is the color that the the plotting
symbols will appear on the screen.
Sometimes you like to cu-, customize that.
You can specify colors using
either a number or a string which, which
is like a word
or you can use a hexcode that's written
in, in character format.
And the colors function will give you a
list of colors that you can specify by
name.
So you can see there are a lot of colors
there.
And then xlab and ylab will let you
specify the x axis and y axis labels.
And that's very useful for annotating
plots.
And a couple other base graphics
parameters that can
be useful that you can set in the par
function.
Because the par function is used to
specify global graphics parameters.
So these, these will be the same in every
single plot that you make.
Of course you could always, always, you
can usually, I should say,
override the global graphics parameters
with,
by specifying them in each function call.
So if you don't like, for example the
background color,
you can usually, you can change that
within a given function.
However, other parameters like the margin
size, or the mfrow or
the mfcol, these cannot be spec, changed
within the plotting function.
They have to be changed using the par
function only.
And so the las, the las, is, is the
orientation of the axis on the labels.
So if you'd like all the labels on the
the,
the axis labels to be kind of horizontal
or,
or perpendicular to the graph, you can
change this.
BG is the background color for the plot.
The margin size, sometimes it needs to be
modified
if you have a very complex x, y axis
or x axis label, you might, might want to
make
the margin a little bit bigger to
accommodate that.
The outer margin is important if you have
multiple plots per page and you
want to have a mar-, a kind of a label
that's in the outer
margin that kind of covers the entire
plot.
And the mfrow and the mfcol control how
many, if
you having multiple plots on the dev, on
the screen device.
And for example you have a matrix of
plots.
And it controls how many plots will appear
per row, and per column.
So you can see what the default values
for some of these global graphics
parameters are,
by just calling the par function with the
name of the parameter and no other
arguments.
So you can see the lty, the default is a
solid line.
For color, the default is black and for
pch the
plotting symbol is 1, which corresponds to
n open circle.
For BG, the, the background is
transparent, so there's really no
background color.
And then for the
margin you can see that there's four
numbers here and each one
of these numbers refers to one of the
margins of a plot.
And if you think of the bottom of the plot
as the first side and then the left hand
side
is the second side, and then the top is
the
third side and the right hand side is the
fourth side.
So you can think of, starting at the
bottom going in a clockwise direction.
Those are the four sides of a plot.
And you can see the bottom margin
gets a spa-, a, a size of 5.1.
And you can roughly think of this as 5.1
lines of text that could be in the bottom
margin.
And then the s-,, the left hand side is
4.1,
the top is 4.1 and the right hand side is
2.1.
So you can adjust those margin sizes if
you need to
accommodate your plot to make more or less
space in those margins.
And then the mfrow defaults
to 1,1, which means one row and one
column.
So that's just a single plot.