Principal Components Analysis and the
Singular Value
Decomposition are a really important
techniques, both in
the exploratory data analysis phase, and
also,
in the more kind of formal modeling phase.
The techniques I've been, can be used in,
very easily in both eight, stages.
But I'm going to talk a little bit about
kind of,
how it's used in the exploratory phase,
and I want to
talk a little bit about, kind of, what,
what, what
goes on underneath, and kind of what their
underlying basis is.
So,
if you look, suppose we have some matrix
data
here and I just generated some random
normal data
here using this code right here, and you
see
that the matrix that I plotted here using
the
image function, it's not particularly
interesting, it looks pretty
noisy and there's no real pattern as we
would
expect there, to not be, Now, I could just
run a hierarchical cluster analysis on
this data set.
I just, I can do an hierarchical, a
cluster
analysis on the rows of the data frame or
the rows of the matrix and the columns of
a matrix.
And I can do this using the heatmap
function very easily in R.
So when I run the heatmap function, you
can see that the cluster analysis
is done, I get the dendrograms printed on
both the columns and the rows.
But again, there's no real interesting
pattern that emerges, and
that's because there's no real interesting
pattern underlying in the data.
So so that's fine.
But now, what if we add a pattern to the
data set.
So let's try to add something and
I, I do it with this code here, with this
four loop here.
So I loop through all the rows, and on a
random row I
flip a coin, and if it turns out to be a
one I just
add a pattern, I just, so, so that five of
the columns have a
mean of zero, and another, and the other
five have a mean of three.
So, I just kind of add a little shift here
across the columns.
So now if I plot the data you see that
their at the
right, on the right hand five columns are
a little
bit more yellow which means that they have
a higher value
and in the left hand side five columns
which are, which
are little bit more red which means
they've a lower value.
That's because some of the rows have a
mean of three in the right hand side
and some of the rows only have a mean of
zero on the right hand side.
So, you can see there's an obvious kind of
step pattern there.
So now, if I do, if I run a higher, higher
group of cluster analysis on
the data, you can see that, that the
the two sets of columns are easily
separated out.
So you can see that the dendrogram on the
top
of the matrix which, which is right on the
columns.
I see it, it has, it clearly splits into
two clusters,
there's five on the left, and there's five
on the right.
On the rows, it's not so obvious, because
there's no real pattern that goes along
the rows.
And so that kind of get reorganized into
a random pattern and, and that's the
picture that emerges from the heat map.
Now, we can take a look at a closer look
at the patterns in the rows
and columns by looking at kind of the
marginal means of the, of the rows and
columns.
So for example I can look at ether the ten
different column
means or I can plot the 40 row means in
this matrix.
So here with this code, that's exactly
what I've done
on the left hand plot I've got the
original matrix data.
That's been kind of reor, that's been
reordered to
look according to the kind of hierarchical
cluster analysis of the, of the rose.
And and and I've plotted in the middle
plot here the mean for each of the rows.
If you look, on, on the y-axis I've got
the row number which goes from
one to 40, so that kind of is roughly
parallel with the image on the left.
And and on the x-axis I've got the mean of
that row.
So for example, you can see that for row
ten
the mean is roughly, you know, minus 0.25
or something like that.
And then for row 30 the mean is roughly
1.5.
And so we see that there's a clear shift
in the mean as you go across the rows.
Similarly, if you go across the columns,
you can see, across the
ten columns, there's a clear shift in the
mean of each column.
So the first ten columns have roughly a
mean of zero or close
to it and then the next ten columns have
roughly a mean of two because, there's a
shift there.
So using the plots on the, on the, in the
middle on the
right you can see a clear pattern, in the
rows and the columns there.
So, some related problems that, that so,
closer analysis are, is
useful for kind of identifying these types
of patterns, but we
can maybe take a little more, a slightly
more formal approach,
that kind of takes advantage of the matrix
structure of the data.
And so the base, there are two kinds of
problems you might want to look at and so
if
you have a lot of variables and we want,
we want to create a new set of variables
that
are uncorrelated and explain as much
variance as possible.
So the idea is that we have a lot of
different variables.
Suppose we have hundreds or maybe
thousands
or tens of thousands of variables in
our data set and the idea is
that they're not all independent
measurements of something.
Right?
So a lot of them will be related to each
other.
They will be correlated with each other.
So for example, you'll have two
measurements
that are like height and weight and so
those will obviously be related to each
other and so they're not all independent
kind
of like factors.
And you see the idea is that we want to
create a set of variables that is smaller
than the original set of variables that we
have and that are all uncorrelated with
each other.
So that they kind of represent different
types of variation in your data set.
And similarly, we want this reduced set of
variables to explain
as much of the variability in your data
set, as possible.
So another related problem is that if you
put all the variables together
in one matrix so like the matrix that we
showed in the image.
You want to find the best matrix that's
created with
fewer variables, the and, but still
explains the original data.
The idea is if you, the more technical
term is that you want to find
a lower rank matrix and that somehow
explains the, the original data reasonably
well.
So the first goal here is a statistical
one and it's,
it's a common problem that's solved by
the method of, of principle components
analysis.
And the second goal here is more of a kind
of data compression problem,
where you want to find a, a kind
of smaller representation of the original
data.
And one way to think about that problem is
with the singular value decomposition.
So the singular value decomposition can be
written in mathematical terms, in matrix
terms as if you have a matrix x where
each, the, all, we can think of each
column in this matrix as a variable or a,
a measurement And each row of
the matrix as an observation, so you might
have many, many observations for a given
metric.
So for example, the rows of your matrix
might represent individual people, and
each column would represent
a measurement on those people.
So for example, the first column might be
the
height, and the second column might be the
weight.
So then the idea is that if you have a
matrix x, that's formatted in this way
then the singular value
decomposition or the SVD is a matrix
decomposition that can,
where it, which decomposses the original
matrix into three separate matrixes.
One is U, one is called D and the other's
called V.
And so they, the column of U are
orthogonal
so they're, ind, they're kind of
independent of each other.
They're called the left singular vectors
and the columns of
V are also orthogonal and they're called
right singular vectors.
And then D is a diagonal matrix which
contains the singular values.
So that's the basic idea of the singular
valued composition.
We'll talk about these components a little
bit later on.
Principle components analysis, also
usually known as PCA,
is related, uses the single valued
composition as a related technique
And the basic idea is that if you were to
take
the original data matrix, and subtract the
mean of each column
from each, so subtract each, the column
mean from each column.
And divide by the column standard
deviation, and then, and
then run a SVD on that kind of
re-normalized matrix.
The principle components would be equal to
the right singular values
of the matrix, so the V matrix.