So one issue with either the SVD or
principal components analysis is miss, is
always missing values.
So real data will typically have missing
values, and the
problem is that if you try to run the SVD
on a data set that doesn't have or that
has
some missing values, like you see that
I've created here.
You can see that you get an error.
You just can't run it on a data set that
has missing values.
So you need to do something about the
missing values.
Before you run an SVD or a PCA.
So, one possibility and there are many
others though, is the,
use the impute package which is available
from the bioconductor project.
and, and just impute the missing datas,
sorry the missing data points and so
that you can have a value there, and then
you can run your SVD.
And so this approach you.
This code here uses the impute.knn
function which takes a, a missing row or
missing values in a row, and imputes it by
the k nearest neighbors to
that row.
So if k, for example, is five, then it
will
take the five rows that are closest to the
row with
the missing data, and then impute the data
in that
missing row with the kind of average of
the other five.
And so, once we've imputed the data with
this impute.knn function we can run the
svd.
You can see, it runs without error.
And we can, we can kind of plot the first
singular
vectors from each of them.
And so you can see that the on the left
hand side, I've got the,
the data, the, kind of the, the
first singular vector from the original
data matrix,
and the second, on the right-hand side,
I've got the, server singular vector from
the
data matrix that was in, that was kind of
where the missing data was imputed.
Now, you can see that they're roughly
similar.
They're not exactly the same, but the
imputation
didn't seem to have a major effect on
the on the running of the svd.
So
this is a final example here, it's just
kind of an interesting example.
I just want to show how you can take an
actual image, which is represented as a
matrix, and
kind of and, and, and kind of develop a
lower dimensional or lower rank
representation of this actual image.
So here's a picture of a face.
It's a relatively low resolution picture
of a face, but you can see that there
is a, you know, a nose and ears and two
eyes and a mouth there.
And so what we're going to do is we're
going to run the svd
on this face data and look at the variance
explained.
And so you can see that the first
singular vector explains about 40% of the
variation.
And then the second is about say 20 some
percent.
And then the third one is about maybe 15%.
And so if you look at say the first five
to ten singular
vectors they capture pretty much all of
the variation in the data set.
And so we can, we can see, we can actually
look at the image that's generated by say
the first
singular vector, or the first five, or the
first ten.
So so let's, so we can take a look at
that,
and so the idea that we're going to use a
little bit
of matrix multiplication here to create an
approximations of the space
that is, that uses fewer components than
the original data set too.
So here I'm creating one that just uses
the first principle component the first
singular vector.
I'm using one that takes the first five
altogether.
And then another one that takes the first
ten.
And, and so we can take a look at what
this approximation looks like.
So the first image here, which is all the
way
on the left here, just uses a single
singular vector.
And you can see that it's not a very good,
it's not a pretty picture so to speak.
There's not really a face there.
There's not much you can see.
But it's asking a lot to represent an
entire image using just a single vector.
So, if we move on to the second one from
the left, you
can see that basically most of the, of the
key features are already there.
So this uses the first five singular
vectors.
And you can see that clearly there's a
face.
There's two eyes, a nose, and a mouth, and
two ears.
It's not ha, as, not exactly the same
as the original data set, but it's pretty
close.
If you move on to the next picture, which
is
letter C, here, you can see that it's a
little bit,
kind of has a little bit more definition.
This is using the first ten pixel,
singular vectors.
And, but it's not very different from the
second one, which uses, only used five.
And then the very last one here on the
right is the original data set.
So, you can see that if you go, if you use
just a few, a singular vector, maybe up to
five or ten.
You can get a reasonable approximation of
this face without
having to kind of store all of the
original data.
So, this is an example
of a kind of data compression type of
approach.
that, that, the singular value
decomposition can can generate.
Now data compression and kind of
statistical summaries
are kind of two sides of the same coin.
And so if you want to summarize the data
set with the, with a,
with a smaller number of features the
singular value decomposition is also
useful for that.
So just a couple of notes and further
resources
for the singular value decomposition and
principle component analysis.
One of the issues is that the scale of
your data matters.
So if you have, for example, it's common
to
measure lot's of different variables that
come on different scales.
And that can cause a problem, because if
one
variable is much larger than another
variable, just because
the unit's so different that will tend to
drive
this, the principle components analysis
over the singular vectors.
And so that may not be particularly
meaningful to you.
And so you want to look at the, see that
the, kind of the
scale of the different columns or rows are
roughly comparable to each other.
the, as we saw in the, one of the, in the
example with the
two different patterns, the principle
components and
the singular vectors may mix together real
patterns.
And so, the patterns that you see may not
represent the kind of
separable patterns but they may be
patterns that may, that are mixed
together.
The singular value decomposition can be
computationally intensive if you have a
very large matrix so that's one, that's
something to keep in mind.
We use relatively small matrices here, but
of course computing power is getting ever
more
powerful and and there there are some
highly optimized and
specialized matrix libraries out there
for computing the singular value
decomposition.
And so this can be done on, on lots of
kind of practical problems.
Without too much kind of planning in
advance.
And so here are a couple links to kind of
further resources
for what, how to use principle
components analysis in the singular value
composition.
And, and also there are other kind
of approaches that are similar to this.
But are a kind of different in many of the
details.
You may hear about these approaches.
Things like factor analysis, independent
components analysis and latent semantic
analysis.
And these are worth exploring, but are
related to the, kind
of the basic ideas behind principle
components analysis and singular valued
decomposition.
Which is that you want to find the kind
of lower dimensional representation that
explains most of the variation
in the data that you see.