Hierarchical clustering is kind of a bread
and butter technique
when it comes to visualizing a high
dimensional or multidimensional data.
It's very simple to use.
The ideas are fairly intuitive for most
people,
and it kind of, can serve as a really
quick way to get a sense of what's going
on in a very high dimensional data set.
So, of course, like, like most clustering
techniques,
for example, like, k-means for example the
basic issue
that you have to deal with, you know, when
you define the method is,
how do we define when things are close
together and when things are far apart?
Because all clustering methods in some
sense try to tell you
when one thing is closer to another thing,
versus something else.
And so, for example, things that are, you
know, cluster are
closer to each other than they are to
elements of another cluster.
And so, we have to define what it means
to be close what it means to group things
together.
How do we group things together?
And then once we've got, we have a
distance
notion, we have, and we have a way of
grouping
things together, how do we visualize the,
you know,
the processing that we've done, the
calculation that we've done?
And how do we interpret you know, how the
grouping is put together?
Cluster analysis is a really important and
widely used technique.
It's a, if you just type cluster analysis
into
Google, there are literally millions of
results that come back.
And it's a widely applied method in all,
in many different areas of science and
other applications.
And so it's useful to know kind of how
these techniques work.
So, hierarchical clustering as, as is
denoted by the
title involves organizing your data into a
kind of hierarchy.
And, and the common approach is
what's called an aglomer, and aglomerative
approach.
And the idea, it was just kind of a bottom
up approach, so you
start with the data as kind of individual
data points, and you start lumping
them together into clusters until
eventually you have, you
know, your entire data set is just one big
cluster.
So you can imagine there's all these
little particles floating around,
and eventually you start kind of grouping
them together into little balls.
And then the balls get grouped up into
bigger balls, and
the bigger balls get grouped together into
one big massive cluster.
And so that's the kind of agglomerative
approach to clut,
to hierarchical clustering, and that's
what we're going to talk about here.
And so the basic idea is that you gotta
find the,
the two points in your data set that are
the closest together.
And then, you kind of merge them together
to
create one, you know, super-point, so that
the merged point
is not an actual point in your data set,
but
you can think of it as being a new point.
And then, you kind of remove your original
two data points,
and you substitute with that, or that kind
of, merged point.
And you kind of repeat this over and over
again.
So, then, you find the next two closest
things, and you put them together.
And then you, as you kind of, and then
once
you kind of put things together, you get
like a
little tree that you can show that
kind of, that
shows the ordering in which things were
put together.
And so this approach requires two
important things.
One is a distance metric.
So what is how do you calculate the
distance between two points?
And, the other thing that is required is
an approach for merging points.
So once you, once you've figured out, okay
well, these two points are the closest
how do you merge them together?
And so the nice thing that hierarchical
clustering produces is a, is a
tree which is sometimes called the
dendrogram
that shows how things are merged together.
And so the most important, arguably the
most
important question to really, to kind of
resolve
in a, in a hierarchical clustering
approach is
to define what do we mean by close.
Because if you have a definition that
doesn't
make sense for your problem then you just
get
garbage in, garbage out, right?
So you have a, a distance metric that
doesn't make
sense then the results that you get will
be relatively meaningless.
So there are a few examples of distance
metrics that are used out there.
Probably the most kind of familiar
distance metric is the Euclidean distance,
which is just kind of the straight-line
distance between any two points.
A kind of analogous distance metric is the
correlation between two points, or the
correlation similarity.
And then another metric is the binary
distance or, or the Manhattan distance,
and I'll, we'll talk a little bit about
what that means in a second.
So you have to make, you have to pick a
distance metric that's, makes
sense for your problem so that you can
produce results that also make sense.
And so, here's Euclidean distance, a
simple diagram.
So if you take two cities, for example,
Baltimore and D.C., or Washington D.C.,
then if you map, put them on a, on a, on a
map for example.
And there's, there's, so, you can imagine
that the center
of each city has an X and a Y coordinate.
And you want to say map the distance
between the two centers of the two cities.
well, you can draw a straight diagonal
line between the two cities.
And then, the you can calculate the
distance, kind of, in the usual way.
And the distance is going to be a function
of the difference
in the x coordinates and the difference in
the y coordinates.
So to calculate the Euclidian distance you
take the distance you know, in the x
coordinates, you square it, you take the
difference
in the y coordinates and you square it.
You add the two squares together, you take
the square root.
That's the classical definition of
Euclidian distance.
And so you can imagine, you know, in real
life, it'd be like
if a bird were to fly from DC to
Baltimore, they would just fly
straight from one city to another, they
could, because they can fly in
the air and they're not impeded by things
like roads or mountains, or whatever.
And so
that's the straight line distance between
two cities.
Whether that makes sense for you depends
on
you know, whether you're a bird or
something else.
And so you have to think about kind of
that in the context of your problem.
Now Euclidean distance is easily
generalizable to higher dimensions.
But even if you have, you know, instead
here we
just have two dimension, but if you have
100 dimensions, you
can easily take the difference between
100, each of the dimensions,
square it, sum it together and then take
the square root.
So it's a very nice type
kind of, it, it extends very naturally to
very high dimensions problems.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The Manhattan distance gets its name from
the idea that, you know, you can, you
can look at points on a kind of a grid or
a city block grid.
Think or imagine you're in the city of
Manhattan in New York.
And you want to get from one point to
another.
So you can look at the two black circles
on this diagram.
And if you want to get from one point to
another,
if you're in a city, you know, in a city
block, you can't just go directly from one
point to
another, because there'd be all these
buildings in the way, or
you'd have to follow the streets.
And so in the streets, because they're in
a grid,
you can either go up or down, or left or
right.
The green line here in that case would
represent the Euclidean distance which
would be like if,
you know, if you were a bird, and you
wanted to fly over everything, across the
two points.
But as a person walking on the ground, you
have to take either the red line,
the blue line, or the yellow line, or
any other, kind of, kind of pattern in
between.
The point is that you'd have to travel
along
the city blocks.
And so, the distance that you would travel
along the city blocks here, in the
gray, kind of, you can imagine the gray
lines as the streets, that's the Manhattan
distance.
And it, it can written formulaically as
the,
as the absolute sum of all the different
coordinates.
So if you have two coordinates, you know,
and you
sum the distance that you travel in the X
dimension,
and then you sum, and then the distance,
the absolute
value of the distance you travel in the Y
direction.
And so the Manhattan distance can be
useful in some contexts, and, and so and,
because it more, it may, in some contexts,
more accurately represent the distance
between two points.
In particular, in a city like Manhattan,
two points may be very far apart.
Even if they, you know, if they seem
relatively
close, you know, in a, in a Euclidean
distance sense.