So the cluster dendogram that's produced
by default in R is relatively nice, but
it, it is, there is possible to kind of
make it a little bit nicer.
So this myplclust function which is
available on the
course website, you can download it
straight from there.
And once you source it into R.
You can get this function which in
turn, produces a cluster dendrogram, but
then all
the, the, the points in the individual
clusters are A, labeled by their cluster
label.
And B, they are
colored in separately, so you can see
cluster one is labeled with all ones.
And it's and it's they're, they're colored
black.
Cluster two is colored red and cluster
three is colored green.
So of course, in order to do this, you
have to determine, you have to specify the
how many clusters there are before you can
actually
you know, label them one, two, and three,
etc.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now you can go to the RGraphGallery to see
some kind of more
interesting cluster diagrams and, and to
look
at some software that people have used.
To create really nice clustering diagrams.
So if you want to look at some, for
example, this cluster dendrogram which has
labels on the, on the leaf nodes, and it's
colored each of the groups.
It's added a little bit of other
information.
You can take a look at this gallery, which
a lot of other really nice plots on it
too.
So, the other i, issue when it comes to
using hierarchical clustering is how do
you merge points together?
And so the question is, you know, when
you, when you, when
you, when you merge a point together what,
what represents its new location.
And so one is called average, so average
linkage.
And the idea is that if you take two
points and their new com,
coordinate location, it's just the average
of
their x coordinates and their y
coordinates.
So it's kind of like the roughly the
center
of gravity or the middle of tat group of
points, now that seems logical and it can,
and it can, it will, it will lead to a
kind of certain type of clustering result.
[NOISE] The other type of, of approach is
called complete linkage and there the
idea is that if you want to measure the
distance between two clusters of points.
Then you take the farthest two points from
each, from the two clusters, as the
distance.
So for example, in this picture, if you
look
at the upper cluster, and the kind of
lower
left cluster, the distance between those
two clusters is
the equal to the distance between the two
farthest points.
And so that gives you the kind of complete
linkage approach.
The average linkage, of course, gives you
the distance between the two centers of
gravity.
So that's the difference between the two
pluses here.
So you can see that in the complete
linkage example
that distance is relatively far.
Where as in the average linkage example
the distance is somewhat shorter.
And so, it's not like there is one right
or one wrong way to do it.
But the point is to show that each of
the, the two different merging approaches
can get to,
give you very different results and so
it's is
useful to try, it's often useful to try
both approaches.
To see what kind of clustering results you
get, in
the end and whether one set makes more
sense than another.
The last function I want to highlight here
is the heatmap
function which is a really nice function
for visualizing matrix data.
So if you have an extremely large table or
a,
a large matrix of numbers that are kind of
similarly scaled,
and you want to, just take a look at them
really
quickly in an organized way, you can call
the heatmap function.
And what the heat map function does is
essentially runs a hierarchical
cluster analysis on the rows of the table
and on the columns of
the table.
So think, on the.
So if you can imagine the, the you know,
rows of the table are like observations.
And then it runs a cluster analysis on the
rows of the table.
And then, think of the columns of the, of
the table as, as sets of observations.
Even if they're not actually observations.
The columns, for example, might be
variables or something like that.
But think of them as just different
observations.
You can write a cluster
analysis on that, too.
And the idea with the heatmap function
is that it uses the hierarchical
clustering function
to organize the rows and the columns of
the tables so that you can visualize them.
You can visualize kind of groups or blocks
of observations within the table using the
image function.
So, what it does is it creates a image
plot here, and and it
reorders the columns and the rows of
the table according to the hierarchical
clustering algorithm.
So here you can see that for example,
along the rows I've got this
hierarchical, this cluster dendogram which
shows that
there are probably you know, three
clusters.
And those clusters, rows are all grouped
together.
And then there are only two columns in the
data frame.
So it's not particularly interesting to do
a hierarchical cluster analysis on that.
But if you had many,many columns, you
know,
you would reorganize the columns so that
we,
they would be kind of, the closer ones
would be closer together, and the farther
ones would
be farther apart.
And so, the heatmap function is really
useful for kind of, or,
as a very quickly visualizing this kind of
high dimensional table data.
So this is summarize what for heirarchical
clustering.
It's a really useful technique for looking
at high-dimensional data.
It organizes the data in a kind of logical
and intuitive way and partic, in
particular, functions like
the heatmap function are, are really
useful for kind
of looking, for quickly looking at table
or matrix data.
And so, of course, you need to know, you
need to define a
notion of what it means for two points to
be close or far apart.
And you have to have a
merging strategy.
So we talked about complete linkage and
average linkage.
So given those two things, you can run,
the hierarchical
clustering algorithm will run, and it will
produce a cluster dendrogram,
which shows you kind of how the merging is
done, or
how the, how the points got merged
together through the algorithm.
So one of, a couple of issues when it
comes to, hierarchical clustering.
And this is often true for many clustering
algorithms.
Is that the, the clustering picture may be
unstable.
And so, for example, if a few points were
to change.
Or, for example, if you have some
outliers.
Then the clustering, if you were to remove
those points.
Or modify them a little bit.
Then the clustering dendogram or whatever
the
final products might be, could change a
lot.
And so you have to be sensitive to that
possibility.
So you might, so the, often the use, a
useful thing is to try different
metrics, distance metrics, to make sure
it's not to see how sensitive it is to
the different distance metrics.
Maybe change emerging strategy to see what
kind of
picture emer, comes out if you change
merging strategy.
And also clustering algorithms could be
sensitive to the scalings of
a given variable, so you might, if, if one
variable, for
example, is, is measured on with units
that are much larger
than another variable then that can
sometimes throw off the algorithm.
So, it may be useful to scale certain
variables so that they're more comparable
to each other.
One nice thing about hierarchical
clustering, at
least the algorithm as discussed here, is
that it is deterministic so there's no
random starting point, there's no
randomness in it.
If you run it once, it will run, and with
the same
parameters and the same data, it will give
you the same picture.
Of course, a key question in any
clustering approach is the, is where to
cut.
And the general idea is, you know,
determining how many clusters there are.
It's not always obvious
to figure out how many clusters there are.
And, and so, but there are a number of
algorithms
that has been proposed, to try to figure
that out.
But I think the best use of hierarchical
clustering is
probably just for exploratory analysis and
just for looking at
your data, visualizing your data, getting
a sense of what
patterns are there, if there are any
patterns at all.
And then, you can kind of take these ideas
and formalize them later in a more
sophisticated models.
So I give you some links, the kind of more
details
about these approaches.
And I encourage you to take a look at them
to explore further.